<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Alzheimers Res Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Alzheimers Res Ther</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Alzheimer's Research &#x00026; Therapy</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1758-9193</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22849569</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3506945</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">alzrt134</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/alzrt134</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Increased expression of the homologue of enhancer-of-split 1 protects neurons from beta amyloid neurotoxicity and hints at an alternative role for transforming growth factor beta1 as a neuroprotector</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Chac&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>Pedro J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>pedro.chacon@cabimer.es</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-T&#x000e9;bar</surname><given-names>Alfredo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>alfredo.rodriguez@cabimer.es</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Centro Andaluz de Biolog&#x000ed;a Molecular y Medicina Regenerativa (CABIMER), Americo Vespucio s/n, Isla de la Cartuja, 41092 Seville, Spain</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9;2012 Chac&#x000f3;n and Rodr&#x000ed;guez-T&#x000e9;bar; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Chac&#x000f3;n and Rodr&#x000ed;guez-T&#x000e9;bar; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://alzres.com/content/4/4/31"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Alzheimer's disease (AD) is a neurodegenerative disorder characterized by the deposition of &#x003b2;-amyloid (A&#x003b2;) in the brain, which produces progressive neuronal loss and dementia. We recently demonstrated that the noxious effects of A&#x003b2; on cultured hippocampal neurons are in part provoked by the antagonism of nerve growth factor (NGF) signalling, which impairs the activation of nuclear factor &#x003ba;B (NF-&#x003ba;B) by impeding the tyrosine phosphorylation of I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;. As a result, the expression of the homologue of Enhancer-of split 1 (<italic>Hes1</italic>) gene is downregulated and ultimately, gamma-aminobutyric acid (GABA)-ergic connectivity is lost.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p><italic>Hes1 </italic>activity was promoted in cultured hippocampal neurons by overexpressing a <italic>Hes1</italic>-encoding plasmid or by upregulating this gene by activating NF-&#x003ba;B through different approaches (overexpressing either the I-&#x003ba;B kinase&#x003b2;, or p65/RelA/NF-&#x003ba;B). Alternatively neurons were exposed to TGF&#x003b2;1. Dendrite patterning, GABAergic connectivity and cell survival were analyzed by immunofluorescence microscopy. <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression was determined by real-time PCR. NF-&#x003ba;B activation was measured using the dual-luciferase reporter assay.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The expression of <italic>Hes1 </italic>abolished the effects of A&#x003b2; on dendritic patterning and GABAergic input, and it prevented the death of the cultured neurons. TGF&#x003b2;1, a known neuroprotector, could counteract the deleterious effects of A&#x003b2; by inducing NF-&#x003ba;B activation following the serine phosphorylation of I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;. Indeed, the number of GABAergic terminals generated by inducing <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression was doubled.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our data define some of the mechanisms involved in A&#x003b2;-mediated cell death and they point to potential means to counteract this noxious activity.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>The amyloid hypothesis considers amyloid beta (A&#x003b2;) as the principal agent underlying the various manifestations of Alzheimer's disease (AD). Accordingly, most therapeutic approaches for AD treatment target the A&#x003b2; peptide, which induces the formation of amyloid deposits in the brain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. These strategies attempt to limit A&#x003b2; production and fibril formation, or to increase A&#x003b2; clearance from brain deposits. This latter approach has been the focus of much investigation, with active and passive methods to immunize against A&#x003b2; effectively reducing brain A&#x003b2; content. However, this reduction in amyloid content has not been conclusively associated with improvements in cognitive performance or a slowing in the progression of AD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>].</p><p>An alternative approach to AD therapy involves interfering with the signals transduced by A&#x003b2; to offset neuronal deterioration and death. While neuronal A&#x003b2; signaling pathways have been studied extensively, many of the underlying mechanisms remain elusive. Several studies have related A&#x003b2; neurotoxicity with NGF neurotrophy and indeed, some current therapeutic approaches for AD involve the use of NGF or other compounds that mimic its effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. The cellular and molecular bases underlying the antagonism of NGF by A&#x003b2; have been described recently, at least in part. Accordingly, A&#x003b2; competes with nerve growth factor (NGF) binding to p75<sup>NTR </sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>], thereby preventing the activation of NF-&#x003ba;B by impairing the tyrosine phosphorylation and the subsequent degradation of I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. The inhibition of nuclear factor kappa-B (NF-&#x003ba;B) mediated by A&#x003b2; results in the downregulation of the <italic>enhancer of split homolog 1 </italic>(<italic>Hes1</italic>) gene, which is known to influence dendrite patterning and gamma-aminobutyric acid (GABA)-ergic inputs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].</p><p>We recently reported that A&#x003b2; impairs the initial steps of NGF signalling at the level of RhoA GTPase and protein tyrosine phosphatase 1B (PTP1B) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Furthermore, we demonstrated that potentiation of NGF signalling (for example, by inhibiting RhoA GTPase and activating PTP1B) confers neuronal resistance to A&#x003b2; neurotoxicity. In the present study, we explored alternative means of activating NF-&#x003ba;B and promoting <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression. We found that overexpression of I-&#x003ba;&#x003b2; kinase (IKK&#x003b2;) a kinase that phosphorylates I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; (an NF-&#x003ba;B inhibitor), p65/RelA or <italic>Hes1 </italic>abolished the effects of A&#x003b2; on dendritic patterning, GABAergic input and the survival of cultured hippocampal neurons. Furthermore, administration of transforming growth factor &#x003b2;1 (TGF&#x003b2;1) produced similar effects, augmenting <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression and GABAergic input, and conferring resistance to A&#x003b2; toxicity. These results further our understanding of A&#x003b2; toxicity in AD and they open new perspectives for AD treatment using anti-amyloid approaches.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Antibodies</title><p>The following primary antibodies were used for immunocytochemistry: rabbit anti-enhanced green fluorescent protein (EGFP, 1:500: Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA), chicken anti-EGFP (1:500: Chemicon, Hampshire, UK), mouse anti-Myc (1:400: Roche Applied Science, Mannheim, Germany), mouse anti-FLAG (1:500: Sigma-Aldrich, Madrid, Spain) and rabbit anti-vesicular inhibitory amino acid transporter (VIAAT, 1:400: Chemicon). The following secondary antibodies were used: goat anti-rabbit Cy<sup>2 </sup>(1:1000), goat anti-mouse Cy<sup>3 </sup>(1:1000), goat anti-rabbit Cy<sup>3 </sup>(1:1000) and goat-anti mouse Cy<sup>5 </sup>(1:500: all from Jackson Immuno Research, West Grove, USA), and goat anti-chicken Alexa-fluor 488 (1:1000: Invitrogen).</p></sec><sec><title>Amyloid &#x003b2; preparation and characterization</title><p>Amyloid &#x003b2; (1-42) was purchased from NeoMPS (Strasbourg, France) and to obtain oligomeric forms, the peptide was dissolved in 1,1,1,3,3,3-hexafluoro-2-propanol and the solution was allowed to evaporate for 2 h at room temperature. The peptide film was dissolved in dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO), sonicated in a water bath for 10 minutes and diluted to 100 &#x003bc;M in PBS. This solution was then briefly vortexed and incubated overnight at 4&#x000b0;C. Aliquots were stored at -20&#x000b0;C. Our A&#x003b2; preparations were resolved by 12% Bis-Tris gel electrophoresis and electrotransferred to polyvinylidene difluoride (PVDF) membranes, which were probed with a mouse monoclonal anti-&#x003b2; Amyloid antibody (clone BAM-10, diluted 1:2,000: Sigma Aldrich). After further incubation with an horseradish peroxidise (HRP)-conjugated anti-mouse antibody (1:10,000: Jackson Immuno Research, West Grove, USA), immunoreactive Ab species were visualised by chemiluminiscence. This analysis revealed that most A&#x003b2; forms were monomeric and dimeric with a less prominent trimeric and tetrameric component (Figure S1A in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>). To kill neurons in culture, a concentration of 5 &#x003bc;M was established empirically (Figure S1B in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Other chemicals</title><p>Recombinant TGF&#x003b2;1 was purchased from Preprotech EC LTD (London, UK). The cell-permeable NF-&#x003ba;B inhibitor peptide SN-50 and its inactive control, SN-50M, were obtained from Calbiochem (Darmstadt, Germany).</p></sec><sec><title>Expression vectors for neuronal transfection</title><p>EGFP-expressing vector (pEGFP-N1) was obtained from Biosciences/Clontech (Palo Alto, CA, USA). Vectors expressing the wild type (wt) forms of IKK&#x003b1; (pCDNA-HA-IKK&#x003b1;) and IKK&#x003b2; (pRK5cFLAG-IKK&#x003b2;) were kindly provided by Lisardo Bosc&#x000e1; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. Vectors encoding mutant forms of I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; (3XFLAG-pCMV-I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;S32/36A and 3XFLAG-pCMV-I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;Y42F) were described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. A FLAG-tagged vector encoding p65/RelA (pCMV-Tag1-p65) was kindly provided by Mayte Coiras [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Vectors encoding <italic>Hes1 </italic>(pCLIG-Hes1) and <italic>Hes6 </italic>(pIRES-Hes6) were kindly provided by Ryoichiro Kageyama [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] and Phil Jones [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>], respectively. Myc-tagged forms of Hes1 and Hes6 were obtained by inserting the corresponding cDNA encoding sequence from previous vectors into the NcoI/EcoRI and NcoI/StuI sites of the pCS2+MT vector.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell culture</title><p>Primary hippocampal neuronal cultures were prepared as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>], with some modifications. Briefly, hippocampi were dissected from embryonic day 17 (E17) CD1 mouse foetuses and dissociated into single cells following trypsin digestion (Worthington, Lakewood, USA) and DNase I treatment (Roche Applied Science). Neurons were plated on glass coverslips or in plastic dishes coated with poly-L-lysine (Sigma-Aldrich, Madrid, Spain), and then cultured in Neurobasal A supplemented with 2 mM GlutaMAX I, 100 units/mL penicillin and 100 &#x003bc;g/mL streptomycin (Gibco BRL, Crewe, UK). After 7 days <italic>in vitro </italic>(DIV) the neurons were exposed to either TGF&#x003b2;1 or A&#x003b2;.</p></sec><sec><title>Neuronal transfection</title><p>For fluorescence immunocytochemistry, cultured neurons (7 days <italic>in vitro</italic>, DIV) were transfected with different vectors using the Effectene Transfection Reagent (Qiagen GmbH, Hilden, Germany) according to the manufacturer's instructions, with some modifications. Briefly, 0.6 &#x003bc;g of DNA was added to 120 &#x003bc;l of EC buffer and 3.5 &#x003bc;L of enhancer, and then left for 5 minutes at room temperature before 10 &#x003bc;L of Effectene was added. After 15 minutes incubation at room temperature, the final solution was added to a 35 mm cell culture dish containing hippocampal neurons, for 3 h before the medium was changed. Less than 0.5% of the neurons were transfected in each dish, permitting the morphology of the neurons to be analyzed without the interference of neighboring labeled neurons. To determine <italic>Hes1 </italic>mRNA, 300,000 neurons were transfected with different vectors using Lipofectamine LTX (Invitrogen), following the protocol recommended by the manufacturer. The rate of transfection was 20-25% of the total number of cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunocytochemistry, image acquisition and morphometric analysis of labeled hippocampal neurons</title><p>Neurons were fixed for 30 minutes in 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) in PBS 18 h after transfection, permeabilized for 15 minutes at room temperature with 0.5% Triton X-100 in PBS and blocked with 10% goat serum in PBS containing 0.1% Triton X-100. The neurons were then incubated with the primary and secondary antibodies. To verify that the labeling was caused specifically by the primary antibodies, it was either omitted or replaced by similarly diluted normal serum from the same species.</p><p>Our methods for the evaluation of dendritic morphology and presynaptic terminal identification in dissociated cell cultures have been described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Briefly, labeled neurons were visualized by standard epifluorescence under a Plan-Neofluar 63&#x000d7; oil objective with a numerical aperture of 1.3 (Zeiss, Oberkochen, Germany). Terminal counts and analysis of dendrite morphology were performed manually. A circular region of interest (ROI) with a diameter of 50 &#x003bc;m was projected onto the EGFP-labeled neuron, its centre roughly coinciding with the centre of the soma. The dendrite length was expressed as the number of dendritic trees that exceeded the limit of the ROI (number of dendrites &#x0003e; 50 &#x003bc;m). In co-transfection experiments, only double-labeled cells were analysed, representing &#x0003e; 90% of the single-labeled cells. Synaptic terminals in contact with an EGFP-labeled neuron were identified by single immunofluorescence, when an antibody against VIAAT was used.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell survival</title><p>After treatment, neurons were fixed for 30 minutes in 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) in PBS and the nuclei were immunostained with the fluorescent dye 4',6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI: Sigma-Aldrich). Non-viable neurons were recognized by nuclear condensation and/or fragmented chromatin. In two independent experiments, the number of viable neurons was counted in triplicate in approximately 50 fields. In co-transfection experiments, only the nuclei of double-labeled cells were analysed.</p></sec><sec><title>Quantitative real time polymerase chain reaction (PCR)</title><p>After treatments, total RNA was extracted from cultures at 7 DIV using the Illustra RNAspin Mini kit (GE-Healthcare, Piscataway, NJ, USA) and first strand cDNA was prepared from the RNA using the First Strand Synthesis kit according to the manufacturer's instructions (Fermentas GmbH, St Leon-Rot, Germany). Quantitative PCR was performed using the ABI Prism 7000 Sequence Detector (Applied Biosystems, Weiterstadt, Germany). TaqMan probes and primers for <italic>Hes1 </italic>and the housekeeping gene <italic>GADPH </italic>(as a control) were selected as the Assay-on-Demand gene expression products (Applied Biosystems). All TaqMan probes were labeled with 6-carboxy fluorescein (FAM) and real time PCR was performed using the TaqMan Universal PCR Master Mix according to the manufacturer's instructions. <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression was normalized to <italic>GAPDH </italic>expression.</p></sec><sec><title>Analysis of reporter gene activity</title><p>For reporter gene studies, 12-well plates (Becton Dickinson) containing 200,000 hippocampal neurons were transfected using the Lipofectamine LTX (Invitrogen) transfection reagent according to the manufacturer's instructions. Transfection efficiency ranged from 20 to 25% in control experiments, as revealed by co-transfection with pEGFP-N1 (Biosciences/Clontech). Cells were co-transfected with 0.5 &#x003bc;g/well of a plasmid containing five tandem repeats of the &#x003ba;B enhancer element upstream of the coding sequence of firefly-luciferase (pNF-&#x003ba;B-luc; Clontech), along with 0.1 &#x003bc;g of a plasmid encoding Renilla-luciferase (phRL-TK-luc: Promega, Madison, WI) as a transfection control for normalization in dual-luciferase assays. Dual-Luficerase reporter assays were performed according to the manufacturer's recommendations (Promega).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The data are presented as the mean &#x000b1; standard error of the mean (SEM). Unpaired Student's <italic>t</italic>-tests were used to determine the significance, denoted as *<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.01, and ***<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.001. All experiments were repeated at least twice.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Hes1 in neuronal morphology, connectivity and survival</title><p>Earlier studies revealed that <italic>Hes1 </italic>mediates the effects of NGF on neuronal morphology and connectivity. NGF increases both dendrite length and GABAergic connectivity in cultured hippocampal neurons, effects that are abrogated by overexpression of Hes6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], a natural inhibitor of Hes1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. We transfected a <italic>Hes1</italic>-expressing vector into cultured hippocampal neurons and analyzed the effects on dendrite morphology and synaptic connectivity. Overexpression of <italic>Hes1 </italic>increased the length of primary dendrites while decreasing their number (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A, B</xref>), and it enhanced GABAergic connectivity, as evident by immunostaining for VIAAT-positive clusters (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>). Interestingly, <italic>Hes1 </italic>transfection of neurons protected these cells from the neurotoxic effects of A&#x003b2;. Indeed, while oligomerization of A&#x003b2; (Figure S1A in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>) decreased the length and increased the number of primary dendrites, albeit decreasing GABAergic input, these effects were completely reversed by <italic>Hes1 </italic>transfection (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A, B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>). Moreover, <italic>Hes1 </italic>overexpression attenuated the effects of A&#x003b2; on neuronal survival. Using a concentration of 5 &#x003bc;M A&#x003b2;(1-42) in these studies to ensure that most cells would die during the experiment (performed over 90 h (Figure S1B in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>), prior transfection with <italic>Hes1 </italic>rescued 50% of neurons from this A&#x003b2;-induced death (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref>). Taken together, these findings demonstrate that optimal expression of <italic>Hes1 </italic>counteracts the effects of A&#x003b2; on neurons at all the levels examined here.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold><italic>Hes1 </italic>overexpression blocked the effects of amyloid beta (A&#x003b2;) on the morphology, GABAergic connectivity and survival of cultured hippocampal neurons</bold>. (<bold>A-C</bold>) E17 hippocampal neurons were plated at a density of 40,000 cells/cm<sup>2 </sup>and cultured for 7 days <italic>in vitro </italic>(DIV). Neurons were treated with A&#x003b2; (5 &#x003bc;M), and/or they were co-transfected with enhanced green fluorescent protein (EGFP) and a myc-tagged <italic>Hes1 </italic>vector for 16 h. The cells were fixed and labeled with anti-EGFP, anti-myc and anti- vesicular inhibitory amino acid transporter (VIAAT) antibodies, and examined by immunofluorescence. (<bold>A</bold>) Representative micrographs of cultured neurons under different conditions. Nuclear labeling (in purple) corresponds to myc-tagged <italic>Hes1</italic>. Punctuated red dots correspond to VIAAT immunostaining. Lower panels show the boxed regions at higher magnification. (<bold>B</bold>) Morphometric analysis was performed as indicated in Materials and methods. Note that A&#x003b2; decreased the length of primary dendrites (left panel) and increased their number (right panel), whereas <italic>Hes1 </italic>induced opposite effects, counteracting those of A&#x003b2;. (<bold>C</bold>) <italic>Hes1 </italic>overexpression increased the number of GABAergic terminals in cultured neurons, overriding the decrease induced by A&#x003b2; administration. (<bold>D</bold>) 7 DIV neurons (30,000 cells/cm<sup>2</sup>) were treated with A&#x003b2; (5 &#x003bc;M). Two days later the neurons were co-transfected with EGFP and the myc-tagged <italic>Hes1 </italic>vector, and the cells were stained with anti-EGFP, anti-myc antibodies and 4',6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI) on the following day. EGFP and myc dual-labeled cells with intact nuclei were counted. Approximately 50% of transfected neurons survived A&#x003b2; treatment. *<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.01, and ***<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt134-1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Activation of NF-&#x003ba;B blocks the effects of A&#x003b2; on neuronal morphology and connectivity</title><p>Having previously revealed that NGF augments <italic>Hes1 </italic>by activating NF-&#x003ba;B [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], the link between NF-&#x003ba;B activation and <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression was confirmed here using an alternative experimental approach. Cultured hippocampal neurons were transfected with a plasmid expressing p65/RelA, and <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression was assessed by quantitative PCR. Although only 20 to 25% of neurons were transfected, a significant increase (35 to 40%) in <italic>Hes1 </italic>mRNA was evident throughout the culture (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>). Transfected, myc-tagged p65/RelA was predominantly found in the nucleus, as expected given its capacity to promote <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). Moreover, p65/RelA overexpression produced marked changes in dendrite arborisation, increasing the length and decreasing the number of primary dendrites (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). These effects were paralleled by a substantial increase in GABAergic connectivity (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B, D</xref>) concomitant with an increase in <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). As seen following <italic>Hes1 </italic>transfection, p65/RelA transfection blocked the effects of A&#x003b2; on both dendrite morphology and connectivity, preventing the increase in dendrite length and the decrease in dendrite number induced by A&#x003b2; (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A, B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>). Indeed, p65/RelA overexpression also prevented the decrease in VIAAT-positive terminals induced by A&#x003b2;. The anti-amyloid effects of p65/RelA overexpression on neuronal survival could not be studied, as p65/RelA overexpression induced neuronal death two days after transfection (that is, before A&#x003b2; had noxious effects on cultured neurons).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Transfection of p65/RelA promoted Hes1 expression and counteracted the effects of amyloid beta (A&#x003b2;) on the morphology and GABAergic connectivity of cultured hippocampal neurons</bold>. (<bold>A</bold>) 7 days <italic>in vitro </italic>(DIV) neurons (300,000 cells) were transfected with a plasmid encoding myc-tagged p65/RelA. After 16 h, the cells were lysed and processed for real time-PCR, showing that <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression levels increased by 35%. (<bold>B-D</bold>) Cultured hippocampal neurons (40,000 cells/cm<sup>2</sup>, 7 DIV) were co-transfected with enhanced green fluorescent protein (EGFP) and myc-p65/RelA plasmids, treated with A&#x003b2; (5 &#x003bc;M) and incubated for a further 16 h, before analyzing dendritic patterning (<bold>B, C</bold>) and GABAergic connectivity (<bold>B, D</bold>). (<bold>B</bold>) Representative micrographs of 7 DIV hippocampal neurons treated with A&#x003b2; and/or transfected with p65/RelA. EGFP immunostaining (green) and the transfected p65/RelA mostly located to the nucleus (purple). Vesicular inhibitory amino acid transporter (VIAAT) was evident as punctuated red dots. Lower panels show the boxed regions at higher magnification. (<bold>C</bold>) Morphometric analysis of treated neurons. p65/RelA overexpression increased the length (left panel) but decreased the number (right panel) of primary dendrites, thereby counteracting the effects of A&#x003b2;. (<bold>D</bold>) p65/RelA overexpression increased the number of GABAergic terminals in cultured neurons and overrode the decrease in GABAergic terminals produced by A&#x003b2;. *<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.01, and ***<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt134-2"/></fig></sec><sec><title>IKK&#x003b2; activation counteracts the effects of beta-amyloid</title><p>NGF was shown to activate NF-&#x003ba;B via tyrosine phosphorylation and the subsequent degradation of I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. The canonical NF-&#x003ba;B activation pathway involves Ser(32,36) phosphorylation of I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; catalysed by the IKKs, and hence we tested whether increased activity of IKK proteins conferred amyloid resistance to cultured neurons. When cultured hippocampal neurons were transfected with a plasmid overexpressing IKK&#x003b2;, again only 20 to 25% of neurons were transfected (data not shown). Nonetheless, the levels of Hes1 mRNA increased significantly (25 to 30%) throughout the entire culture (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>). As expected, IKK&#x003b2; overexpression produced similar alterations in neuronal morphology as <italic>Hes1 </italic>or p65/RelA transfection (longer and fewer dendrites) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). In addition, IKK&#x003b2; transfection conferred hippocampal neurons with resistance to A&#x003b2; (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>, left panel). These effects were specific to IKK&#x003b2; as transfection with IKK&#x003b1; produced no noticeable changes in dendrites (not shown) and conferred only very modest resistance to A&#x003b2; neurotoxicity (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>, right panel).</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>I-&#x003ba;B kinase (IKK-&#x003b2;) induces <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression, modulates dendritic morphology and neuronal survival, and it counteracts amyloid beta (A&#x003b2;) activity</bold>. (<bold>A</bold>) The efficiency of transfecting 7 days <italic>in vitro </italic>(DIV) cultured neurons (300,000 cells) with a vector expressing Flag-tagged IKK&#x003b2; was 20-25%. After 16 h, the cells were lysed and <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression was quantified by real time PCR, and transfection of IKK&#x003b2; increased <italic>Hes-1 </italic>mRNA levels by 35%. (<bold>B</bold>) Hippocampal neurons were cultured for 7 DIV (40,000 cells/cm<sup>2</sup>), treated with A&#x003b2; (5 &#x003bc;M), and/or co-transfected with enhanced fluorescent green protein (EGFP) and FLAG-tagged IKK-&#x003b2; for 16 h. Transfection with IKK&#x003b2; increased the length (left panel) but decreased the number (right panel) of primary dendrites, and blocked the effect of A&#x003b2; on dendrite morphology. (<bold>C</bold>) 7 DIV hippocampal neurons (30,000 cells/cm<sup>2</sup>) were cultured for 7 days and then treated with A&#x003b2; (5 &#x003bc;M). Two days later, the neurons were co-transfected with EGFP, FLAG-tagged IKK&#x003b2; and/or HA-tagged IKK&#x003b1; and the number of live cells was determined on the following day. IKK&#x003b2; transfection rescued about 50% of neurons from A&#x003b2;-induced death (left panel), whereas this rescue was more modest when neurons were transfected with IKK&#x003b1; rather than IKK&#x003b2; (right panel). *<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.01, and ***<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt134-3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Effects of TGF&#x003b2;1 on neuronal morphology, connectivity and survival</title><p>Based on the changes observed in dendrite morphology, and in neuronal connectivity and survival following <italic>Hes1 </italic>overexpression, we investigated the effects of an alternative means of activating NF-&#x003ba;B using the cytokine TGF&#x003b2;1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. The role of TGF&#x003b2;1 in neuronal polarity and axonal specification has been studied previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>], and while TGF&#x003b2;1-3 promote dendrite growth in retinal ganglion cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>], the effects of TGF&#x003b2; on neuronal plasticity remain unclear. We first studied the effects of TGF&#x003b2;1 on dendritic patterning in cultured hippocampal neurons after 7 DIV. Exposure to TGF&#x003b2;1 increased the number of primary dendrites while decreasing the number of remaining dendrites (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). Moreover, GABAergic connectivity was augmented in cultured hippocampal neurons treated with TGF&#x003b2;1, as revealed by VIAAT immunostaining (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>, right panel). Varicosities containing VIAAT also increased upon TGF&#x003b2;1 administration. The effects of TGF&#x003b2;1 were mediated by <italic>Hes1 </italic>as TGF&#x003b2;1 had no such activity in neurons transfected with the <italic>Hes1 </italic>inhibitor <italic>Hes6 </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Impairment of <italic>Hes1 </italic>also prevented TGF&#x003b2;1 from altering dendrite patterning and GABAergic connectivity.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Transforming growth factor &#x003b2;1 (TGF&#x003b2;1) controls dendrite morphology and neuronal connectivity via I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; and <italic>Hes1</italic></bold>. Hippocampal neurons (7 days <italic>in vitro </italic>(DIV), 40,000 cells/cm<sup>2</sup>) were treated with TGF&#x003b2;1 (10 ng/ml) before they were co-transfected with pEGFP and plasmids overexpressing either myc-tagged Hes6 (<bold>A</bold>) or mutant forms of FLAG-tagged I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; (<bold>B</bold>) for 16 h. The neurons were then processed for immunocytochemistry using anti-EGFP and anti-myc/anti-FLAG antibodies. (<bold>A</bold>) Overexpression of <italic>Hes6</italic>, a known inhibitor of <italic>Hes1</italic>, abrogated the effects of TGF&#x003b2;1 on dendritic length (left panel) and on the number of primary dendrites (middle panel). <italic>Hes6 </italic>overexpression also prevented the TGF&#x003b2;1-induced increase in the number of GABAergic terminals (right panel). (<bold>B</bold>) Transfection of I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; S32-36A (a mutation that affects serine phosphorylation of the inhibitor) prevented the TGF&#x003b2;1-induced increase in dendritic length (left panel) and attenuated the formation of vesicular inhibitory amino acid transporter (VIAAT)-positive clusters (right panel). The I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; Y42F mutation that affects the tyrosine phosphorylation of the inhibitor had no effect on TGF&#x003b2;1 activity. *<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.01, and ***<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt134-4"/></fig><p>Although the TGF&#x003b2;1 transduction pathway that modulates neuronal plasticity is poorly understood (but see Discussion), TGF&#x003b2;1 is known to activate NF-&#x003ba;B in hippocampal neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. We found that this activation of NF-&#x003ba;B by TGF&#x003b2;1 may be involved in neuronal plasticity, and thus we analyzed the morphological changes induced by TGF&#x003b2;1 in cells transfected with either a non-serine phosphorylatable mutant I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; or a non-tyrosine phosphorylatable form of I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;. Transfection with the serine mutant blocked the effects of TGF&#x003b2;1 on dendrite elongation and GABAergic connectivity (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>), whereas transfection with the tyrosine mutant of I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; had no effect on TGF&#x003b2;1 activity. Accordingly, the effects of TGF&#x003b2;1 on neuronal plasticity are dependent upon serine phosphorylation of I-&#x003ba;B and its capacity to activate NF-&#x003ba;B. By contrast, overexpression of the tyrosine mutant form had no effect on TGF&#x003b2;1 activity (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>). In conjunction with previous findings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], these results suggest that <italic>Hes1 </italic>can be activated by either NGF or TGF&#x003b2;1. Both these factors activate NF-&#x003ba;B, although the former degrades I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; by phosphorylation at tyrosine 42 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] and the latter by phosphorylating serines 32 and 36.</p></sec><sec><title>Anti-amyloid effects of TGF&#x003b2;1</title><p>As A&#x003b2; prevents NGF-induced tyrosine phosphorylation and the subsequent degradation of I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], we asked whether TGF&#x003b2;1 could counteract the noxious effects of A&#x003b2; by activating NF-&#x003ba;B after having promoted serine phosphorylation of I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;. Using a reporter gene luminescent assay, we demonstrated that TGF&#x003b2;1 activated NF-&#x003ba;B (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>), more than doubling its activity in cultured neurons. Moreover, the reporter gene assay revealed a modest but significant decrease in NF-&#x003ba;B activity produced by A&#x003b2;, which significantly failed to prevent TGF&#x003b2;1-induced activation of NF-&#x003ba;B. In accordance with this observation, we found that TGF&#x003b2;1 increased neuronal <italic>Hes1 </italic>mRNA expression, while A&#x003b2; induced a significant reduction in <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). Indeed, exposure to TGF&#x003b2;1 partially restored the low levels of <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression induced by A&#x003b2;. These results demonstrate that TGF&#x003b2;1 opposes the effects of A&#x003b2; on NF-&#x003ba;B activation and <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression.</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Tranforming growth factor &#x003b2;1 (TGF&#x003b2;1) activates nuclear factor kappa-B (NF-&#x003ba;B) and induces <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression, controlling dendrite morphology and GABAergic connectivity, and conferring cultured neurons with resistance to amyloid beta (A&#x003b2;) neurotoxicity</bold>. (<bold>A</bold>) Dual-luciferase NF-&#x003ba;B reporter gene assay. After transfecting NF-&#x003ba;B-luc and RL-TK-luc, 7 days <italic>in vitro </italic>(DIV) hippocampal neurons were incubated for 16 h and the neurons were then exposed to A&#x003b2; (5 &#x003bc;M) with TGF&#x003b2;1 (10 ng/ml) added to the medium 1 h later. The neurons were analyzed after a further 4 h incubation and the data represent the means of six experiments. (<bold>B</bold>) Cultured neurons (7 DIV, 300,000 cells) were treated with A&#x003b2; (5 &#x003bc;M) and then TGF&#x003b2;1 (10 ng/ml) 1 h later, and the cells incubated for a further 16 h. After lysing the cells, <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression was quantified by real time PCR (the means of 10 determinations are shown). (<bold>C-E</bold>) Hippocampal neurons (7 DIV, 40,000 cells/cm<sup>2</sup>) were transfected with enhanced green fluorescent protein (EGFP) and treated with A&#x003b2; (5 &#x003bc;M) and/or TGF&#x003b2;1 (10 ng/ml). After 16 h, immunostaining for EGFP and vesicular inhibitory amino acid transporter (VIAAT) was performed as described in Materials and methods. (<bold>C</bold>) Representative micrographs of cultured neurons under different conditions (the lower panels show the boxed regions at higher magnification). (<bold>D</bold>) Morphometric analysis of A&#x003b2;- and TGF&#x003b2;1-treated neurons. TGF&#x003b2;1 increased the length (left panel) and decreased the number (right panel) of primary dendrites, thereby counteracting the effects of A&#x003b2;. (<bold>E</bold>) Quantification of GABAergic clusters. TGF&#x003b2;1 increased the number of GABAergic terminals in cultured neurons and overrode the decrease in GABAergic terminals induced by A&#x003b2;. (<bold>F</bold>) Hippocampal neurons (7 DIV, 30,000 cells/cm<sup>2</sup>) were treated with A&#x003b2; (5 &#x003bc;M) and/or TGF&#x003b2;1 (10 ng/ml) for 90 h and the number of intact nuclei were counted after 4',6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI) staining. TGF&#x003b2;1 prevented A&#x003b2;-induced death of a portion of cultured hippocampal neurons. *<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.01, and ***<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt134-5"/></fig><p>Based on the above findings, we examined the anti-amyloid effects of TGF&#x003b2;1 on neuronal morphology, connectivity and survival (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C-F</xref>). TGF&#x003b2;1 blocked the effects of A&#x003b2; on dendrite length and number (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C, D</xref>), and it prevented the A&#x003b2;-induced decrease in the number of GABAergic terminals (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C, E</xref>). Finally, administration of TGF&#x003b2;1 to cultured neurons protected about 50% of neurons from A&#x003b2; neurotoxicity Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5F</xref>). These results emphasize the potential of TGF&#x003b2;1 as a neuroprotective agent and reveal, at least in part, the molecular basis of this neuroprotective activity.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>The effect of NF-&#x003ba;B activity on neuron survival</title><p>Transcription factors, including NF-&#x003ba;B, are implicated in experience-based synaptic regulation, and mouse models involving altered NF-&#x003ba;B activity have revealed the importance of the various forms of this transcription factor in learning and memory (reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]). NF-&#x003ba;B may influence neuronal plasticity at multiple levels as it mediates neurite outgrowth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] and participates in the development of dendritic spines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. NF-&#x003ba;B also plays an important role in the dendritic development of Purkinje cells, since when it is inhibited with a lysyl oxidase peptide, serious deficits in dendritic arborisation are provoked [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. Here, we show that p65/RelA transfection induces significant changes in the morphology of the dendrites emitted by cultured hippocampal neurons. These alterations were similar to those previously described for NGF, the effects of which are partially mediated by NF-&#x003ba;B [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Overexpression of p65/RelA induces an increase in dendritic length and a decrease in dendrite number within 16 h. Perhaps more importantly, p65/RelA overexpression counteracts the effects of A&#x003b2; on dendrite morphology, decreasing dendrite length and increasing the number of primary dendrites. This finding provides an important indication of the anti-amyloid effects of p65/RelA overexpression.</p><p>NF-&#x003ba;B exerts neuroprotective effects against some neurotoxic agents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>], including A&#x003b2; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>], and total abrogation of NF-&#x003ba;B activation by pharmacological agents was followed by hippocampal neuron death (Figure S2A in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>). However, with the exception of bcl-XL induction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>] and the suppression of apoptotic proteins such as Bax and Bim [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>], the mechanisms underlying NF-&#x003ba;B-induced neuroprotection remain elusive. In neurons, NF-&#x003ba;B is required to maintain high GluR1 levels and neuronal hyperexcitability following the induction of long-term potentiation (LTP) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. However, increases in NF-&#x003ba;B activity in response to enhanced excitatory transmission may accelerate the onset of the cognitive defect in a mouse model of Alzheimer's disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. The present results show that p65/RelA promotes GABAergic connectivity in cultured hippocampal neurons, as revealed by the substantial increases in terminals containing VIAAT. We previously reported a substantial loss of VIAAT-labeled terminals shortly after A&#x003b2; administration in cultured hippocampal neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] These effects were fully prevented by overexpressing p65/RelA, which may explain the basis underlying the anti-amyloid activity of NF-&#x003ba;B.</p><p>Together with inhibitors of NF-&#x003ba;B kinases, NF-&#x003ba;B regulates many physiological responses, and activation of IKK in neurons should induce similar cellular changes to those elicited by p65/RelA overexpression. The canonical pathway of NF-&#x003ba;B activation involves I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; phosphorylation via activation of the IKK complex (reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]). Transfection of hippocampal neurons with a plasmid expressing IKK&#x003b2; promoted dendritic growth while decreasing the number of primary dendrites. Furthermore, IKK&#x003b2; transfection prevented A&#x003b2; from altering dendritic patterning. Most importantly, IKK&#x003b2; overexpression protected a significant number of neurons from the deleterious effects of A&#x003b2;. Thus, canonical activation of NF-&#x003ba;B conferred amyloid resistance to cultured hippocampal neurons.</p></sec><sec><title>The role of Hes1 in anti-amyloid neuroprotection</title><p><italic>Hes1 </italic>is an important target of IKK&#x003b2;/NF-&#x003ba;B in terms of its influence on neuronal morphology and survival. Activation of NF-&#x003ba;B by NGF increases <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression, whereas specific inhibition of this nuclear factor abrogates the activity of the neurotrophin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] and it eventually caused cell death (Figure S2A in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>). We found that overexpression of either IKK&#x003b2; or p65/RelA induces an increase in <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression in transfected hippocampal neurons. To further demonstrate that both the morphological and anti-amyloid effects of IKK&#x003b2; and p65/RelA depend upon <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression, we transfected neurons with a vector that drives the overexpression of this gene. <italic>Hes1 </italic>overexpression induced the same morphological changes as seen following IKK&#x003b2; or p65/RelA overexpression, including a large increase in GABAergic connectivity. As expected, <italic>Hes1 </italic>overexpression counteracted the effects of A&#x003b2; on cell morphology and GABAergic terminals, and strikingly, overexpression of <italic>Hes1 </italic>also rescued 50% of neurons from A&#x003b2;-induced death. Conversely, inhibition of <italic>Hes1 </italic>activity by overexpression of <italic>Hes6 </italic>induced cell death (Figure S2B in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>). Together, these findings indicate that correct expression of <italic>Hes1 </italic>confers anti-amyloid resistance to cultured hippocampal neurons, strongly suggesting that strategies to increase <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression and activity may protect neurons from A&#x003b2; toxicity.</p></sec><sec><title>TGF&#x003b2;1 provides an alternative means of promoting Hes1 expression and inducing anti-amyloid activity</title><p>TGF&#x003b2;1 has long been recognized as a neuroprotective agent (for a review see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]) and indeed, neurodegeneration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>] and A&#x003b2; deposition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>] are enhanced in TGF&#x003b2;1-deficient mice. Furthermore, components of the hippocampal TGF&#x003b2; pathway are altered in schizophrenia and psychiatric disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. Several TGF&#x003b2; signalling pathways have been elucidated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>] and the canonical pathway involves the activation and nuclear localization of the Smad complex, where it modulates target gene transcription. However, our data suggest that the neuroprotective activity of TGF&#x003b2;1 is not mediated by this canonical pathway but rather, by NF-&#x003ba;B/<italic>Hes1</italic>. Administration of TGF&#x003b2;1 to cultured neurons alters dendritic patterning and GABAergic connectivity in a manner consistent with <italic>Hes1 </italic>overexpression. Moreover, transfection with <italic>Hes6</italic>, an inhibitor of <italic>Hes1 </italic>transcriptional activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>], abrogated all the effects of TGF&#x003b2;1 on neuronal morphology and connectivity. Although <italic>Hes1 </italic>upregulation by TGF&#x003b2;1 has been reported previously in fibroblasts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>], this is the first time the regulation of this bHLH gene by TGF&#x003b2;1 has been described in hippocampal neurons.</p><p>Further assays of neuronal morphology and connectivity revealed the involvement of I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; in TGF&#x003b2;1 signalling. Transfection with a serine mutant form of I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; abolishes the effects of TGF&#x003b2;1 on both dendritic shape and on the number of GABAergic terminals. However, a tyrosine mutant form of I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; had no effect on TGF&#x003b2;1 activity, indicating that serine phosphorylation of I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; preceded NF-&#x003ba;B activation in this pathway. Direct biochemical measurements revealed that treatment of cultured neurons with TGF&#x003b2;1 promoted NF-&#x003ba;B activation and <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression. The activation of NF-&#x003ba;B by TGF&#x003b2;1 has been reported previously in cultured hippocampal neurons from rat embryos [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. However, we also observed that TGF&#x003b2;1 reversed the loss in NF-&#x003ba;B activity and <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression induced by A&#x003b2;. Indeed, TGF&#x003b2;1 also prevented the formation of VIAAT-positive clusters in response to A&#x003b2;, and it prevented A&#x003b2; from altering dendrite patterning. Most importantly, TGF&#x003b2;1 rescued a significant portion of neurons from A&#x003b2;-induced death. These findings confirm the neuroprotective capacity of this cytokine and the underlying role of NF-&#x003ba;B activation and <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression.</p><p>We showed previously that the action of A&#x003b2; is exerted in part by inhibiting early steps in the NGF signalling pathway, including the deactivation of RhoA and the activation of PTP1B, both events that are needed for NF-&#x003ba;B activation and to promote <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Accordingly, TGF&#x003b2;1 can circumvent such effects by activating NF-&#x003ba;B through an alternative mechanism that involves the serine phosphorylation of I-&#x003ba;B, as shown here. However, when NF-&#x003ba;B activation was pharmacologically impaired by SN-50 or when <italic>Hes1 </italic>activity was blocked by <italic>Hes6 </italic>overexpression, TGF&#x003b2;1 activity was abrogated (Figure S2A and S2B in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>). Together, these results suggest that on the one hand, NF-&#x003ba;B activation and <italic>Hes1 </italic>activity are needed for cell survival, and on the other, that TGF&#x003b2;1 exert its anti-amyloid activity by potentiating NF-&#x003ba;B and <italic>Hes1 </italic>activities.</p></sec><sec><title>Modulation of GABAergic input in neuroprotection</title><p>Growth factors may control synaptic development and transmission in quantitative terms. Brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF) upregulates glutamatergic input and downregulates the number of GABAergic synaptic terminals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>], while insulin promotes the postsynaptic accumulation of GABA<sub>A </sub>receptors by increasing Akt-mediated phosphorylation of &#x003b2; subunits (reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]). NGF also increases the expression of GABAergic terminals in cultured hippocampal neurons, an effect mediated by altering <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Via the canonical pathway involving Smad4, TGF&#x003b2;1 is a critical factor in use-dependent modulation of GABA<sub>A</sub>-mediated synaptic transmission and dendrite homeostasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>].</p><p>In all experimental paradigms assayed here, including the transfection of cultured neurons with IKK&#x003b2;, I&#x003ba;-B&#x003b1; or p65/RelA and the exposure of cultured neurons to TGF&#x003b2;1, VIAAT immunocytochemistry indicated that there was a large increase in the expression of GABAergic terminals. These experimental approaches also consistently prevented A&#x003b2; from affecting GABAergic terminals, since exposure to A&#x003b2; decreases the number of GABAergic connections after 16 h and kills cells after 90 h. Thus, there is compelling evidence that <italic>Hes1 </italic>is an important element in the maintenance of GABAergic connectivity, although the mechanisms underlying this phenomenon remain unknown. The increase in GABAergic input promoted by NF-&#x003ba;B/<italic>Hes1 </italic>may provide a negative feedback in the control of excitatory activity and consequently, protect neurons from excitotoxicity. The increase in inhibitory activity induced by NF-&#x003ba;B activation or TGF&#x003b2;1 administration may account for the neuroprotective effects observed. Indeed, TGF&#x003b2;1 plays an important role in the excitatory/inhibitory balance of hippocampal transmission [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The findings presented here support the notion that neurons can be protected from the noxious effects of A&#x003b2; by modulating inhibitory transmission. Moreover, strategies that mildly activate NF-&#x003ba;B and/or that enhance <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression could provide beneficial neuroprotection. Significantly, TGF&#x003b2;1 signalling counteracts the inhibitory effect of A&#x003b2; on NGF signalling (summarized in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>), possibly supplementing the attenuated activity of NGF in Alzheimer's disease and representing a potential target for the development of anti-amyloid therapies.</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Transforming growth factor &#x003b2;1 (TGF&#x003b2;1), nerve growth factor (NGF) and amyloid beta (A&#x003b2;)-induced signaling in hippocampal neurons</bold>. Diagram outlining the signal transduction pathways downstream of TGF&#x003b2;1 that promote <italic>Hes1 </italic>expression and neuronal survival. How NGF is impaired by A&#x003b2; is also illustrated. In contrast to NGF, the activation of NF-&#x003ba;B and the increased expression of <italic>Hes1 </italic>induced by TGF&#x003b2;1 are not inhibited by A&#x003b2;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt134-6"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>A&#x003b2;: amyloid beta; AD: Alzheimer's disease; Akt: acutely transforming retrovirus AKT8 in rodent T cell lymphoma; BDNF: brain-derived neurotrophic factor; bHLH: basic helix-loop-helix; DAPI: 4',6-diamidino-2-phenylindole; DMSO: dimethyl sulfoxide; EGFP: enhanced green fluorescent protein; FAM: 6-carboxy fluorescein; GABA: gamma-aminobutyric acid; GLU1: glutamate receptor 1; HRP: horseradish peroxidise; I-&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;: I kappa B&#x003b1;; Hes1: enhancer of split homolog 1; IKKB: I-&#x003ba;B kinase; LTP: long-term potentiation; NF-&#x003ba;B: nuclear factor kappa-B; NGF: nerve growth factor; PBS: phosphate-buffered saline; PFA: paraformaldehyde; PTP1B: protein tyrosine phosphatase 1B; PVDF: polyvinylidene difluoride; ROI: region of interest; TGF&#x003b2;1: transforming growth factor &#x003b2;1; VIAAT: vesicular inhibitory amino acid transporter; wt: wild type.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>PJC and ART designed and performed research; PJC and ART analyzed data; PJC and ART wrote the paper. Both authors have read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional file 1</title><p><bold>Figure showing molecular characterization and neurotoxic properties of the amyloid &#x003b2; (A&#x003b2;) preparations used in this study</bold>. (<bold>A</bold>) The preparations of A&#x003b2; were characterized in western blots probed with an anti-A&#x003b2; antibody following Bis-Tris PAGE separation (see Methods). Lane (1) shows that the stock preparation mostly contained monomeric and dimeric species, with smaller quantities of trimeric and tetrameric forms. In lanes 2 to 5, A&#x003b2; was added to 35 mm culture dishes that containing one glass polylysine coated 2 &#x000d7; 2 cm coverslip and 2 mL of medium at the concentrations indicated. After a three-day incubation at 37&#x000b0;C, aliquots of the medium were taken and resolved by electrophoresis (supernatant, snt, lanes 2 and 3). Simultaneously, the glass coverslips were washed with LDS sample buffer and the material released was also separated in the same gels (immobilized on glass, imm, lanes 4 and 5). Note that the incubation of amyloid favoured the formation of higher molecular weight forms, although most species were small oligomers and the larger aggregates, including fibrils, only represented a small fraction of the amyloid. (<bold>B</bold>) Hippocampal neurons (7 days <italic>in vitro </italic>(DIV) and 30,000 cells/cm<sup>2</sup>) were treated with A&#x003b2; as indicated. After 90 h, the cells were fixed and stained with 4',6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI) to asses the integrity of their nuclei. Note that A&#x003b2; (5 &#x003bc;M) produced a high rate of cell death, which justified the use of this concentration in further experiments. VF, microscope view field.</p></caption><media xlink:href="alzrt134-S1.TIFF" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Additional file 2</title><p><bold>Figure showing the nuclear factor kappa B (NF-&#x003ba;B) pathway and <italic>Hes1 </italic>activity are needed for the survival of neurons, while transforming growth factor &#x003b2;1 (TGF&#x003b2;1) is unable to rescue cells from death</bold>. E17 hippocampal neurons were plated at a density of 30,000 cells/cm<sup>2 </sup>and cultured for 7 days <italic>in vitro </italic>(DIV). Neurons were (<bold>A</bold>) treated for 24 h with SN-50 (5 &#x003bc;M) or with its control peptide in the presence or absence of TGF&#x003b2;1 (10 ng/ml). (<bold>B</bold>) Neurons were co-transfected with enhanced green fluorescent protein (EGFP) and a myc-tagged <italic>Hes6 </italic>vector for 48 h in the presence or absence of TGF&#x003b2;1. The cells were fixed and labeled with anti-EGFP and anti-myc antibodies, while the integrity of their nuclei was assessed by 4',6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI) staining. Note that the obliteration of either NF-&#x003ba;B activation or <italic>Hes1 </italic>activity was followed by neuron death. The addition of TGF&#x003b2;1 did not reverse these effects.</p></caption><media xlink:href="alzrt134-S2.TIFF" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>P Chacon was supported by the Instituto de Salud Carlos III (Contratos Post-Doctorales Sara Borrell). This work was financed by the Fundaci&#x000f3; La Caixa (grant BM05-184) and the Spanish Ministry of Education and Science (grants BFU2007-63033 and BFU2010-20995). We are indebted to Emmanuel Villanueva, &#x000c1;ngel J del Marco and Rosa M Garc&#x000ed;a-Mej&#x000ed;as for technical assistance. We thank Dr Lisardo Bosc&#x000e1; (Madrid, Spain) for providing the IKK plasmids, Dr Mayte Coyras (Madrid, Spain) for the p65/RelA plasmid, Dr Ryoichiro Kageyama (Kyoto, Japan) for the <italic>Hes1 </italic>plasmid, Dr Phil Jones (Cambridge, UK) for the <italic>Hes6 </italic>plasmid.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wilcock</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Colton</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><article-title>Anti-amyloid-beta immunotherapy in Alzheimer's disease: relevance of transgenic mouse studies to clinical trials</article-title><source>J Alzheimers Dis</source><year>2008</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>555</fpage><lpage>569</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19096156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdile</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><article-title>Immunization in Alzheimer's disease: naive hope or realistic clinical potential?</article-title><source>Mol Psychiatry</source><year>2009</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mp.2008.115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18957942</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>St George-Hyslop</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><article-title>Will anti-amyloid therapies work for Alzheimer's disease?</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2008</year><volume>372</volume><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(08)61047-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18640437</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>De Rosa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Braschi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Capsoni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Maffei</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Berardi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cattaneo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Intranasal administration of nerve growth factor (NGF) rescues recognition memory deficits in AD11 anti-NGF transgenic mice</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>3811</fpage><lpage>3816</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0500195102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15728733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Louzada</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendonca-Silva</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Noel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>De Mello</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><article-title>Taurine prevents the neurotoxicity of beta-amyloid and glutamate receptor agonists: activation of GABA receptors and possible implications for Alzheimer's disease and other neurological disorders</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>2004</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.03-0739com</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15003996</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Louzada</surname><given-names>PR</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Paula Lima</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>De Mello</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><article-title>Dual role of glutamatergic neurotransmission on amyloid beta(1-42) aggregation and neurotoxicity in embryonic avian retina</article-title><source>Neurosci Lett</source><year>2001</year><volume>301</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-3940(01)01585-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11239716</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tuszynski</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Blesch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Nerve growth factor: from animal models of cholinergic neuronal degeneration to gene therapy in Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>Prog Brain Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14699979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tuszynski</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Thal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmon</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>U</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakay</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Blesch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vahlsing</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Potkin</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Fallon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mufson</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kordower</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gall</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Conner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>A phase 1 clinical trial of nerve growth factor gene therapy for Alzheimer disease</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>551</fpage><lpage>555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm1239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15852017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tuszynski</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><article-title>Nerve growth factor gene therapy in Alzheimer disease</article-title><source>Alzheimer Dis Assoc Disord</source><year>2007</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/WAD.0b013e318068d6d2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17545746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yaar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilch</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisenhauer</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fine</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilchrest</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><article-title>Binding of beta-amyloid to the p75 neurotrophin receptor induces apoptosis. A possible mechanism for Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>1997</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>2333</fpage><lpage>2340</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI119772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9410912</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yaar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fine</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisenhauer</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Arble</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilchrest</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><article-title>Amyloid beta binds trimers as well as monomers of the 75-kDa neurotrophin receptor and activates receptor signaling</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>7720</fpage><lpage>7725</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M110929200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11756426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Arevalo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Roldan</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chacon</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Tebar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Amyloid &#x003b2; serves as an NGF-like neurotrophic factor or acts as a NGF antagonist depending on its concentration</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2009</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>1425</fpage><lpage>1433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-4159.2009.06412.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20050289</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Salama-Cohen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Arevalo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Grantyn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Tebar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>NGF controls dendrite development in hippocampal neurons by binding to p75NTR and modulating the cellular targets of Notch</article-title><source>Mol Biol Cell</source><year>2005</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>339</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15496460</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Salama-Cohen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Arevalo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Grantyn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Tebar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Notch and NGF/p75NTR control dendrite morphology and the balance of excitatory/inhibitory synaptic input to hippocampal neurones through Neurogenin 3</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2006</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>1269</fpage><lpage>1278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-4159.2006.03783.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16539652</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chacon</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Mejias</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Tebar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Inhibition of RhoA GTPase and the subsequent activation of PTP1B protects cultured hippocampal neurons against amyloid beta toxicity</article-title><source>Mol Neurodegener</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1750-1326-6-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21294893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Castrillo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>de Las</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hortelano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Villar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosca</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Inhibition of the nuclear factor kappa B (NF-kappa B) pathway by tetracyclic kaurene diterpenes in macrophages. Specific effects on NF-kappa B-inducing kinase activity and on the coordinate activation of ERK and p38 MAPK</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>15854</fpage><lpage>15860</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M100010200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11278990</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chacon</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Arevalo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tebar</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><article-title>NGF-activated protein tyrosine phosphatase 1B mediates the phosphorylation and degradation of I-kappa-Balpha coupled to NF-kappa-B activation, thereby controlling dendrite morphology</article-title><source>Mol Cell Neurosci</source><year>2010</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>384</fpage><lpage>393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcn.2010.01.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20123020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Coiras</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez-Huertas</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mateos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Alcami</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Caspase-3-mediated cleavage of p65/RelA results in a carboxy-terminal fragment that inhibits IkappaBalpha and enhances HIV-1 replication in human T lymphocytes</article-title><source>Retrovirology</source><year>2008</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>109</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1742-4690-5-109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19046417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bessho</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hojo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kageyama</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>The bHLH gene Hes6, an inhibitor of Hes1, promotes neuronal differentiation</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2000</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>2933</fpage><lpage>2943</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10851137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cossins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vernon</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Philpott</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><article-title>Hes6 regulates myogenic differentiation</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2002</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>2195</fpage><lpage>2207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11959828</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Goslin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Banker</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Experimental observations on the development of polarity by hippocampal neurons in culture</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1989</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>1507</fpage><lpage>1516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.108.4.1507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2925793</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Konig</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kogel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rami</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Prehn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><article-title>TGF-{beta}1 activates two distinct type I receptors in neurons: implications for neuronal NF-{kappa}B signaling</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>1077</fpage><lpage>1086</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200407027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15781474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hand</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Polleux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehlers</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><article-title>TGF-beta signaling specifies axons during brain development</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2010.06.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20603020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hocking</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hehr</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McFarlane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>TGFbeta ligands promote the initiation of retinal ganglion cell dendrites in vitro and in vivo</article-title><source>Mol Cell Neurosci</source><year>2008</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcn.2007.09.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17997109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Koyano-Nakagawa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kintner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Hes6 acts in a positive feedback loop with the neurogenins to promote neuronal differentiation</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2000</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>4203</fpage><lpage>4216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10976052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kaltschmidt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaltschmidt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>NF-kappaB in the nervous system</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>a001271</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a001271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20066105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gavalda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><article-title>Developmental switch in NF-kappaB signalling required for neurite growth</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2009</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>3405</fpage><lpage>3412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.035295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19762427</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boersma</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dresselhaus</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>De Biase</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mihalas</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergles</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Meffert</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><article-title>A requirement for nuclear factor-kappaB in developmental and plasticity-associated synaptogenesis</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2011</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>5414</fpage><lpage>5425</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2456-10.2011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21471377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Calicchio</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>YD</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vartanian</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasqualini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Arap</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Libermann</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Sidman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><article-title>Nna1 mediates Purkinje cell dendritic development via lysyl oxidase propeptide and NF-kappaB signaling</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2010</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2010.08.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20920790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bhakar</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tannis</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeindler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Jobin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>MacPherson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><article-title>Constitutive nuclear factor-kappa B activity is required for central neuron survival</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2002</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>8466</fpage><lpage>8475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12351721</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Blondeau</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Widmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazdunski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Heurteaux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Activation of the nuclear factor-kappaB is a key event in brain tolerance</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2001</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>4668</fpage><lpage>4677</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11425894</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Barger</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Horster</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Krieglstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><article-title>Tumor necrosis factors alpha and beta protect neurons against amyloid beta-peptide toxicity: evidence for involvement of a kappa B-binding factor and attenuation of peroxide and Ca2+ accumulation</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1995</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>9328</fpage><lpage>9332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.92.20.9328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7568127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><article-title>Brain-derived neurotrophic factor enhances Bcl-xL expression through protein kinase casein kinase 2-activated and nuclear factor kappa B-mediated pathway in rat hippocampus</article-title><source>Brain Pathol</source><year>2011</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>150</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1750-3639.2010.00431.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20731656</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mincheva</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gou-Fabregas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Encinas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolcet</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Soler</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><article-title>The canonical nuclear factor-kappaB pathway regulates cell survival in a developmental model of spinal cord motoneurons</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2011</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>6493</fpage><lpage>6503</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0206-11.2011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21525290</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>O'Mahony</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Raber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Montano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Foehr</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>LeFevour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakraborty-Sett</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><article-title>NF-kappaB/Rel regulates inhibitory and excitatory neuronal function and synaptic plasticity</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>7283</fpage><lpage>7298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.00510-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16980629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Arancio</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Trinchese</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Puzzo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegde</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Luddy</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lue</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Roher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Buttini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mucke</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kindy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyslop</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Du Yan</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><article-title>RAGE potentiates Abeta-induced perturbation of neuronal function in transgenic mice</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2004</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>4096</fpage><lpage>4105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.emboj.7600415</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15457210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><article-title>Integrating cell-signalling pathways with NF-kappaB and IKK function</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm2083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17183360</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Caraci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Battaglia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbonaro</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Giuffrida</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Drago</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sortino</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicoletti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Copani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>TGF-beta1 Pathway as a new target for neuroprotection in alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>CNS Neurosci Ther</source><year>2011</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1755-5949.2009.00115.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19925479</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brionne</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tesseur</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Masliah</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyss-Coray</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>Loss of TGF-beta 1 leads to increased neuronal cell death and microgliosis in mouse brain</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2003</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1133</fpage><lpage>1145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-6273(03)00766-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14687548</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Makwana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuthill</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Heuer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohatschek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hristova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedrichsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ormsby</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bueringer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Koppius</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Doetschman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Raivich</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Endogenous transforming growth factor beta 1 suppresses inflammation and promotes survival in adult CNS</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2007</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>11201</fpage><lpage>11213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2255-07.2007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17942715</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tesseur</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Berber</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Can</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Crews</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mucke</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Masliah</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyss-Coray</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>Deficiency in neuronal TGF-beta signaling promotes neurodegeneration and Alzheimer's pathology</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2006</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>3060</fpage><lpage>3069</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI27341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17080199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Benes</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Matzilevich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Subburaju</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Minns</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Regulation of the GABA cell phenotype in hippocampus of schizophrenics and bipolars</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>10164</fpage><lpage>10169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0703806104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17553960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><article-title>Signaling cross-talk between TGF-beta/BMP and other pathways</article-title><source>Cell Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cr.2008.302</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19002158</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kennard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lilly</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>Transforming growth factor-beta (TGF- 1) down-regulates Notch3 in fibroblasts to promote smooth muscle gene expression</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2008</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>1324</fpage><lpage>1333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17981798</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Henneberger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Betances</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Arevalo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-T&#x000e9;bar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Grantyn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Altered balance of glutamatergic/GABAergic synaptic input and associated changes in dendrite morphology after BDNF expression in BDNF-deficient hippocampal neurons</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2006</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>7189</fpage><lpage>7200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5474-05.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16822976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Luscher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilpatrick</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><article-title>GABAA receptor trafficking-mediated plasticity of inhibitory synapses</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2011</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>385</fpage><lpage>409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2011.03.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21555068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gewirtz</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bofenkamp</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wickham</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Connor</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><article-title>Canonical TGF-beta signaling is required for the balance of excitatory/inhibitory transmission within the hippocampus and prepulse inhibition of acoustic startle</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2010</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>6025</fpage><lpage>6035</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0789-10.2010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20427661</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>