<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Alzheimers Res Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Alzheimers Res Ther</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Alzheimer's Research &#x00026; Therapy</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1758-9193</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22621179</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3506932</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">alzrt121</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/alzrt121</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Overlapping profiles of A&#x003b2; peptides in the Alzheimer's disease and pathological aging brains</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>Brenda D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>brendar@ufl.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Chakrabarty</surname><given-names>Paramita</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>pchakrabarty@ufl.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Levites</surname><given-names>Yona</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>levites.yona@ufl.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name><surname>Kukar</surname><given-names>Tom L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>thomas.kukar@emory.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5"><name><surname>Baine</surname><given-names>Ann-Marie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>atbaine09@aol.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6"><name><surname>Moroni</surname><given-names>Tina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>tinamoroni@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A7"><name><surname>Ladd</surname><given-names>Thomas B</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>tomladd@ufl.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A8"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>Pritam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>das.pritam@mayo.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A9"><name><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>Dennis W</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>dickson.dennis@mayo.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A10"><name><surname>Golde</surname><given-names>Todd E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>tgolde@ufl.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Center for Translational Research in Neurodegenerative Disease, Department of Neuroscience, McKnight Brain Institute, College of Medicine, University of Florida, 1275 Center Drive, Gainesville, FL, 32610, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Pharmacology, Emory University School of Medicine, 1510 Clifton Road, Atlanta, GA, 30322, USA</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department Of Neuroscience, Mayo Clinic College of Medicine, 4500 San Pablo Road, Jacksonville, FL, 32224, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>3</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>17</day><month>4</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9;2012 Moore et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Moore et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://alzres.com/content/4/3/18"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>A hallmark of Alzheimer's disease (AD) is the presence of senile plaques composed of aggregated amyloid &#x003b2; (A&#x003b2;) peptides. Pathological aging (PA) is a postmortem classification that has been used to describe brains with plaque pathology similar in extent to AD, minimal cortical tau pathology, and no accompanying history of cognitive decline in the brain donor prior to death. PA may represent either a prodromal phase of AD, a benign form of A&#x003b2; accumulation, or inherent individual resistance to the toxic effects of A&#x003b2; accumulation. To attempt to distinguish between these possibilities we have systematically characterized A&#x003b2; peptides in a postmortem series of PA, AD and non-demented control (NDC) brains.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>A&#x003b2; was sequentially extracted with tris buffered saline (TBS), radioimmunoprecipitation buffer (RIPA), 2% sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS) and 70% formic acid (FA) from the pre-frontal cortex of 16 AD, eight PA, and six NDC patients. These extracts were analyzed by 1) a panel of A&#x003b2; sandwich ELISAs, 2) immunoprecipitation followed by mass spectrometry (IP/MS) and 3) western blotting. These studies enabled us to asses A&#x003b2; levels and solubility, peptide profiles and oligomeric assemblies.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>In almost all extracts (TBS, RIPA, 2% SDS and 70% FA) the average levels of A&#x003b2;1-40, A&#x003b2;1-42, A&#x003b2; total, and A&#x003b2;x-42 were greatest in AD. On average, levels were slightly lower in PA, and there was extensive overlap between A&#x003b2; levels in individual PA and AD cases. The profiles of A&#x003b2; peptides detected using IP/MS techniques also showed extensive similarity between the PA and AD brain extracts. In select AD brain extracts, we detected more amino-terminally truncated A&#x003b2; peptides compared to PA patients, but these peptides represented a minor portion of the A&#x003b2; observed. No consistent differences in the A&#x003b2; assemblies were observed by western blotting in the PA and AD groups.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>We found extensive overlap with only subtle quantitative differences between A&#x003b2; levels, peptide profiles, solubility, and SDS-stable oligomeric assemblies in the PA and AD brains. These cross-sectional data indicate that A&#x003b2; accumulation in PA and AD is remarkably similar. Such data would be consistent with PA representing a prodromal stage of AD or a resistance to the toxic effects of A&#x003b2;.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Alzheimer's disease (AD) is characterized by large numbers of extracellular amyloid plaques with dense amyloid cores that are associated with dystrophic neurites and neuroinflammatory changes as well as intraneuronal neurofibrillary tangles. Pathological aging (PA) patients also have abundant and widespread amyloid plaques; however, these plaques have typically been described as diffuse in nature. In PA there are fewer cored plaques and there is little or no inflammatory reaction, neuritic pathology or neurofibrillary tangles in the cortex. These patients are reported to be cognitively normal prior to death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Based on our current understanding of the progression of AD, PA may represent a prodromal phase of AD (for example, preclinical stage 1 AD, plaque only), a benign form of A&#x003b2; accumulation, or inherent individual resistance to the toxic effects of A&#x003b2; accumulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>].</p><p>A&#x003b2; is the principle component of amyloid deposits in the AD brain. It is a secreted peptide produced through sequential cleavage of the Amyloid-&#x003b2; Protein Precursor (APP) by &#x003b2;- and &#x003b3;-secretases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. A&#x003b2; peptides have a heterogeneous carboxyl-terminus with the majority (approximately 40% to 70%) composed of 40 amino acids A&#x003b2;1-40, while a minor product (approximately 5% to 20%) contains a two amino acid extension A&#x003b2;1-42. Additional minor A&#x003b2; peptides are also normally produced (for example, 1-34, 1-37, 1-38 and 1-39), although few reports have quantified the levels of these peptides in the brain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. A&#x003b2;1-42 is more amyloidogenic and has been implicated as the pathogenic form of A&#x003b2; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. A recent study also suggested that A&#x003b2;1-43 could play a critical role in A&#x003b2; accumulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Furthermore, a variety of truncated and modified A&#x003b2; peptides have been described (for example, 1-28, 1-29, 1-45, 2-46, 3-44, 3-47, 2-42, 4-42, 5-42, 6-42, 7-45, 8-42, 1-42Met35ox, pE3-42, pE11-42) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Of these truncated and modified forms the pyroglutamate modified forms, A&#x003b2;pE3-42 and A&#x003b2;pE11-42, have been highly investigated, as key species possibly involved in initial nucleation or seeding events [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>].</p><p>Once liberated from APP, A&#x003b2; can self-associate to form various aggregates. These aggregates include soluble oligomers, protofibrils, and amyloid fibrils [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. Although there is currently debate within the field regarding which form or forms of A&#x003b2; aggregates are the most pathogenic, there is general consensus that the aggregated forms of A&#x003b2; are harmful and that A&#x003b2;1-42 or possibly A&#x003b2;1-43 is required for aggregation in the absence of internal mutations within A&#x003b2; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>].</p><p>Because many different forms of A&#x003b2; exist and accumulate in various higher order assemblies, it is possible that the relatively poor correlation between cognitive deficits and plaque load is attributable to either qualitative or quantitative differences between a particular species or assembly of A&#x003b2;. This poor correlation could also reflect an inherent difference in vulnerability to 'toxic' effects of different forms of A&#x003b2; aggregates. Additionally, given the growing acceptance of the concept of preclinical AD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>], where the initial stage is defined by the presence of A&#x003b2; deposits in the absence of other pathologies and no evidence for cognitive impairment, the poor correlation could be attributable to differences in time from initial deposition to frank neurodegeneration and clinical deterioration.</p><p>As PA represents the most clear cut example of the dissociation between A&#x003b2; accumulation and cognitive impairment, investigation of the type and species of A&#x003b2; peptides in PA cohorts could provide novel insights into the poor correlation between A&#x003b2; and cognition. Previous studies investigating differences in A&#x003b2;1-40 and A&#x003b2;1-42 species extracted from PA and AD brains demonstrated that A&#x003b2;1-40 levels were as much as approximately 20-fold higher in AD brains compared to PA brains whereas A&#x003b2;1-42 levels were only about 2-fold higher [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. A more recent and extensive study using both ELISAs and western blotting to analyze A&#x003b2; levels and oligomeric assemblies failed to detect major differences in PA and AD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Other more anecdotal studies comparing oligomeric assemblies in a single PA brain versus AD brains failed to detect significantly elevated levels of A&#x003b2; dimer in the PA brain extracts compared to AD brain extracts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>].</p><p>Although these studies suggest that there may be both quantitative and qualitative differences in A&#x003b2; peptides in PA brains as opposed to AD brains, we felt that a more extensive investigation with larger cohorts was warranted. Here we report on our analysis of A&#x003b2; peptides sequentially extracted from the pre-frontal cortices of 16 AD patients, eight PA patients, and six non-demented controls (NDC) using a battery of biochemical tests. Our analysis shows that AD and PA brains are clearly distinct from controls, but there is extensive overlap between PA and AD with respect to extractable A&#x003b2; levels as measured by ELISA. Using immunoprecipitation mass spectrometry (IP/MS) to profile individual A&#x003b2; species in the PA and AD brain extracts we find that there is also extensive overlap in the profiles of accumulated A&#x003b2;. However, individual AD brains showed more extensive heterogeneity with an increase of diversity of A&#x003b2; species, particularly amino-terminally truncated A&#x003b2; species. Assessment of SDS-stable oligomers by western blotting also showed no consistent differences between PA and NDC.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Selection of PA cases</title><p>Frozen pre-frontal cortex (AD = 16, PA = 8, NDC = 7) was obtained from the Mayo Clinic Brain Bank with informed consent, in accordance with the Mayo Clinic institutional review board, using previously described acquisition and diagnostic analyses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. We analyzed 16 brains from AD patients (age range = 66 to 99; average age = 82), eight pathologic aging brains from subjects (age range = 66 to 90; average age = 80) without clinical evidence of dementia and seven brains with rare or no AD lesions from elderly individuals without clinical evidence of a neurological illness (age range = 66 to 87; average age = 76). Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> summarizes the cases studied here.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of demographics of human subjects studied.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th align="center" colspan="3">Group</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td/><td align="center"><bold>AD (<italic>n </italic>= 16)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>PA (<italic>n </italic>= 8)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>NDC (<italic>n </italic>= 7)</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Age</td><td align="center">82 (66 to 99)</td><td align="center">80 (66 to 90)</td><td align="center">76 (66 to 87)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Gender</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;M</td><td align="center">8 (50%)</td><td align="center">6 (75%)</td><td align="center">5 (71%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;F</td><td align="center">8 (50%)</td><td align="center">2 (25%)</td><td align="center">2 (29%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Braak</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">2.0</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td><td align="center">4 (50%)</td><td align="center">4 (57%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">2.5</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td><td align="center">1 (13%)</td><td align="center">1 (14%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3.0</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td><td align="center">3 (38%)</td><td align="center">2 (29%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3.5</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">4.0</td><td align="center">2 (13%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">4.5</td><td align="center">2 (13%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">5.0</td><td align="center">7 (44%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">5.5</td><td align="center">2 (13%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">6.0</td><td align="center">3 (19%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">CAA</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">6 (38%)</td><td align="center">5 (63%)</td><td align="center">5 (71%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">0 - 1+</td><td align="center">1 (6%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td><td align="center">1 (14%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1+</td><td align="center">6 (38%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td><td align="center">1 (14%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1+ - 2+</td><td align="center">1 (6%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">2+</td><td align="center">1 (6%)</td><td align="center">1 (13%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">2+ - 3+</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td><td align="center">1 (13%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3+</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td><td align="center">1 (13%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">4+</td><td align="center">1 (6%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td><td align="center">0 (0%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Median ages (age range), gender distribution, Braak score and CAA score are denoted. CAA scoring was done by post-mortem neuropathologic analysis by DW. AD, Alzheimers disease; CAA, cerebral amyloid angiography; F, female; M, male; n, number; NDC, non-demented controls; PA, Pathological aging.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Brain extraction</title><p>Frozen pre-frontal cortex tissue was cryo-pulverized in liquid nitrogen. Briefly, for ELISA and IP/MS, the cryo-pulverized tissue was sequentially extracted with Tris-buffered saline (TBS), radioimmunoprecipitation buffer (RIPA), 2% sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS) and 70% formic acid (FA) containing protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche, Indianapolis, IN, USA) as described before at a concentration of 300 mg/mL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. For immunoblotting, samples were either serially extracted in TBS and 2% SDS or directly extracted with RIPA at a concentration of 500 mg/mL.</p></sec><sec><title>ELISA</title><p>TBS, RIPA, 2% SDS and neutralized 70% FA extracted samples were diluted appropriately and used for sandwich ELISAs as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. A&#x003b2;1-40 was captured with monoclonal antibody (mAb) Ab9 (human A&#x003b2;1-16 specific; T.E. Golde) and detected by horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated mAb 13.1.1 (human A&#x003b2;35-40 specific; T.E. Golde); A&#x003b2;1-42 was captured with mAb 2.1.3 (human A&#x003b2;35-42 specific; T.E. Golde) and detected by HRP-conjugated mAb Ab9; Total A&#x003b2; was captured with mAb Ab9 and detected by HRP-conjugated mAb 4G8 (Covance, Princeton, NJ, USA); A&#x003b2;x-42 was captured with mAb 2.1.3 and detected by HRP-conjugated mAb 4G8.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunoprecipitation followed by mass spectrometry (IP/MS)</title><p>Magnetic sheep-anti-mouse IgG beads (Invitrogen, Grand Island, NY, USA) were incubated with 4.5 &#x003bc;g antibody (either Ab9 or 4G8 (Covance)) for 30 minutes at room temperature with constant shaking. The beads were then washed and incubated with each extract, which were diluted appropriately. All sample incubations were in the presence of 0.1% TritonX-100 (Tx-100) and either 10 pmol A&#x003b2;1-28 (TBS and RIPA extracts) or 100 pmol A&#x003b2;1-28 (2% SDS and 70% FA extracts) as an internal calibration standard. The samples were successively exposed to Ab9 and 4G8 coated beads for 30 minutes each with rotation. Bound beads were washed sequentially with 0.1% and 0.05% Tx-100 followed by water. Samples were eluted using a mix of 75% acetonitrile, 24.9% water and 0.1% FA. Samples were mixed in equal volume with sinapinic acid (25 mg/mL) in 50% acetonitrile, 49.5% water and 0.5% trifluoroacetic acid, and 1 &#x003bc;L was spotted onto a ProteinChip Gold Array (A-H format) (Bio-Rad Hercules, CA, USA) and analyzed with a Bio-Rad ProteinChip System Series 4000 (Enterprise Edition) mass spectrometer.</p></sec><sec><title>Western blotting</title><p>TBS, RIPA and 2% SDS brain lysates, heated at 50&#x000b0;C for three minutes in the presence of denaturing sample buffer, were separated on 4% to 12% Bis-Tris gel (Bio-Rad) in 1X 2-(N-morpholino)ethanesulfonic acid (MES) running buffer (Bio-Rad). Initially, we performed a comparative analysis of different immunoblotting techniques with different combinations of membranes (0.2 &#x003bc;m nitrocellulose and 0.2 &#x003bc;m polyvinylidene fluoride (PVDF)) and antigen retrieval techniques (boiling, glutaraldehyde and guanidine) in combination with three different primary antibodies (4G8, 82E1 (IBL, Hamburg, Germany) and Ab5 (human A&#x003b2;1-16 specific; T.E. Golde). After extensive analysis samples immunoblotted with 82E1 on boiled nitrocellulose membranes yielded the best results in terms of sensitivity and resolution. Transferred membranes were blocked in Starting Block (Thermo Scientific, Waltham, MA) and incubated overnight with primary antibody (82E1) and detected with donkey anti-mouse antibody conjugated to HRP (Jackson ImmunoResearch, West Grove, PA). Chemilumiscence signal (West Femto Chemiluminescent Substrate (Thermo Scientific)) was visualized with a FujiFilm system.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Results, unless otherwise mentioned, were analyzed with Prism 5 (GraphPad) by one way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with tukey <italic>post hoc </italic>test and presented as data &#x000b1; standard error of the mean (s.e.m.). Statistical significance is denoted by an asterisk.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Immunohistochemical characterization of A&#x003b2; plaques and phospho-tau in AD, PA and NDC</title><p>The sample population was chosen based on long standing AD and PA classification systems. Brains selected as PA had no evidence of cognitive decline in the clinic, but had extensive cortical A&#x003b2; plaques (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). To obtain more extensive characterization of A&#x003b2; and tau pathology in the PA cohort, we immunostained frontal cortical tissue for total A&#x003b2;, phospho-tau, A&#x003b2;1-40 (13.1.1) and A&#x003b2;1-42 (21.3.1) (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Consistent with the PA classification system, PA brains had extensive amyloid deposits and displayed only sparse CP13 immunoreactivity whereas AD patients contained widespread amyloid deposits as well as abundant phospho-tau bearing neurofibrillary tangles (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1, A, B, C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1F, G, H</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1I</xref>). PA brains showed more widespread A&#x003b2;1-42 immunoreactivity than A&#x003b2;1-40 immunoreactivity, perhaps corresponding to more abundant diffuse plaques as alluded to by independent groups (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2, C, D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2H, I</xref>). Cohorts with increased vessel-associated A&#x003b2;1-40 immunoreactivity have been sub-categorized as having cerebral amyloid angiopathy (CAA); CAA+ AD patients had more A&#x003b2;1-40 than the corresponding PA group (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2, A, B, C, D, F, G, H</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2I</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Immunohistochemical characterization of amyloid and tau pathology in Alzheimer's disease (AD), pathological aging (PA) and normal non-demented controls (NDC)</bold>. <bold>A-E</bold>. Representative paraffin embedded formalin fixed hippocampi from human AD (A, B), PA (C, D) and control (NDC; E) subjects were stained with 33.1.1 antibody (pan A&#x003b2;1-16). Insets show higher magnification with special emphasis on cored A&#x003b2; plaques associated with blood vessels in subjects with a post-mortem clinical pathological diagnosis of cerebral amyloid angiopathy (CAA+). <italic>Scale Bar</italic>, 600 &#x003bc;m (A-E), <italic>insets </italic>60 &#x003bc;m (A-E). <bold>F-J</bold>. Representative paraffin embedded formalin fixed hippocampi from human AD (F, G), PA (H, I) and NDC (J) subjects were stained with anti-phosphorylated tau (CP13). Insets highlight phorphorylated tau containing tangles and neuritic structures. <italic>Scale Bar</italic>, 600 &#x003bc;m (A-E), <italic>insets </italic>60 &#x003bc;m (A-E). A&#x003b2;, amyloid &#x003b2;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt121-1"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Immunohistochemical characterization of A&#x003b2;1-40 and A&#x003b2;1-42 in Alzheimer's disease (AD), pathological aging (PA) and normal non-demented controls (NDC)</bold>. <bold>A-E</bold>. Representative paraffin embedded formalin fixed hippocampi from human AD (A, B), PA (C, D) and control (NDC; E) subjects were stained with 13.1.1 antibody (A&#x003b2;35-40). Insets show higher magnification with special emphasis on cored A&#x003b2; plaques associated with blood vessels in subjects with a post-mortem clinical pathological diagnosis of cerebral amyloid angiopathy (CAA+). <italic>Scale Bar</italic>, 600 &#x003bc;m (A-E), <italic>insets </italic>60 &#x003bc;m (A-E). <bold>F-J</bold>. Representative paraffin embedded formalin fixed hippocampi from human AD (A, B), PA (C, D) and control (NDC; E) subjects were stained with 2.1.3 antibody (A&#x003b2;35-42). Insets show higher magnification with special emphasis on cored A&#x003b2; plaques associated with blood vessels in subjects with a post-mortem clinical pathological diagnosis of cerebral amyloid angiopathy (CAA+). <italic>Scale Bar</italic>, 600 &#x003bc;m (A-E), <italic>insets </italic>60 &#x003bc;m (A-E). A&#x003b2;, amyloid &#x003b2;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt121-2"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Biochemical results of A&#x003b2; levels in AD, PA and NDC</title><p>We analyzed A&#x003b2; levels from sequentially extracted brain lysates using four different anti-A&#x003b2; antibody combinations to detect A&#x003b2;1-40, A&#x003b2;1-42, A&#x003b2;total and NH<sub>2</sub>-truncated A&#x003b2;x-42 species (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). In each of our A&#x003b2; ELISAs the detection limit was approximately 0.04 pmol/g. Compared to the 2% SDS and 70% FA extracted fractions, minimal A&#x003b2; was detected in the TBS and RIPA fractions. For example, in AD extracts the mean total A&#x003b2; measured was 1.0, 1.0, 184 and 2,065 pmol/g for the TBS, RIPA, 2% SDS and 70% FA extracts, respectively (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). The levels of total A&#x003b2; in PA lysates were 0.8, 0.6, 87 and 1,490 pmol/g for the TBS, RIPA 2% SDS and 70% FA extracts, respectively (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Thus, the sequential solubility of the A&#x003b2; was similar in AD and PA. In NDC brain extracts the levels of total A&#x003b2; were 0.2, 0.4, 7 and 38 pmol/g for the TBS, RIPA, 2% SDS and 70% FA extracts, respectively (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Thus, a major difference between AD, PA, and controls, is the dramatic increase in A&#x003b2; that requires either 2% SDS or 70% FA to solubilize, suggesting that both AD and PA cohorts had dramatically increased levels of insoluble aggregates of A&#x003b2;.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Biochemical analysis of A&#x003b2; from human brain lysates</bold>. Human prefrontal cortical tissue from Alzheimer's disease (AD), pathological aging (PA) and normal controls (NDC) was sequentially extracted with TBS (<bold>A</bold>), RIPA (<bold>B</bold>), 2% SDS (<bold>C</bold>) and 70% FA (<bold>D</bold>). End-specific sandwich ELISAs measuring A&#x003b2;1-40, A&#x003b2;1-42, A&#x003b2;total and A&#x003b2;x-42 are presented for each of these fractions. <italic>N </italic>= 16 (AD), 8 (PA) and 6 (NDC). (***<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.001, **<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.01, *<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.05 by ANOVA with tukey post-hoc analysis raw data analyzed (<bold>A, B</bold>) and log-transformed data analyzed (<bold>C, D</bold>)). A&#x003b2;, amyloid &#x003b2;; ANOVA, analysis of variance; ELISA, enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay; FA, formic acid; RIPA, radioimmunoprecipitation buffer; SDS, sodium dodecyl sulfate; TBS, Tris buffered saline.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt121-3"/></fig><p>On average, AD and PA lysates exhibited much higher levels of A&#x003b2; than NDC samples, with mean A&#x003b2; levels in each PA lysate ranging from almost equivalent to approximately 50% less than the A&#x003b2; level detected in AD lysates (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Although not reaching significance in each analysis, there were clear differences between the average levels of A&#x003b2; in AD and PA extracts as compared to NDC. There was also extensive overlap between individual A&#x003b2; levels in PA and AD as shown in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>, Figure S1.</p></sec><sec><title>Profiling of A&#x003b2; peptides by immunoprecipitation/mass spectrometry (IP/MS)</title><p>We next analyzed the lysates by IP/MS to identify various A&#x003b2; peptides associated with AD, PA and NDC cohorts. We used sequential immunoprecipitations using two non-overlapping anti-A&#x003b2; antibodies, Ab9 (anti-A&#x003b2;1-16) followed by 4G8 (anti-A&#x003b2;17-24), as our pilot studies suggested that predominant species (detected by Ab9) obscure less abundant peptides, and that Ab9 does not capture all NH<sub>2</sub>-terminally truncated A&#x003b2; peptides. Spectra from the TBS and RIPA lysates had low signal to noise ratio attributable to the low amounts (0 to 4 pmol/g) of A&#x003b2; in these samples limiting our ability to definitively identify A&#x003b2; peptides. In contrast, high quality spectra were obtained for the vast majority of the 2% SDS and 70% FA extracted lysates. Representative spectra of the 2% SDS and 70% FA extracts after immunoprecipitation with Ab9 and 4G8 are shown in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, respectively. In these spectra A&#x003b2; species were assigned to the inferred mass based on m/z. Numerous COOH- and NH<sub>2</sub>-terminal fragments of A&#x003b2; peptides were observed in a subset of the lysates from the AD, PA and NDC cohorts; however, few unique truncated peptides were identified in any patient group, and these 'unique' peptides were only detected in a minority of the samples in that group. Unique peptides that 1) have not been previously reported in other MS analyses of AD brains (for example, A&#x003b2;1-26, 9-40 and 4-40) or 2) that were uniquely present in PA (for example, A&#x003b2;1-22, 4-42 and 11-42), AD (for example, A&#x003b2;8-40, 1-37, 1-38 and 1-39) or NDC (for example, A&#x003b2;1-26, 1-27 and 2-42) are distinguished in Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref> by differential fonts. Though the profiles were overlapping between AD, PA and NDC samples (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>; Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>), there were more complex mixtures of A&#x003b2; peptides observed in a subset of the AD samples versus PA and for most of the AD and PA samples relative to control. These differences typically related to minor peaks in a subset of the spectra. This did not appear to be related to absolute levels of A&#x003b2; as they were similar to levels measured by ELISAs in the starting extracts. Notably, consistent with many previous studies, A&#x003b2;1-42 was the only species consistently detected by the Ab9 IP/MS in all AD and PA brains.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Mass spectrometric (MS) analysis following immunoprecipiation of A&#x003b2; from 2% SDS extracted lysates of human subjects</bold>. 2% SDS lysates of Alzheimer's disease (AD; <bold>A, D</bold>), pathological aging (PA; <bold>B, E</bold>) and control (NDC; <bold>C, F</bold>) subjects were subjected to immunoprecipitation with pull-down by Ab9 (A-C), sequential pull-down with Ab9 and 4 G8 (D-F). Representative MS spectra are shown (A-F). Peaks corresponding to A&#x003b2; peptides have been labeled according to m/z. A&#x003b2;1-28 was spiked in as an experimental control. The 1-42* peak denotes a possible modified A&#x003b2;1-42 species (A&#x003b2;1-42 + 16 Da, A-E). A&#x003b2;, amyloid &#x003b2;; SDS, sodium dodecyl sulfate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt121-4"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Mass spectrometric (MS) analysis following immunoprecipiation of A&#x003b2; peptides from 70% formic acid extracted lysates of human subjects</bold>. 70% formic acid extracted lysates of Alzheimer's disease (AD; <bold>A, D</bold>), pathological aging (PA; <bold>B, E</bold>) and control (NDC; <bold>C, F</bold>) cohorts were subjected to immunoprecipitation with pull-down by Ab9 (A-C), sequential pull-down with Ab9 and 4G8 (D-F). Representative MS spectra are shown. Peaks corresponding to A&#x003b2; peptides have been labeled according to m/z. A&#x003b2;1-28 was spiked in as an experimental control. Different peaks corresponding to modified A&#x003b2; are shown (4-42*, A&#x003b2;4-42 + 16 Da; 1-40*, A&#x003b2;1-40 +16 Da; 1-42**, A&#x003b2;1-42 + 22 Da). A&#x003b2;, amyloid &#x003b2;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt121-5"/></fig><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Mass spectrometric analysis of SDS soluble fraction immunoprecipitated with Ab9 from human brains reveal unique A&#x003b2; peaks.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center">A&#x003b2; Peptide</th><th align="center">predicted MW</th><th align="center">observed MW</th><th align="center">AD (<italic>n </italic>= 16)</th><th align="center">PA (<italic>n </italic>= 9)</th><th align="center">NDC (<italic>n </italic>= 8)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><underline>1-22</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>2661.82</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>2663.37</underline></td><td/><td align="center"><italic>1 (11.1%)</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center"><underline>1-26</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>3020.16</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>3021.17</underline></td><td align="center">3 (18.8%)</td><td align="center">3 (33.3%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center"><underline>8-40</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>3458.98</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>3461.27</underline></td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center"><underline>9-40</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>3371.90</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>3372.80</underline></td><td/><td align="center">2 (22.2%)</td><td align="center">1 (12.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><underline>4-40</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>4014.57</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>4016.50</underline></td><td align="center">1 (6.3%)</td><td align="center">1 (11.1%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">5-42</td><td align="center">4051.57</td><td align="center">4053.50</td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">1-38</td><td align="center">4131.52</td><td align="center">4133.95</td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">4-42</td><td align="center">4198.74</td><td align="center">4200.44</td><td align="center">7 (43.8%)</td><td align="center">3 (33.3%)</td><td align="center">2 (25%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-39</td><td align="center">4230.65</td><td align="center">4233.33</td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">1-40</td><td align="center">4329.78</td><td align="center">4331.96</td><td align="center">10 (62.5%)</td><td align="center">3 (33.3%)</td><td align="center">2 (25%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-40 +16 Da</td><td align="center">4345.78</td><td align="center">4345.96</td><td/><td align="center">1 (11.1%)</td><td align="center">2 (25%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-41</td><td align="center">4442.94</td><td align="center">4446.86</td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">2-43</td><td align="center">4500.11</td><td align="center">4503.58</td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">1-42</td><td align="center">4514.02</td><td align="center">4516.48</td><td align="center">16 (100%)</td><td align="center">9 (100%)</td><td align="center">5 (62.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-42 +16 Da</td><td align="center">4530.02</td><td align="center">4531.81</td><td align="center">8 (50%)</td><td align="center">3 (33.3%)</td><td align="center">2 (25%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-43</td><td align="center">4615.20</td><td align="center">4616.60</td><td align="center">3 (18.8%)</td><td align="center">1 (11.1%)</td><td align="center">1 (12.5%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Human brain tissue was extracted with 2% SDS and sequentially immunoprecipitated with Ab9 and 4G8 antibodies to enrich different truncated or modified A&#x003b2; peptides. Mass spectrometric analysis shows unique A&#x003b2; peptides that 1) have not been previously reported in other mass spectrometric analyses of AD brains (underlined) 2) uniquely present in AD (bold font) or PA (italicized) are differentially highlighted. Predicted molecular weights and observed molecular weights have been calculated using ExPASy PeptideMass and ProteinChip Data Manager software (Bio-Rad), respectively. The number of subjects (AD, Alzheimer's disease; PA, Pathological aging; NDC, controls) displaying each uniquely identifiable A&#x003b2; peptides and the percentage of occurrence of such peptides corresponding to the total sample size is denoted. A&#x003b2;, amyloid &#x003b2;; MW, molecular weight; n, number; SDS, sodium dodecyl sulfate.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Mass spectrometric analysis of SDS soluble fraction immunoprecipitated with 4G8 from human brains reveal unique A&#x003b2; peaks.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center">A&#x003b2; Peptide</th><th align="center">predicted MW</th><th align="center">observed MW</th><th align="center">AD (<italic>n </italic>= 16)</th><th align="center">PA (<italic>n </italic>= 9)</th><th align="center">NDC (<italic>n </italic>= 8)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">8-40</td><td align="center">3458.98</td><td align="center">3462.81</td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center"><underline>4-40</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>4014.57</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>4018.49</underline></td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">4-42</td><td align="center">4198.74</td><td align="center">4202.62</td><td align="center">4 (25.0%)</td><td align="center">3 (33.39%)</td><td align="center">1 (12.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-40</td><td align="center">4329.78</td><td align="center">4333.49</td><td align="center">3 (18.8%)</td><td/><td align="center">1 (12.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-42</td><td align="center">4514.02</td><td align="center">4516.74</td><td align="center">9 (56.3%)</td><td align="center">7 (77.80%)</td><td align="center">2 (25%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-42 +16 Da</td><td align="center">4530.02</td><td align="center">4534.90</td><td align="center">2 (12.5%)</td><td align="center">2 (22.2%)</td><td align="center">2 (25%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Human brain tissue was extracted with 2% SDS and sequentially immunoprecipitated with Ab9 and 4G8 antibodies to enrich different truncated or modified A&#x003b2; peptides. Mass spectrometric analysis shows unique A&#x003b2; peptides that 1) have not been previously reported in other mass spectrometric analyses of AD brains (underlined) 2) uniquely present in AD (bold font) are differentially highlighted. Predicted molecular weights and observed molecular weights have been calculated using ExPASy PeptideMass and ProteinChip Data Manager software (Bio-Rad), respectively. The number of subjects (AD, Alzheimer's disease; PA, Pathological aging; NDC, controls) displaying each uniquely identifiable A&#x003b2; peptide and the percentage of occurrence of such peptides corresponding to the total sample size is denoted. A&#x003b2;, amyloid &#x003b2;; MW, molecular weight; n, number; SDS, sodium dodecyl sulfate.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Mass spectrometric analysis of formic acid (FA) fraction immunoprecipitated with Ab9 from human brains reveal unique A&#x003b2; peaks.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center">A&#x003b2; Peptide</th><th align="center">predicted MW</th><th align="center">observed MW</th><th align="center">AD (<italic>n </italic>= 16)</th><th align="center">PA (<italic>n </italic>= 9)</th><th align="center">NDC (<italic>n </italic>= 8)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">1-18</td><td align="center">2167.28</td><td align="center">2167.70</td><td align="center"><bold>2 (12.5%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center"><underline>1-26</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>3020.16</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>3021.02</underline></td><td/><td/><td align="center"><bold>
<italic>2 (25%)</italic>
</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center">pE11-40</td><td align="center">3115.65</td><td align="center">3151.47</td><td/><td/><td align="center"><bold>
<italic>1 (12.5%)</italic>
</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-27</td><td align="center">3134.27</td><td align="center">3134.77</td><td/><td/><td align="center"><bold>
<italic>1 (12.5%)</italic>
</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center">pE11-42</td><td align="center">3317.90</td><td align="center">3318.91</td><td align="center">1 (6.3%)</td><td align="center">2 (22.2%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center"><underline>9-40</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>3371.90</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>3372.97</underline></td><td align="center">8 (50%)</td><td align="center">6 (66.7%)</td><td align="center">5 (62.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-30 +16 Da</td><td align="center">3406.57</td><td align="center">3409.22</td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">1-36</td><td align="center">4017.42</td><td align="center">4019.60</td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">1-37</td><td align="center">4074.47</td><td align="center">4076.58</td><td align="center"><bold>2 (12.5%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">1-37 +16 Da</td><td align="center">4090.47</td><td align="center">4094.07</td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">1-38</td><td align="center">4131.52</td><td align="center">4134.52</td><td align="center"><bold>4 (25.0%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">1-38 + 16 Da</td><td align="center">4147.52</td><td align="center">4150.11</td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">4-42</td><td align="center">4198.74</td><td align="center">4200.32</td><td/><td align="center"><italic>2 (22.2%)</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">4-42 +16 Da</td><td align="center">4214.74</td><td align="center">4216.78</td><td align="center">1 (6.3%)</td><td align="center">1 (11.1%)</td><td align="center">1 (12.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-39</td><td align="center">4230.65</td><td align="center">4232.14</td><td align="center">2 (12.5%)</td><td align="center">1 (11.1%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center"><underline>3-41</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>4256.85</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>4260.60</underline></td><td align="center">2 (12.5%)</td><td align="center">1 (11.1%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">pE3-42</td><td align="center">4309.90</td><td align="center">4312.76</td><td/><td align="center"><italic>1 (11.1%)</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">1-40</td><td align="center">4329.78</td><td align="center">4332.14</td><td align="center">12 (75.0%)</td><td align="center">6 (66.7%)</td><td align="center">2 (25%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-40 +16 Da</td><td align="center">4345.78</td><td align="center">4347.41</td><td align="center">7 (43.8%)</td><td align="center">1 (11.1%)</td><td align="center">1 (12.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">2-42</td><td align="center">4395.93</td><td align="center">4399.63</td><td/><td/><td align="center"><bold>
<italic>1 (12.5%)</italic>
</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-41</td><td align="center">4442.94</td><td align="center">4444.51</td><td align="center">1 (6.3%)</td><td align="center">1 (11.1%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">1-42</td><td align="center">4514.02</td><td align="center">4516.58</td><td align="center">16 (100%)</td><td align="center">9 (100%)</td><td align="center">4 (50%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-42 +16 Da</td><td align="center">4530.02</td><td align="center">4532.13</td><td align="center">9 (56.3%)</td><td align="center">4 (44.4%)</td><td align="center">1 (12.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-43</td><td align="center">4615.20</td><td align="center">4617.58</td><td align="center">4 (25.0%)</td><td align="center">3 (33.3%)</td><td align="center">1 (12.5%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Human brain tissue, extracted with 70% FA, was sequentially immunoprecipitated with Ab9 and 4G8 antibodies to enrich different truncated or modified A&#x003b2; species. Mass spectrometric analysis shows unique A&#x003b2; peptides that 1) have not been previously reported in other mass spectrometric analyses of AD brains (underlined) 2) uniquely present in AD (bold font), PA (italicized font) or controls (bold and italicized font) are differentially highlighted. Predicted molecular weights and observed molecular weights have been calculated using ExPASy PeptideMass and ProteinChip Data Manager software (Bio-Rad), respectively. The number of subjects (AD, Alzheimer's disease; PA, Pathological aging; NDC, controls) displaying each uniquely identifiable A&#x003b2; peptide and the percentage of occurrence of such peptide corresponding to the total sample size is denoted. A&#x003b2;, amyloid &#x003b2;; MW, molecular weight; n, number.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T5" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Mass spectrometric analysis of formic acid (FA) fraction immunoprecipitated with 4G8 from human brains reveal unique A&#x003b2; peaks.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center">A&#x003b2; Peptide</th><th align="center">predicted MW</th><th align="center">observed MW</th><th align="center">AD (<italic>n </italic>= 16)</th><th align="center">PA (<italic>n </italic>= 9)</th><th align="center">NDC (<italic>n </italic>= 8)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">1-18</td><td align="center">2167.28</td><td align="center">2165.21</td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">1-27</td><td align="center">3134.27</td><td align="center">3135.30</td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">E11-42</td><td align="center">3317.90</td><td align="center">3320.02</td><td align="center">8 (50.0%)</td><td align="center">7 (77.8%)</td><td align="center">1 (12.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-29</td><td align="center">3319.49</td><td align="center">3320.87</td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">11-42</td><td align="center">3335.90</td><td align="center">3328.79</td><td/><td align="center"><italic>1 (11.1%)</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center"><underline>9-40</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>3371.90</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>3373.39</underline></td><td align="center">3 (18.8%)</td><td align="center">5 (55.6%)</td><td align="center">4 (50%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><underline>8-40</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>3458.98</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>3460.65</underline></td><td align="center">1 (6.3%)</td><td align="center">1 (11.1%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">1-31</td><td align="center">3503.72</td><td align="center">3503.55</td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">9-42</td><td align="center">3556.08</td><td align="center">3557.85</td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">8-42</td><td align="center">3643.15</td><td align="center">3644.86</td><td align="center">5 (31.3%)</td><td/><td align="center">1 (12.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">7-42</td><td align="center">3758.24</td><td align="center">3758.89</td><td align="center"><bold>2 (12.5%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">1-34</td><td align="center">3787.09</td><td align="center">3786.56</td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">1-35</td><td align="center">3918.29</td><td align="center">3918.96</td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center"><underline>4-40</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>4014.57</underline></td><td align="center"><underline>4016.85</underline></td><td align="center">1 (6.3%)</td><td align="center">1 (11.1%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">1-36</td><td align="center">4017.42</td><td align="center">4018.25</td><td align="center">1 (6.3%)</td><td align="center">1 (11.1%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">5-42</td><td align="center">4051.57</td><td align="center">4053.59</td><td align="center">4 (25.0%)</td><td/><td align="center">1 (12.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-37</td><td align="center">4074.47</td><td align="center">4075.25</td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">1-38</td><td align="center">4131.52</td><td align="center">4131.33</td><td align="center">1 (6.3%)</td><td align="center">1 (11.1%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">4-42</td><td align="center">4198.74</td><td align="center">4201.29</td><td/><td align="center">5 (55.6%)</td><td align="center">2 (25%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">4-42 +16 Da</td><td align="center">4214.74</td><td align="center">4217.09</td><td align="center">2 (12.5%)</td><td align="center">1 (11.1%)</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">1-39</td><td align="center">4230.65</td><td align="center">4231.46</td><td align="center"><bold>1 (6.3%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">E3-42</td><td align="center">4309.90</td><td align="center">4312.76</td><td align="center">4 (25.0%)</td><td align="center">3 (33.3%)</td><td align="center">1 (12.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-40</td><td align="center">4329.78</td><td align="center">4331.85</td><td align="center">8 (50.0%)</td><td align="center">5 (55.6%)</td><td align="center">2 (25%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-40 +16 Da</td><td align="center">4345.78</td><td align="center">4348.09</td><td align="center"><bold>4 (25.0%)</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">1-42</td><td align="center">4514.02</td><td align="center">4516.70</td><td align="center">10 (62.5%)</td><td align="center">7 (77.8%)</td><td align="center">4 (50%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-42 +16 Da</td><td align="center">4530.02</td><td align="center">4533.03</td><td/><td/><td align="center"><bold>
<italic>1 (12.5%)</italic>
</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Human brain tissue, extracted with 70% FA, was sequentially immunoprecipitated with Ab9 and 4G8 antibodies to enrich different truncated or modified A&#x003b2; species. Mass spectrometric analysis shows unique A&#x003b2; peptides that 1) have not been previously reported in other mass spectrometric analyses of AD brains (underlined) 2) uniquely present in AD (bold font), PA (italicized font) or controls (bold and italicized font) are differentially highlighted. Predicted molecular weights and observed molecular weights have been calculated using ExPASy PeptideMass and ProteinChip Data Manager software (Bio-Rad), respectively. The number of subjects (AD, Alzheimer's disease; PA, Pathological aging; NDC, controls) displaying each uniquely identifiable A&#x003b2; peptide and the percentage of occurrence of such peptide corresponding to the total sample size is denoted. A&#x003b2;, amyloid &#x003b2;; MW, molecular weight; n, number.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Summary of SDS soluble A&#x003b2; peptides in test subjects</bold>. 2% SDS extracted lysates from human prefrontal cortical tissues were subjected to immunoprecipitation with pull-down by Ab9 (<bold>A</bold>) or sequential pull-down with Ab9 and 4G8 (<bold>B</bold>), followed by MS. Data are graphically presented as a percentage of subjects in each cohort (Alzheimer's disease (AD), Pathological aging (PA) or controls (NDC)) containing A&#x003b2; peptides (x-axis). <italic>N </italic>= 16 (AD), 8 (PA) and 6 (NDC). A&#x003b2;, amyloid &#x003b2;; MS, mass spectrometry; N, number; SDS, sodium dodecyl sulfate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt121-6"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>Summary of formic acid soluble A&#x003b2; peptides in test subjects</bold>. 70% FA extracted lysates from human prefrontal cortical tissue were subjected to immunoprecipitation with pull-down by Ab9 (<bold>A</bold>) or sequential pull-down with Ab9 and 4G8 (<bold>B</bold>), followed by MS. Data are graphically presented as a percentage of subjects in each cohort (Alzheimer's disease (AD), Pathological aging (PA) or controls (NDC)) containing A&#x003b2; peptides (x-axis). <italic>N </italic>= 16 (AD), 8 (PA) and 6 (NDC). A&#x003b2;, amyloid &#x003b2;; FA, formic acid; MS, mass spectrometry; N, number.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt121-7"/></fig><p>Several modified A&#x003b2; peptides, that were consistent with a 16 Da increase in mass, were observed. This mass shift is typically indicative of oxidation. Control studies demonstrated that the methodology used did not induce oxidation of reduced synthetic A&#x003b2;. Thus, there was evidence that A&#x003b2;1-30, 1-37, 1-38, 1-40 and 1-42 were present in the brain as oxidized species. In most cases the peptides were detected in only a few samples among the cohort sets and there were no notable differences in the rate of detection between AD, PA and controls. However, oxidized A&#x003b2; peptides were detected more frequently in AD cases with CAA (ten of ten) compared to cases without CAA (one of six). This association was not apparent in PA where oxidized A&#x003b2; peptides were detected in two of four cases with and three of five cases without CAA. Three peaks, consistent with pyroglutamate A&#x003b2;, were detected in the 70% FA fraction of AD, PA and controls: A&#x003b2;pE11-40, A&#x003b2;pE11-42 and A&#x003b2;pE3-42. These species were not detected in the 2% SDS lysates suggesting that they are highly insoluble.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunoblotting analysis of A&#x003b2; species</title><p>We next analyzed these samples by SDS-PAGE followed by Western Blot. The representative blots shown were separated by electrophoresis, transferred to nitrocellulose, not boiled and stained with 82E1 antibody (anti-A&#x003b2;1-16) (IBL). We found that this method gave the most sensitive detection and, based on estimates, our detection limit was 1 to 10 pmol monomeric A&#x003b2;. A number of Western Blots failed to differentiate oligomer assemblies between PA and AD in TBS and 2% SDS lysates (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>) and RIPA lysates (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref>). We detected a 10 kDa band in the TBS and RIPA lysates of AD, PA and NDC cohorts. This band could be an oligomeric assembly of A&#x003b2;, an APP &#x003b2;-C-terminal fragment (since there is cross-reactivity of these two species with 82E1) or a non-specific band. This band was consistently detected with other anti-A&#x003b2; antibodies, although these other antibodies had lower limits of sensitivity.</p><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><bold>Immunoblot analysis of A&#x003b2; species from sequentially extracted human prefrontal cortical tissue lysates</bold>. Human hippocampi from Alzheimer's disease (AD), pathological aging (PA) and normal (N) cohorts were sequentially extracted with TBS, 2% SDS extracted lysates from human subjects. Representative immunoblots probed with 82E1 antibody are shown. Control lanes includes cell lysates expressing C99 (CTF&#x003b2;) and recombinant A&#x003b2;1-42 (43 pmol). A&#x003b2;, amyloid &#x003b2;; SDS, sodium dodecyl sulfate; TBS, Tris buffered saline.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt121-8"/></fig><fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p><bold>Immunoblot analysis of A&#x003b2; species from RIPA soluble lysates from human subjects</bold>. Human hippocampi from Alzheimer's disease (AD), pathological aging (PA) and normal (N) cohorts were extracted with RIPA. Representative anti-82E1 immunoblot of RIPA extracted lysates of Alzheimer's disease (AD), pathologic aging (PA) and control (N) subjects with (<bold>A</bold>) and without (<bold>B</bold>) a post-mortem clinical pathological diagnosis of cerebral amyloid angiopathy (+CAA). Longer exposure panels below highlight no significant differences between the three cohorts in the dimer/trimer molecular weight range. A&#x003b2;, amyloid &#x003b2;; RIPA, radioimmunoprecipitation buffer.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt121-9"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study we systematically characterized A&#x003b2; levels and solubility, peptide profiles and oligomeric assemblies in a postmortem series of PA, AD and NDC cohorts. Using a panel of A&#x003b2; sandwich ELISAs we appraised the levels of A&#x003b2;1-40, A&#x003b2;1-42 and A&#x003b2;total, as well as A&#x003b2;x-42. We found extensive overlap in A&#x003b2; levels between AD and PA brains. On average, AD and PA lysates contained much more A&#x003b2; than NDC samples. A&#x003b2; levels in PA lysates were similar to the levels in the AD lysates, ranging from almost equivalent to approximately 50% less than the A&#x003b2; detected in AD lysates and solubility profiles were similar with the vast majority of A&#x003b2; in PA and AD requiring either SDS or FA to solubilize.</p><p>We examined A&#x003b2; peptide profiles by IP/MS in AD, PA and NDC patient brain lysates. A&#x003b2;1-42 was identified as the predominant peak in the SDS and FA 'insoluble' fractions across all groups. As noted above, it was the only A&#x003b2; peptide detected by IP/MS in all PA and AD cases. In addition, several unique NH<sub>2</sub>- and COOH-terminal truncated A&#x003b2; peptides were observed in the AD brain lysates. However, few unique truncated A&#x003b2; peptides were observed in any one patient group and these peptides represented minor peaks. These truncated peptides may represent alternate cleavage products by &#x003b2;- and &#x003b3;-secretases or products of A&#x003b2; degradation.</p><p>Interestingly, we detected peaks that correspond to A&#x003b2;1-30, 1-37, 1-38, 1-40 and 1-42 with a 16 Da mass shift that we hypothesize to be oxidation products of A&#x003b2;. Oxidation of these A&#x003b2; peptides could be an artifact due to the extraction and IP/MS techniques utilized in this study; however, this is unlikely since we did not observe the mass shift in other detected A&#x003b2; peptides or in control IP/MS studies using reduced synthetic A&#x003b2;. Although A&#x003b2; is composed of several amino acids that could be oxidized, most studies have suggested oxidation occurs primarily at the methionine residue at position 35 (Met-35) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. A number of studies suggest that oxidized A&#x003b2; peptides are present in the brain and that oxidation of A&#x003b2;1-42 decreases the rate of aggregation, disrupts fibril morphology and inhibits oligomerization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. Oxidized A&#x003b2; peptides were observed as minor peaks in the spectra, indicating that these represent a minor fraction of total A&#x003b2; since control studies showed that both peptides ionized at the same levels. There were no striking differences in oxidized peptides between AD and PA patients. However, remarkably all of the AD patients with CAA had oxidized A&#x003b2; peptides while only one of six AD patients without CAA had oxidized A&#x003b2; peptides.</p><p>We detected peaks corresponding to pyroglutamate modified A&#x003b2; (A&#x003b2;pE), at position 11, A&#x003b2;pE11-40, A&#x003b2;pE11-42, and at position 3, A&#x003b2;pE3-42, in the insoluble lysates of AD, PA and NDC. A&#x003b2;pE is formed by glutamate cyclization at position 11 by glutaminyl cyclase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. The conversion of glutamate to pyroglutamate is reported to protect the A&#x003b2; peptide from degradation through resistance to aminopeptidases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. A&#x003b2;pE is also reported to be highly prone to oligomerization and can possibly seed the oligomerization and fibrillation process of full-length A&#x003b2; species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. Based on these data as well as other studies examining A&#x003b2;pE levels and animal modeling studies that manipulate A&#x003b2;pE levels, an initiating role for A&#x003b2;pE in AD has been proposed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>]. Although our detection of A&#x003b2;pE in a control brain would not be inconsistent with a postulated role in seeding aggregation, its presence in some PA brains suggest that its toxicity is not inherently different from other aggregated A&#x003b2; peptides.</p><p>There is currently much debate regarding which types of A&#x003b2; aggregates are the most toxic. A&#x003b2; rapidly forms stable fibrillar amyloid structures, which account for much of the A&#x003b2; that accumulates in the AD brain. Over the last decade, a variety of soluble oligomeric species, including dimers, trimers, tetramers and 10-12-mers have been identified and isolated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]. These oligomers have been shown to be biologically active as they inhibit hippocampal long-term potentiation and create memory impairments when injected into rodents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>]. Additional circumstantial data suggests that oligomeric assemblies may account for some of the behavioral deficits observed in APP mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>]. As there is no standard methodology to detect oligomeric assemblies, we empirically settled on a method that was the most sensitive in our hands, and also would enable us to survey oligomeric assemblies in multiple brain lysates. This survey revealed that there were no obvious differences in higher molecular weight bands between AD, PA and NDC. Our data are consistent with a recent publication that reported a more extensive analysis of oligomeric assemblies and also failed to detect major differences in PA and AD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Indeed, it is not the relatively small increases in the TBS and RIPA extractable A&#x003b2; pools but that of the SDS and 70% FA extractable insoluble A&#x003b2; pools that clearly distinguish both AD and PA from controls.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In summary, we investigated A&#x003b2; levels, peptides and assemblies from soluble, detergent-soluble and insoluble pools from AD, PA and NDC brain. We found only subtle quantitative differences between PA and AD brains that, in most cases, did not reach significance. We found overlap between the PA and AD A&#x003b2; peptide profile, as examined by IP/MS, but AD patients contained additional amino terminal truncated A&#x003b2; peptides. There were no major differences observed in SDS-stable A&#x003b2; oligomeric assemblies. We cannot rule out the possibility that there are conformational differences or very subtle differences in minor A&#x003b2; peptides or assemblies that distinguish AD from PA; however, our data, which shows extensive similarities between deposited A&#x003b2; in AD and PA, would indicate that PA is not likely to represent a form of benign A&#x003b2; deposition. Indeed, our data are more consistent with the hypothesis that PA represents an initial prodromal stage of AD and that these individuals would eventually go on to develop clinical symptoms, if they live long enough [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. Notably, PA brains do not completely lack cortical tau pathology; however, pathological phospho-tau levels are present in lower levels compared to AD (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Indeed, given predictions of the amyloid cascade hypothesis, many of which are being demonstrated in living humans via imaging and cerebrospinal fluid studies, one would predict that a subset of cognitively normal subjects would die with heavy amyloid loads but limited tau pathology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]. This possibility needs to be taken into account in the debate regarding identification of the toxic A&#x003b2; species. We should not discount the role of insoluble fibrillar assemblies in driving downstream pathologies; assemblies may produce an insidious form of cellular toxicity that may be difficult to assess in more acute experimental models. This concept may best be phrased that amyloid-like assemblies are necessary but not sufficient to drive neurodegeneration. Although speculative, it is also possible that PA patients may be protected from the downstream effects of A&#x003b2;. In the latter case, genetic studies, gene expression profiling, or perhaps even development of induced pluripotent stem cells from PA subjects could identify factors that confer protection from A&#x003b2;. Ultimately, in order to determine whether PA represents a prodromal phase of AD or could reflect inherent resistance to A&#x003b2;, long-term longitudinal amyloid imaging, biomarker studies, and postmortem neuropathological examination will be needed. If powered sufficiently such studies could determine whether there are subsets of individuals who develop AD-like plaque pathology but retain normal cognitive function without neurodegeneration after extended periods of time or whether parenchymal A&#x003b2; accumulation invariably leads to neurodegeneration and AD.</p></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>A&#x003b2;: amyloid-beta; AD: Alzheimer's disease; APP: amyloid &#x003b2; protein precursor; CAA: cerebral amyloid angiopathy; ELISA: enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay; FA: formic acid; HRP: horseradish peroxidase; IP/MS: immunoprecipitation/mass spectrometry; mAb: monoclonal antibody; PA: pathological aging; NDC: non-demented controls; RIPA: radioimmunoprecipitation buffer; SDS: sodium dodecyl sulfate; TBS: Tris buffered saline.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>BDM, TEG and PD conceived and designed the study. DWD provided human samples and contributed to critical discussions. BDM, PC, AMB, TM and TL prepared samples and acquired data. BDM and TEG drafted the manuscript. BDM, PC, YL, TK, PD and TEG contributed to the interpretation of findings. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional file 1</title><p><bold>Figure S1</bold>. Biochemical analysis of A&#x003b2; levels from human brain lysates. A panel of sandwich ELISAs measuring A&#x003b2;1-40, A&#x003b2;1-42, A&#x003b2;total and A&#x003b2;x-42 from brain lysates sequentially extracted with TBS (A), RIPA (B), 2% SDS (C) and 70% formic acid (D) is shown. Data are presented as scatter dot plots, <italic>n </italic>= 16 (AD), 8 (PA) and 6 (NDC). (***<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.001, **<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.01, *<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.05 by ANOVA with tukey post-hoc analysis raw data analyzed (A, B) and log-transformed data analyzed (C, D)).</p></caption><media xlink:href="alzrt121-S1.TIFF" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are grateful to all patients, family members and caregivers who agreed to brain donation, without which these studies would not have been possible. We also acknowledge the expert technical assistance of Monica Casey-Castanedes, Linda Rousseau and Virginia Phillips for immunohistochemistry and for histology. This research was funded by the Mayo Clinic Alzheimer's Disease Research Center Pilot Project Grant (AG16574) and the NIH AG20206 (TEG).</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Crystal</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bevona</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Honer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Correlations of synaptic and pathological markers with cognition of the elderly</article-title><source>Neurobiol Aging</source><year>1995</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><comment>discussion 298-304</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0197-4580(95)00013-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7566338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Crystal</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattiace</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Masur</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Blau</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Aronson</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><article-title>Identification of normal and pathological aging in prospectively studied nondemented elderly humans</article-title><source>Neurobiol Aging</source><year>1992</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0197-4580(92)90027-U</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1311804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Golde</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Filling the gaps in the Ab cascade hypothesis of Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>Curr Alz Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/156720506779025189</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacova</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekosky</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Barberger-Gateau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Delacourte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Frisoni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Galasko</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hampel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jicha</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mequro</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasquier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salloway</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarazin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheltens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Revising the definition of Alzheimer's disease: a new lexicon</article-title><source>Lancet Neurol</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1118</fpage><lpage>1127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(10)70223-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20934914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Reinhard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>De Strooper</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>The amyloid-beta precursor protein: integrating structure with biological function</article-title><source>Embo J</source><year>2005</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>3996</fpage><lpage>4006</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.emboj.7600860</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16252002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>De Strooper</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Vassar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Golde</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>The secretases: enzymes with therapeutic potential in Alzheimer disease</article-title><source>Nat Rev Neurol</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrneurol.2009.218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20139999</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Tur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Golde</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>The presenilin 1 C92S mutation increases abeta 42 production</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2000</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.2000.3646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11027672</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweeney</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gandy</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sisodia</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><article-title>The profile of soluble amyloid beta protein in cultured cell media. Detection and quantification of amyloid beta protein and variants by immunoprecipitation-mass spectrometry</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>31894</fpage><lpage>31902</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.271.50.31894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8943233</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Younkin</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><article-title>The role of A beta 42 in Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>J Physiol Paris</source><year>1998</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0928-4257(98)80035-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9789825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Suemoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Brouwers</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sleegers</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Funamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mihira</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuba</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Broeckhoven</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Saido</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><article-title>Potent amyloidogenicity and pathogenicity of Abeta43</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><year>2011</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1023</fpage><lpage>1032</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.2858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21725313</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lewczuk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Esselmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Groemer</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bibl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maler</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinacker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kornhuber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiltfang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Amyloid beta peptides in cerebrospinal fluid as profiled with surface enhanced laser desorption/ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometry: evidence of novel biomarkers in Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>Biol Psychiatry</source><year>2004</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>524</fpage><lpage>530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2003.10.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15023581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lewczuk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Esselmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wollscheid</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maler</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruther</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kornhuber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiltfang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>The amyloid-beta (Abeta) peptide pattern in cerebrospinal fluid in Alzheimer's disease: evidence of a novel carboxyterminally elongated Abeta peptide</article-title><source>Rapid Commun Mass Spectrom</source><year>2003</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1291</fpage><lpage>1296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/rcm.1048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12811752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wiltfang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Esselmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cupers</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kretzschmar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Beyermann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schleuder</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jahn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruther</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kornhuber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Annaert</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>De Strooper</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Saftiq</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Elevation of beta-amyloid peptide 2-42 in sporadic and familial Alzheimer's disease and its generation in PS1 knockout cells</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>42645</fpage><lpage>42657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M102790200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11526104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Head</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Garzon-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lott</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotman</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Glabe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Oxidation of Abeta and plaque biogenesis in Alzheimer's disease and Down syndrome</article-title><source>Neurobiol Dis</source><year>2001</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>792</fpage><lpage>806</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/nbdi.2001.0431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11592849</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Naslund</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schierhorn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellman</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Lannfelt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Roses</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tjernberg</surname><given-names>LO</given-names></name><name><surname>Silberring</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gandy</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Winblad</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Greengard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordstedt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Terenius</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Relative abundance of Alzheimer A beta amyloid peptide variants in Alzheimer disease and normal aging</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1994</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>8378</fpage><lpage>8382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.91.18.8378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8078890</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Beach</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sue</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Layne</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kokjohn</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalback</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Luehrs</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Vishnivetskaya</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Abramowski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sturchler-Pierrat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Staufenbiel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Weller</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name><name><surname>Roher</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><article-title>The evolution of A beta peptide burden in the APP23 transgenic mice: implications for A beta deposition in Alzheimer disease</article-title><source>Mol Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>609</fpage><lpage>618</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11778650</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boutte</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Woltjer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stamer</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Montine</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Manno</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Cimino</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liebler</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Montine</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><article-title>Selectively increased oxidative modifications mapped to detergent-insoluble forms of Abeta and beta-III tubulin in Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>2006</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1473</fpage><lpage>1483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.06-5920com</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16816122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrow</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><article-title>The A beta 3-pyroglutamyl and 11-pyroglutamyl peptides found in senile plaque have greater beta-sheet forming and aggregation propensities in vitro than full-length A beta</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1999</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>10871</fpage><lpage>10877</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi990563r</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10451383</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Violani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Salis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Venezia</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolcini</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Damonte</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Benatti</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Arrigo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Patrone</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schettini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Pyroglutamate-modified amyloid beta-peptides--AbetaN3(pE)--strongly affect cultured neuron and astrocyte survival</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2002</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>1480</fpage><lpage>1489</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1471-4159.2002.01107.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12354296</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauber</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaupp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Manhart</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohm</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Demuth</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name><article-title>On the seeding and oligomerization of pGlu-amyloid peptides (in vitro)</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2006</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>12393</fpage><lpage>12399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi0612667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17029395</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wirths</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Breyhan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cynis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Demuth</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><article-title>Intraneuronal pyroglutamate-Abeta 3-42 triggers neurodegeneration and lethal neurological deficits in a transgenic mouse model</article-title><source>Acta Neuropathol</source><year>2009</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00401-009-0557-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19547991</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hartlage-Rubsamen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Morawski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Waniek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeitschel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cynis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schliebs</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Demuth</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Glutaminyl cyclase contributes to the formation of focal and diffuse pyroglutamate (pGlu)-Abeta deposits in hippocampus via distinct cellular mechanisms</article-title><source>Acta Neuropathol</source><year>2011</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>705</fpage><lpage>719</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00401-011-0806-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21301857</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lansbury</surname><given-names>PT</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><article-title>Models of amyloid seeding in Alzheimer's disease and scrapie: mechanistic truths and physiological consequences of the time-dependent solubility of amyloid proteins</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biochem</source><year>1997</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>385</fpage><lpage>407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.biochem.66.1.385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9242912</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lomakin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Teplow</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirschner</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Benedek</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><article-title>Kinetic theory of fibrillogenesis of amyloid beta-protein</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1997</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>7942</fpage><lpage>7947</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.94.15.7942</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9223292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Selkoe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><article-title>The amyloid hypothesis of Alzheimer's disease: progress and problems on the road to therapeutics</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>297</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1072994</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12130773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hartley</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Diehl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasquez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vassilev</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Teplow</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Selkoe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><article-title>Protofibrillar intermediates of amyloid beta-protein induce acute electrophysiological changes and progressive neurotoxicity in cortical neurons</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>1999</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>8876</fpage><lpage>8884</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10516307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Krafft</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Finch</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><article-title>Targeting small Abeta oligomers: the solution to an Alzheimer's disease conundrum?</article-title><source>Trends Neurosci</source><year>2001</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0166-2236(00)01749-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11250006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Westerman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper-Blacketer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mariash</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotilinek</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawarabayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Younkin</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Younkin</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashe</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><article-title>The relationship between Abeta and memory in the Tg2576 mouse model of Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2002</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1858</fpage><lpage>1867</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11880515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kawarabayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Younkin</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen-Lang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsubara</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashe</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Younkin</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><article-title>Dimeric amyloid beta protein rapidly accumulates in lipid rafts followed by apolipoprotein E and phosphorylated tau accumulation in the Tg2576 mouse model of Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2004</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>3801</fpage><lpage>3809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5543-03.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15084661</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McGowan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickford</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Onstead</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriksen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Skipper</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Beard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Delucia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolios</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckman</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Golde</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>Abeta42 is essential for parenchymal and vascular amyloid deposition in mice</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2005</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2005.06.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16039562</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Golde</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><article-title>Anti-abeta therapeutics in Alzheimer's disease: the need for a paradigm shift</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2011</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2011.01.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21262461</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jack</surname><given-names>CR</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigand</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiste</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Senjem</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Knopman</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiung</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunter</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Boeve</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><article-title>Serial PIB and MRI in normal, mild cognitive impairment and Alzheimer's disease: implications for sequence of pathological events in Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>Brain</source><year>2009</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>1355</fpage><lpage>1365</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awp062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19339253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojanowski</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><article-title>The levels of soluble versus insoluble brain Abeta distinguish Alzheimer's disease from normal and pathologic aging</article-title><source>Exp Neurol</source><year>1999</year><volume>158</volume><fpage>328</fpage><lpage>337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/exnr.1999.7085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10415140</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maarouf</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Daugs</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name><name><surname>Kokjohn</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kruchowsky</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Woltjer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Castano</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabbagh</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Beach</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Roher</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><article-title>Alzheimer's disease and non-demented high pathology control nonagenarians: comparing and contrasting the biochemistry of cognitively successful aging</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e27291</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22087282</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Munoz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepardson</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemere</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Regan</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabatini</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Selkoe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><article-title>Amyloid-beta protein dimers isolated directly from Alzheimer's brains impair synaptic plasticity and memory</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>837</fpage><lpage>842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm1782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18568035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Saido</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><source>Alzheimer's Disease: Biology, Diagnosis and Therapeutics</source><year>1997</year><publisher-name>New York: Wiley</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>DiDario</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Otvos</surname><given-names>L</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Hoshi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kant</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojanowski</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><article-title>Plaque-associated neuronal proteins: a recurrent motif in neuritic amyloid deposits throughout diverse cortical areas of the Alzheimer's disease brain</article-title><source>Exp Neurol</source><year>1994</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/exnr.1994.1209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7867760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kawarabayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Younkin</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Saido</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashe</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Younkin</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><article-title>Age-dependent changes in brain, CSF, and plasma amyloid (beta) protein in the Tg2576 transgenic mouse model of Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2001</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>372</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11160418</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Levites</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwizinski</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Troendle</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Verbeeck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Smithson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonoda</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rangachari</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Younkin</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Graff-Radford</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberry</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Golde</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><article-title>BRI2 (ITM2b) inhibits Abeta deposition in vivo</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2008</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>6030</fpage><lpage>6036</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0891-08.2008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18524908</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Butterfield</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Methionine residue 35 is critical for the oxidative stress and neurotoxic properties of Alzheimer's amyloid beta-peptide 1-42</article-title><source>Peptides</source><year>2002</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1299</fpage><lpage>1309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0196-9781(02)00066-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12128086</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchant</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zagorski</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><article-title>Methionine 35 oxidation reduces fibril assembly of the amyloid abeta-(1-42) peptide of Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>40173</fpage><lpage>40176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.C200338200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12198111</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bitan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarus</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Vollers</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lashuel</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Condron</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Straub</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Teplow</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><article-title>A molecular switch in amyloid assembly: Met35 and amyloid beta-protein oligomerization</article-title><source>J Am Chem Soc</source><year>2003</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>15359</fpage><lpage>15365</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja0349296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14664580</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cynis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Saido</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Demuth</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name><article-title>Amyloidogenic processing of amyloid precursor protein: evidence of a pivotal role of glutaminyl cyclase in generation of pyroglutamate-modified amyloid-beta</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2008</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>7405</fpage><lpage>7413</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi800250p</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18570439</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tekirian</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Glabe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Geddes</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><article-title>Toxicity of pyroglutaminated amyloid beta-peptides 3(pE)-40 and -42 is similar to that of A beta1-40 and -42</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>1999</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>1584</fpage><lpage>1589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10501204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harigaya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Saido</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckman</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Prada</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Younkin</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><article-title>Amyloid beta protein starting pyroglutamate at position 3 is a major component of the amyloid deposits in the Alzheimer's disease brain</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2000</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>422</fpage><lpage>427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.2000.3490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11027491</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schieb</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kratzin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jahn</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Mobius</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Staufenbiel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiltfang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Klafki</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><article-title>Beta-amyloid peptide variants in brains and cerebrospinal fluid from amyloid precursor protein (APP) transgenic mice: comparison with human Alzheimer amyloid</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2011</year><volume>286</volume><fpage>33747</fpage><lpage>33758</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M111.246561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21795681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jawhar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirths</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><article-title>Pyroglutamate amyloid-beta (Abeta): a hatchet man in Alzheimer disease</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2011</year><volume>286</volume><fpage>38825</fpage><lpage>38832</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.R111.288308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21965666</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jawhar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirths</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Graubner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Demuth</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><article-title>Overexpression of glutaminyl cyclase, the enzyme responsible for pyroglutamate A{beta} formation, induces behavioral deficits, and glutaminyl cyclase knock-out rescues the behavioral phenotype in 5XFAD mice</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2011</year><volume>286</volume><fpage>4454</fpage><lpage>4460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M110.185819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21148560</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Alexandru</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jagla</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Graubner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauscher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohlmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sedlmeier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Raber</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cynis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ronicke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Reymann</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrasch-Parwez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartlage-Rubsamen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Waniek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Osmand</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Demuth</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name><name><surname>von Horsten</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Selective hippocampal neurodegeneration in transgenic mice expressing small amounts of truncated Abeta is induced by pyroglutamate-Abeta formation</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2011</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>12790</fpage><lpage>12801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1794-11.2011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21900558</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wittnam</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Portelius</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zetterberg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustavsson</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Demuth</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name><name><surname>Blennow</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirths</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><article-title>Pyroglutamate A(beta) aggravates behavioral deficits in 5XFAD mice</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2012</year><volume>287</volume><fpage>8154</fpage><lpage>8162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M111.308601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22267726</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Klyubin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Fadeeva</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Cullen</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Anwyl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Selkoe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><article-title>Naturally secreted oligomers of amyloid beta protein potently inhibit hippocampal long-term potentiation in vivo</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>416</volume><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/416535a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11932745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Selkoe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><article-title>Effects of secreted oligomers of amyloid beta-protein on hippocampal synaptic plasticity: a potent role for trimers</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>572</volume><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>492</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2005.103754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16469784</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lesne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotilinek</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kayed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Glabe</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashe</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><article-title>A specific amyloid-beta protein assembly in the brain impairs memory</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2006</year><volume>440</volume><fpage>352</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature04533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16541076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanzi</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Borchelt</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sisodia</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><article-title>Alzheimer's disease: genetic studies and transgenic models</article-title><source>Annu Rev Genet</source><year>1998</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.genet.32.1.461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9928488</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ashe</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zahs</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><article-title>Probing the biology of Alzheimer's disease in mice</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2010</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>631</fpage><lpage>645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2010.04.031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20547123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Arvanitakis</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><article-title>Neuropathology of older persons without cognitive impairment from two community-based studies</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>2006</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>1837</fpage><lpage>1844</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/01.wnl.0000219668.47116.e6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16801647</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Naslund</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Haroutunian</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohs</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Greengard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Buxbaum</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><article-title>Correlation between elevated levels of amyloid beta-peptide in the brain and cognitive decline</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2000</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>1571</fpage><lpage>1577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.283.12.1571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10735393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>