<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Alzheimers Res Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Alzheimers Res Ther</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Alzheimer's Research &#x00026; Therapy</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1758-9193</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23497709</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3707057</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">alzrt168</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/alzrt168</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Modeling the heterogeneity in risk of progression to Alzheimer's disease across
cognitive profiles in mild cognitive impairment</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Tatsuoka</surname><given-names>Curtis</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>cmt66@case.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>Huiyun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>ht2157@columbia.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Jaeger</surname><given-names>Judith</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I6">6</xref><email>judith.jaeger@astrazeneca.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name><surname>Varadi</surname><given-names>Ferenc</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I7">7</xref><email>fvaradi123@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Mark A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I8">8</xref><email>mark.smith@case.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>Tomoko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>txy128@case.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A7"><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>Kathleen A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>kathleen.smyth@case.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A8"><name><surname>Lerner</surname><given-names>Alan J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>ajl3@case.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A9"><collab>The Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging Initiative</collab><email>null@null.com</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Neurology, Case Western Reserve University, 11100 Euclid Avenue,
Cleveland, OH 44106 USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Neurological Institute, University Hospitals Case Medical Center, 3619 Park East
Drive, Beachwood, OH 44122 USA</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, Case Western Reserve University,
10900 Euclid Avenue, Cleveland, OH 44106 USA</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Department of Human Development, Teachers College, Columbia University, 525 West
120th Street, New York, NY 10027 USA</aff><aff id="I5"><label>5</label>AstraZeneca Pharmaceuticals, Clinical Development, Neuroscience, 1800 Concord
Pike, Wilmington, DE 19807 USA</aff><aff id="I6"><label>6</label>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, Albert Einstein College of
Medicine, 1300 Morris Park Avenue, Bronx, NY 10461 USA</aff><aff id="I7"><label>7</label>Tanar Software, Hunting Valley, OH 44022 USA</aff><aff id="I8"><label>8</label>Department of Pathology, Case Western Reserve University, 2103 Cornell Road,
Cleveland, OH 44106 USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>3</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2013 Tatsuoka et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Tatsuoka et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons
Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which
permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://alzres.com/content/5/2/14"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Heterogeneity in risk of conversion to Alzheimer's disease (AD) among individuals
with mild cognitive impairment (MCI) is well known. Novel statistical methods that
are based on partially ordered set (poset) models can be used to create models
that provide detailed and accurate information about performance with specific
cognitive functions. This approach allows for the study of direct links between
specific cognitive functions and risk of conversion to AD from MCI. It also allows
for further delineation of multi-domain amnestic MCI, in relation to specific
non-amnestic cognitive deficits, and the modeling of a range of episodic memory
functioning levels.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>From the Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging Initiative (ADNI) study, conversion at
24 months of 268 MCI subjects was analyzed. It was found that 101 of those
subjects (37.7%) converted to AD within that time frame. Poset models were then
used to classify cognitive performance for MCI subjects. Respective observed
conversion rates to AD were calculated for various cognitive subgroups, and by
APOE e4 allele status. These rates were then compared across subgroups.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The observed conversion rate for MCI subjects with a relatively lower functioning
with a high level of episodic memory at baseline was 61.2%. In MCI subjects who
additionally also had relatively lower perceptual motor speed functioning and at
least one APOE e4 allele, the conversion rate was 84.2%. In contrast, the observed
conversion rate was 9.8% for MCI subjects with a relatively higher episodic memory
functioning level and no APOE e4 allele. Relatively lower functioning with
cognitive flexibility and perceptual motor speed by itself also appears to be
associated with higher conversion rates.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Among MCI subjects, specific baseline cognitive profiles that were derived through
poset modeling methods, are clearly associated with differential rates of
conversion to AD. More precise delineation of MCI by such cognitive functioning
profiles, including notions such as multidomain amnestic MCI, can help in gaining
further insight into how heterogeneity arises in outcomes. Poset-based modeling
methods may be useful for providing more precise classification of cognitive
subgroups among MCI for imaging and genetics studies, and for developing more
efficient and focused cognitive test batteries.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>There is increasing interest in the recognition and treatment of prodromal stages of
Alzheimer's disease (AD), especially mild cognitive impairment (MCI). MCI is viewed as a
state between normal cognitive functioning and dementia. Those with MCI are
characterized as exhibiting mild problems with memory and/or other cognitive functions,
while still being able to perform daily life activities normally or nearly so
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Despite having a higher overall risk
of developing AD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>], conversion outcomes among
those with MCI are quite heterogeneous. Only about 15% of these individuals convert to
AD per year; many never convert, and some revert to normal cognition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. This heterogeneity makes it difficult to design
efficient trials of agents designed to delay or prevent progression from MCI to AD or to
interpret the outcomes of these trials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>], or to
evaluate potential AD biomarkers. Hence, there is a clear need to better delineate
cognitive phenotypes in MCI.</p><p>Although MCI subgroups that reflect deficit heterogeneity, such as amnestic single
domain MCI, amnestic multidomain MCI, and non-amnestic multidomain MCI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] have been developed, they lack specificity in the
particular cognitive functions that are impaired in each subgroup. This type of
specification is challenging because neuropsychological (NP) response data are complex.
It can be difficult to isolate a deficit in a particular cognitive function, since
performing well on most NP measures requires tapping into several cognitive functions,
and it is often not possible to design tests that tap one cognitive domain to the
exclusion of all others. For example, it is possible to perform poorly on a verbal
list-learning task as a result of impaired attention or word fluency, and in the absence
of an amnestic disturbance. Hence, if an individual performs poorly on a given measure,
it may be difficult to pinpoint exactly which function is impaired.</p><p>Subscales are commonly used in an attempt to improve specificity in analysis of NP
assessment data. For instance, subscales can be derived from factor analysis through the
use of factor scores. However, scale-based approaches are generally limited by the
assumption of a direct correspondence between a subscale score and an associated
function. Poor performance on a subscale is interpreted as indicating a deficit in the
function the subscale is purported to measure, even if the poor performance is due to
deficits in functions not associated with the subscale. This makes it difficult to link
NP test performance to specific functional deficits, and hence to identify cognitive
phenotypes that can be linked to outcomes such as conversion from MCI to AD.</p><p>Use of total scores on multi-item measures, such as the Alzheimer's disease assessment
scale-cognitive (ADAS-Cog) measure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] or the
mini-mental status exam (MMSE) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>], as a basis
for cognitive phenotyping is also problematic. Total scores represent a (weighted) sum
of response scores from items assessing several cognitive domains. However, the same
total score can be derived from a range of different response patterns, without regard
to the cognitive functions being assessed by each item. In this sense, items are viewed
as interchangeable, even though the cognitive targets of assessment for the items can
vary considerably. Because a wide range of response patterns and cognitive
interpretations can give rise to the same score, resulting phenotypes lack
specificity.</p><sec><title>The partially ordered set (poset) modeling approach to interpreting NP data</title><p>Poset models serve as a basis for novel methods tailored for classifying the
performance (that is, functioning) levels of subjects with respect to specific
cognitive functions. Classification is conducted based on observed responses to NP
measures. Each measure is associated with specific cognitive functions that are
involved in performing well on that measure, so that the ties between observed
responses and functioning levels are clear. This approach is feasible because posets
have essential statistical convergence properties such as assuring that a subject's
state is identified accurately with sufficient measurement, even in the presence of
measures that are associated with multiple functions. Theoretically derived
validation tools are available as well. Statistical theory and data-analytic
frameworks for the poset approach have been established in Tatsuoka and Ferguson
(2003) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] and Tatsuoka (2002) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>].</p><p>In this paper, our goal is to demonstrate that posets can improve our understanding
of MCI heterogeneity. The modeling results in the development of states associated
with profiles of cognitive functioning that summarize performance levels for each of
the cognitive functions being tested by a given NP battery. Hence, a state can be
viewed as similar to a diagnostic classification in which the diagnosis represents a
particular pattern of cognitive strengths and weaknesses. States are ordered by
comparing the associated performance levels for each of the functions included in the
analysis. One state is considered greater than a second state if its associated
performance level on at least one function is strictly higher than the performance
level for the second state, and its performance levels for all other functions are at
least as high. However, posets are flexible in that it is not necessary that one
state be greater than another, in other words, the states can be partially ordered.
This arises when one state in comparison to another state has a higher performance
level with respect to one function, while having a lower performance level with
respect to another function. This enables models to reflect a complex range of
responses from an NP battery.</p><p>A probability distribution on the states is used to represent belief about which
state best describes the cognitive capabilities of a subject. Bayes' rule is used to
obtain updated posterior probabilities of state membership once responses to measures
are observed. This allows for a systematic manner in which the information obtained
from observing multiple measures can be combined for statistical classification. Two
response distributions are estimated per NP measure, one representing the response
tendencies of subjects who perform at a relatively high level on all functions
associated with the particular measure and another for those subjects who do not.
These distributions are used to weigh the relative likelihood of an observed response
indicating that a subject has the associated higher level functioning. The approach
of estimating two response distributions per NP measure is parsimonious in that there
is no need to estimate response distribution parameters that are specific to each
profile; rather, response distribution parameters are shared either by profiles that
have the associated functioning levels, or those that do not. Ideally, one state in
the model will have a probability close to 1 for each individual, while other states
will have probabilities near 0, indicating that a subject's cognitive profile is
known with near certainty. As long as models are correctly specified, this near
certainty will indeed be obtained given a sufficient amount of testing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Once classification is completed, subjects who
share a cognitive profile can be aggregated, and observed rates of conversion to AD
between the resulting subgroups can be compared.</p><p>In our study, we used NP data collected by the Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging
Initiative (ADNI) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] to evaluate the
usefulness of poset models to identify specific cognitive phenotypes associated with
conversion from MCI to AD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. We
hypothesized that poset modeling would generate interpretable and sufficiently
detailed cognitive phenotypes with clearly differentiated rates of conversion from
MCI to AD. Given its established importance in progression risk for AD,
Apolipoprotein E (APOE) e4 status was also taken into account [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Study sample</title><p>MCI subjects enrolled in the ADNI (<italic>n </italic>= 389) were included in the
classification analysis if their scores on the selected NP battery were available at
both baseline and at 24 months. The sample was 64.5% male and 93.1% Caucasian. About
3.8% were African American, 2.8% were Asian, and 0.3% were American Indian or Alaskan
Native. Mean age was 74.8 years (SD = 7.5) and mean length of education was 15.7
years (SD = 3.0).</p></sec><sec><title>Modeling and classification approach</title><p>We used neuropsychologist expert opinion (JJ and HYT) to map the relationship between
selected ADNI NP measures (ADAS delayed recall and word recognition subscales and
number cancellation; auditory verbal learning test (AVLT) Trial 6 and List B; Boston
naming test; category fluency; trail making Test A and Test B, and Wechsler adult
intelligence scale-revised (WAIS-R) digit symbol substitution) and the cognitive
functions required to perform them (episodic memory at four different levels, word
fluency, cognitive flexibility, perceptual motor speed, and attention). See Table
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> for the listing of these specifications. Measures were
selected based on the types of functions they tested and retained based on
statistical criteria such as discriminatory properties and correspondence with model
fit. Given the reliance on expert opinion, data-analytic validation is important.
Statistical details on how this validation was performed are provided in Additional
file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref> (Appendix).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Cognitive functions and how they are tapped into by selected ADNI
neuropsychology measures, as specified according to expert opinion</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center">ADNI measure </th><th align="center" colspan="7">Cognitive function</th></tr><tr><th/><th colspan="7"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th/><th align="center">Episodic memory level 1</th><th align="center">Episodic memory level 2</th><th align="center">Episodic memory level 3</th><th align="center">Word fluency</th><th align="center">Selective attention</th><th align="center">Cognitive flexibility</th><th align="center">Perceptualmotor speed</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">ADAS-delayed recall subscale</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">ADAS word recognition subscale</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">AVLT-Trial 6</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">AVLT-List B</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">Boston naming test</td><td/><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">Category fluency<sup>*</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">ADAS-number cancellation</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">Trail making test A</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td><td/><td align="center">X</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Trail making test B</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td></tr><tr><td align="center">WAIS-R digit symbol substitution</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td><td/><td align="center">X</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>ADAS, Alzheimer's Disease Cooperative Study; ADNI, Alzheimer's Disease
Neuroimaging Initiative; AVLT, adult verbal learning test; WAIS-R, Wechsler
adult intelligence scale-revised; <sup>*</sup>average of vegetable and animal
categories.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To acknowledge the key role of episodic memory impairment as an early symptom in AD
and to better represent the varying levels of episodic memory required across the
measures, we identified four levels of episodic memory proficiency (levels 0 through
3). These levels are ordered in terms of episodic memory demand, with level the
highest, and level 0 the lowest. Level 3 corresponds to relatively longer-term
delayed recall with distractors, while level 2 and level 1, respectively, relate to
shorter and shorter recall durations involved in AVLT List B and immediate recall. A
subject at level 0 cannot perform well at any of the other levels. A brief summary of
the practical interpretation of the episodic memory levels to be used here is given
in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Description of episodic memory functioning levels used in the model</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Level</th><th align="center">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Level 3</td><td align="left">Relatively longer-term delayed recall with distractors</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Level 2</td><td align="left">Relatively shorter recall durations, such as involved in AVLT List B</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Level 1</td><td align="left">Immediate recall, word recognition</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Level 0</td><td align="left">Cannot perform well at any of the above levels</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>AVLT, adult verbal learning test</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Through the assumed hierarchical ordering between levels of episodic memory, note
that the delayed recall measures that involve level 3 also can provide information on
functioning with levels 1 and 2. High functioning at level 3 implies high functioning
at levels 1 and 2 as well. Also, poor performance on word recognition, which is
associated with level 1, not only provides evidence that level 1 is at a low level,
but that functioning at levels 2 and 3 should be low as well. Hence, even though
associations of measures involving episodic memory can be at different levels, they
still can inform other levels of episodic memory functioning, affording some degree
of replication.</p></sec><sec><title>Poset model generation</title><p>A poset model was generated based on the functions associated with each of the ADNI
NP measures. In the cognitive profiles associated to states in the model, performance
levels for a function were denoted either as relatively high, or relatively low, in
relation to the MCI and early AD sample. See Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref> for a
complete list of profiles that can be distinguished by the given set of NP measures
that were analyzed.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Poset states and their corresponding profiles of cognitive functioning relative
to mild cognititve impairment and Alzheimer's disease</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center">Poset state</th><th align="center" colspan="7">Cognitive function</th></tr><tr><th/><th colspan="7"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th/><th align="center">Selective attention</th><th align="center">Episodic memory level 1</th><th align="center">Episodic memory level 2</th><th align="center">Episodic memory level 3</th><th align="center">Word fluency</th><th align="center">Cognitive flexibility</th><th align="center">Perceptual motor speed</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td></tr><tr><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td align="center">X</td></tr><tr><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td></tr><tr><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td></tr><tr><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td align="center">*</td><td align="center">X</td></tr><tr><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td></tr><tr><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td align="center">X</td><td/><td align="center">X</td></tr><tr><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td></tr><tr><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td><td/><td align="center">X</td></tr><tr><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/><td align="center"><sup>*</sup></td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">15</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td></tr><tr><td align="center">16</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">17</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td><td/><td align="center">X</td></tr><tr><td align="center">18</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">19</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td></tr><tr><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td></tr><tr><td align="center">21</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/><td/><td align="center"><sup>*</sup></td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">22</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td></tr><tr><td align="center">23</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">24</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td><td/><td align="center">X</td></tr><tr><td align="center">25</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">26</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td><td align="center">X</td></tr><tr><td align="center">27</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td align="center">X</td></tr><tr><td align="center">28</td><td align="center">X</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td align="center"><sup>*</sup></td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">29</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>X indicates relatively high functioning; <sup>*</sup>undetermined..</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The resultant poset model comprised 29 states. These states (and associated cognitive
profiles) represent the profiles that can be distinguished from the NP battery, and
were identified algorithmically from the expert-derived specifications in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref> shows how the cognitive functions we examined are distributed
across states to create distinct cognitive profiles. The corresponding partial
ordering of these profiles is graphically depicted in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>
as a Hasse diagram. Note that state 1 is the highest state in the poset, as it has
the highest level of functioning for all five cognitive functions. State 29 is the
lowest state, since all its functioning for all five functions is at the lowest
level. For the in-between states, there exists at least one function for which
performance is not at a relatively high level. In the diagram, connected lines
between states indicate direct ordering, with the higher of the states being greater
than the lower one.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Partially ordered set (poset) model for cognitive functioning of mild
cognifitive impairment and early Alzheimer's disease subjects</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt168-1"/></fig><p>In our analysis, a uniform prior probability value of 1/29 was assigned to each state
for each subject to indicate prior belief about which profile would fit a given
subject. We then estimated two response distributions for each NP measure as
described above. These distributions were then used to weigh the relative likelihood
that an observed response indicated that a subject had the associated higher level
functioning.</p></sec><sec><title>Response distributions</title><p>Responses from both the MCI subjects and also early AD subjects (an additional 174
such subjects) were included in the estimation, to allow for a range of values. Given
the apparent non-normality of response data, nonparametric approaches to response
distribution estimation were adopted [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] (see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Grouping of profiles and classified subjects</title><p>The ordered relationships between states arise when identifying subgroups with shared
functioning levels for a function. For instance, the subgroup of states that have
high performance level for episodic memory level 2 are all the states greater than or
equal to state 14. Precisely, this would be state 1 through 12, and state 14. The
complement of this subgroup (all states not greater than or equal to state 14) would
thus comprise the states with lower performance level. Once subgroups such as this
have been identified and classification conducted, the probability that a subject has
a particular performance level for a function can be computed by summing the
posterior probabilities of membership of each of the states in the subgroup. These
probabilities are used as a basis for cutoff values in function-related groupings,
which are then compared statistically in terms of proportion of AD conversions from
MCI. All reported <italic>P</italic>-values are two-sided.</p><p>We treated cognitive flexibility slightly differently from other NP functions, due to
confounding of its functioning status in classification under certain profiles,
specifically for states 7, 14, 21, and 28. Confounded profiles arise due to
limitations of the NP battery to distinguish all possible profiles. Profiles with
confounding give conflicting information about certain functions, but probabilities
for a subject being at certain functioning levels can still be obtained by weighting
the information provided across a set of confounded profiles (see Additional file
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref> for more details).</p></sec><sec><title>Model validation</title><p>Briefly, model fit appears to be good. Response distribution estimates for all
measures correspond to the assumed order structure, in that those subjects expected
by the model to score well actually tended to do so, and those not expected to score
well tended not to do so. Moreover, classification was fairly decisive, especially
given the limited number of NP measures employed. Observed responses to the measures
were thus consistent with the model specifications. See Figures S1 through S6 and
Table S1 in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><p>We explored different cognitive groupings within MCI subjects, to assess conversion
rates to AD at two years post baseline. Not surprisingly, episodic memory is the
cognitive function that appears to be most significantly related to future conversion.
Still, the different performance levels of episodic memory in our model appear to have
varying degrees and ways of association with conversion outcomes. For instance, as seen
in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>, level 2 episodic memory performance levels influence
the rate of conversion among those with MCI. In subjects for whom level 2 episodic
memory functioning is low (in other words, below the cutoff probability value of less
than 0.275), 41 out of 67 (61.2%&#x000b1;11.7%, 95% CI) converted to AD within two years,
which is much higher than the overall MCI to AD conversion rate in this sample of 101
out of 268 (37.7%&#x000b1;5.8%, 95% CI). Those with relatively lower performance in level 2
of episodic memory significantly differ in conversion rates compared with those with
higher performance, regardless of whether or not the APOE e4 allele is present. The
<italic>P</italic>-value for Fisher's exact test is 0.000 for a two-sided test of no
association between conversion and having relatively low episodic memory level 2
functioning.</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Relationship between episodic memory level 2 functioning and conversion to
Alzheimer's disease (AD) over a two-year period</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center">Converted to AD</th><th align="center">Low episodic memory level 2 function</th><th align="center">Not low episodic memory level 2 function</th><th align="center">Total</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><bold>Yes</bold></td><td align="center">61.2% (41)</td><td align="center">29.9% (60)</td><td align="center">37.7% (101)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>No</bold></td><td align="center">38.8% (26)</td><td align="center">70.1% (141)</td><td align="center">62.3% (167)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>Total</bold></td><td align="center">100% (67)</td><td align="center">100% (201)</td><td align="center">100% (268)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Results are presented as the percent (number) of patients. Fisher's exact test
two-sided <italic>P</italic>-value = 0.000 for a test of no association; positive
predictive value = 0.612; negative predictive value = 0.701.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Other functions where relatively lower functioning at baseline may indicate higher risk
for conversion from MCI to AD are perceptual motor speed and cognitive flexibility. For
perceptual motor speed, using a cutoff probability value of 0.40 to delineate a lower
functioning subgroup, and considering subjects with at least one APOE4 allele, 23 of 35
(65.7%&#x000b1;15.7%, 95% CI) of MCI subjects with relatively low functioning convert to AD
within 24 months. On the other hand, only 14 of 35 MCI subjects with relatively low
perceptual motor speed and without an APOE4 allele convert (40%&#x000b1;16.2%, 95% CI).
Further, for cognitive flexibility, using a cutoff probability value of 0.30 to
delineate a lower functioning subgroup, 28 of 48 (58.3%&#x000b1;13.9%, 95% CI) of MCI
subjects with relative low baseline functioning convert to AD within 24 months. In this
case, the <italic>P</italic>-value for Fisher's exact test of no association is 0.007.</p><p>Interestingly, we conversely found much lower rates of conversion among certain
cognitive profiles. In particular, only four out of forty-one (9.8%&#x000b1;9.1%, 95% CI)
MCI subjects with no APOE e4 alleles and relatively high level-3 episodic memory
functioning (cutoff probability value greater than 0.80) convert in two years. This rate
appears to be lower than for subjects with no APOE e4 allele but without high level-3
episodic memory functioning (<italic>P</italic>-value = 0.001, Fisher's exact test of no
association).</p><sec><title>Amnestic multidomain MCI identified with poset models</title><p>An advantage of the poset approach is the ability to provide classification to
profiles that address a range of functions. Subgroups, such as amnestic multidomain
MCI, can be characterized more precisely by identifying specific functions that are
relatively impaired along with episodic memory.</p><p>In our sample, subjects with relatively low functioning on episodic memory level 2
(probability of being at high level at level 2 being 0.275 or less) and perception
speed (probability cutoff value of 0.40 or less) were identified. As shown in Table
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>, among subjects with at least one APOE e4 allele and with
relatively low levels of both episodic memory and perception speed, 16 out of 19
converted (84.2%&#x000b1;16.4%, 95% CI). Considering only subjects with lower level-2
episodic memory functioning, those who additionally have lower functioning in
perceptual motor speed appear even more likely to convert (<italic>P</italic>-value = 0.013,
Fisher's exact test of no association). In contrast, additionally having lower
functioning with cognitive flexibility did not appear to significantly increase risk
for conversion. Among subjects with lower episodic memory level 2 functioning,
observed percentages of conversion with and without lower cognitive flexibility were
66.7% versus 57.5% (18 out of 27 versus 23 out of 40).</p><table-wrap id="T5" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Relationship between episodic memory level 2 and perceptual motor speed
functioning and conversion to AD over a two-year period by APOE4 allele
status</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center">Converted to AD</th><th align="center" colspan="3">Low episodic memory function and no APOE4 allele<sup>a</sup></th><th align="center" colspan="3">Low episodic memory function and at least one APOE4
allele<sup>b</sup></th></tr><tr><th/><th colspan="3"><hr/></th><th colspan="3"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th/><th align="center">Low perceptual motor speed function</th><th align="center">Not low perceptual motor speed function</th><th align="center">Total</th><th align="center">Low perceptual motor speed function</th><th align="center">Not low perceptual motor speed Function</th><th align="center">Total</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><bold>Yes</bold></td><td align="center">63.6% (7)</td><td align="center">54.5% (6)</td><td align="center">59.1% (13)</td><td align="center">84.2% (16)</td><td align="center">37.8% 17)</td><td align="center">61.2% (18)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>No</bold></td><td align="center">36.4% (4)</td><td align="center">45.5% (5)</td><td align="center">40.9% (9)</td><td align="center">15.8% (3)</td><td align="center">62.2% (28)</td><td align="center">38.8% (10)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>Total</bold></td><td align="center">100% (11)</td><td align="center">100% (11)</td><td align="center">100% (22)</td><td align="center">100% (19)</td><td align="center">100% (13)</td><td align="center">100% (28)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Results are presented as the percent (number) of patients.<sup>a</sup>Fisher's
exact test two-sided <italic>P</italic>-value = 1.00 for a test of no association.
<sup>b</sup>Fisher's exact test two-sided <italic>P</italic>-value = 0.013 for a
test of no association. AD, Alzheimer's disease; APOE, Apolipoprotein.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Cognitive change before conversion</title><p>Over the range of cognitive functions, histograms were generated for the respective
probabilities of converters having relatively high functioning over the 24 months
preceding conversion. Analogous histograms were generated for non-converters over a
time period of the same duration starting from baseline. See Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>. Note that for non-converters, only those subjects who did not convert
over the full 36-month period of the study were included in the plots. By comparing
corresponding plots between converters and non-converters, it becomes clearer how the
above findings of heterogeneity in conversion outcomes by cognitive profile
arose.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figures 2</label><caption><p><bold>Probabilities of functioning over time among mild cognitive impairment (MCI)
converters to Alzheimer's disease (AD) versus MCI non-converters</bold>.
(<bold>a</bold>) Probability of relatively high functioning with episodic memory
level 1 from 24 to 0 months before conversion to AD among MCI subjects.
Respectively, <italic>n </italic>= 75, 75, 68, 51, and 36 for 0, 6, 12, 18 and 24
months before conversion. (<bold>b</bold>) Probability of relatively high functioning
with episodic memory level 1 from baseline (0 months) to 24 months among MCI
subjects who did not convert within 36 months; <italic>n </italic>= 90.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt168-2"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Probabilities of functioning over time among mild cognitive impairment (MCI)
converters to Alzheimer's disease (AD) versus MCI non-converters</bold>.
(<bold>a</bold>) Probability of relatively high functioning with episodic memory
level 2 from 0 to 24 months before conversion to AD among MCI subjects.
(<bold>b</bold>) Probability of relatively high functioning with episodic memory
level 2 from baseline to 24 months among MCI subjects who did not convert
within 36 months.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt168-3"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Probabilities of functioning over time among mild cognitive impairment (MCI)
converters to Alzheimer's disease (AD) versus MCI non-converters</bold>.
(<bold>a</bold>) Probability of relatively high functioning with episodic memory
level 3 from 24 to 0 months before conversion to AD among MCI subjects.
(<bold>b</bold>) Probability of relatively high functioning with episodic memory
level 3 from baseline to 24 months among MCI subjects who did not convert
within 36 months.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt168-4"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Probabilities of functioning over time among mild cognitive impairment (MCI)
converters to Alzheimer's disease (AD) versus MCI non-converters</bold>.
(<bold>a</bold>) Probability of relatively high functioning with word fluency from
24 to 0 months before conversion to AD among MCI subjects. (<bold>b</bold>)
Probability of relatively high functioning with word fluency from baseline to
24 months among MCI subjects who did not convert within 36 months.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt168-5"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Probabilities of functioning over time among mild cognitive impairment (MCI)
converters to Alzheimer's disease (AD) versus MCI non-converters</bold>.
<bold>(a</bold>) Probability of relatively high functioning with
attention/sustained vigilance from 24 to 0 months before conversion to AD among
MCI subjects. (<bold>b</bold>) Probability of relatively high functioning with
attention/sustained vigilance from baseline to 24 months among MCI subjects who
did not convert within 36 months.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt168-6"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>Probabilities of functioning over time among mild cognitive impairment (MCI)
converters to Alzheimer's disease (AD) versus MCI non-converters</bold>.
(<bold>a</bold>) Probability of relatively high functioning with cognitive
flexibility from 24 to 0 months before conversion to AD among MCI subjects.
(<bold>b</bold>) Probability of relatively high functioning with cognitive
flexibility from baseline to 24 months among MCI subjects who did not convert
within 36 months.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt168-7"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><bold>Probabilities of functioning over time among mild cognitive impairment (MCI)
converters to Alzheimer's disease (AD) versus MCI non-converters</bold>.
(<bold>a</bold>) Probability of relatively high functioning with perceptual motor
speed from 24 to 0 months before conversion to AD among MCI subjects.
(<bold>b</bold>) Probability of relatively high functioning with perceptual motor
speed from baseline to 24 months among MCI subjects who did not convert within
36 months.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt168-8"/></fig><p>For Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, which correspond to the episodic memory levels, note that relative to
level 2, level 1 does not see the same amount of decline over 24 months for
converters, as reflected by a shift to lower probability values. Hence, the
discrepancy between the histograms in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2a</xref> versus 2b over
time between converters and non-converters is not very strong. On the other hand, in
Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3a</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3b</xref>, it is clear that for
converters, there is quite a bit of decline in level 2 values during this time
period, while non-converters appear stable. This makes level 2 attractive for
discrimination and prediction over this duration. In Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4a</xref>
and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4b</xref>, note that level 3 functioning is low among almost all
converters preceding conversion. However, lower functioning for this more difficult
level also is common for non-converters, lessening the discriminatory properties of
level 3. Still, there is a sizeable proportion of non-converters retaining high
probability values for level 3, which allows for cognitively-based identification of
a very low-risk group.</p><p>In Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5a</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5b</xref>, it appears that
there may be decline in word fluency values for a relatively small subset of subjects
as they near conversion, but many converters also appear to retain high functioning.
For non-converters, some subjects have lower functioning as well. Hence, word fluency
does not appear useful for predicting conversion within a two-year period. In Figures
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6a</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6b</xref>, note that there may be some
slight decline in attention/sustained vigilance for converters, but almost all
subjects still retain high probability values for being at a high level of attention
functioning.</p><p>In Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7a</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7b</xref>, there is definitely
a fair amount of decline in values for cognitive flexibility among converters,
although it is also not as pronounced as for episodic memory level 2. Also, some
converters retain high functioning. Most non-converters retain high functioning over
the duration. Hence, cognitive flexibility can be useful for discriminating future
conversion outcomes, but does not appear as informative as episodic memory level 2.
Finally, in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8a</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8b</xref>, for
perceptual motor speed, note that there appears to be a subset of converters for whom
perceptual motor speed becomes more impaired. While there are non-converters who also
have low probability values, this number is outweighed by the converters over the
duration. Moreover, as Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref> indicates, these converters are
likely to also be relatively more impaired with episodic memory level 2 than the
non-converters. This allows us to identify this particular combination of lower level
functioning as being specifically associated with high risk for conversion.</p></sec><sec><title>Multivariate prediction using logistic regression models</title><p>A multivariate model was fit that recognized the above findings, and included other
variables such as gender, age, and educational level. The presence of an APOE4 allele
was viewed as a binary variable, as well as whether or not a subject had attended
college. Also, probability values for performing at a relatively high level for
episodic memory level 2, cognitive flexibility, and perceptual motor speed were
viewed as continuous explanatory variables. After an initial fit of a full model,
gender, age, and educational level were clearly not significant predictors in the
model (respective <italic>P</italic>-values were 0.96, 0.65, and 0.81; Wald's test). Using
goodness-of-fit tests based on the test statistic of -2 times the difference in
log-likelihood values to compare nested models, it appears the best fit is when
episodic memory level 2, perceptual motor speed, and APOE4 status are included in the
model. Results are given in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>. Note that episodic memory
level 2, perceptual motor speed, and APOE4 status all are significant predictors
(<italic>P</italic>-value &#x0003c;0.05; Wald's test). When cognitive flexibility is included
with these variables, it is not significant (<italic>P</italic>-value = 0.26).</p><table-wrap id="T6" position="float"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Multivariate logistic regression model with outcome as conversion to
Alzheimer's disease (AD) from mild cognitive impairment (MCI) within 24 months
from baseline</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center">Explanatory variables</th><th align="center">B</th><th align="center">Wald test <italic>P</italic>-value</th><th align="center">Exp (B)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><bold>APOE4</bold></td><td align="center">0.623</td><td align="center">0.024</td><td align="center">0.536</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>Episodic memory level 2</bold></td><td align="center">-1.445</td><td align="center">0.001</td><td align="center">0.236</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>Perceptual motor speed</bold></td><td align="center">-0.926</td><td align="center">0.009</td><td align="center">0.396</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>Intercept</bold></td><td align="center">1.193</td><td align="center">0.000</td><td align="center">3.298</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Dependent variable value of 1 indicates that a subject has converted to AD from
MCI within 24 months of baseline. Binary variable Apolipoprotein (APOE)4 = 1
indicates that the subject has at least one APOE4 allele and higher risk for
conversion. Larger probability values of relatively high performance indicate
lower risk for conversion.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Using the model-based estimated probabilities of converting to AD as a predictor, and
for instance, using a cutoff value of 0.55 or higher, classification accuracy is
66.8%, with positive predictive value of 61.5% (32 out of 52). Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref> displays receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves for these
logistic regression probabilities, as well as for the probabilities for episodic
memory level 2, perceptual motor speed, and cognitive flexibility. Values for the
area under the curve (AUC) are 0.710, 0.678, 0.655, and 0.644, respectively. Using a
multivariate approach can thus apparently improve prediction. However, compared to
relying upon episodic memory level 2 alone without the need for APOE4 status
information, which would have practical appeal, the difference does not appear to be
striking.</p><fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p><bold>Area under the curve (AUC)</bold>. Multivariate logistic model probability
values for conversion = 0.710, episodic memory level 2 probability of high
functioning = 0.678, perceptual motor speed probability of high functioning =
0.655, cognitive flexibility probability of high functioning = 0.644.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt168-9"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Other prediction approaches</title><p>A comprehensive review of research efforts using ADNI data is given in Weiner <italic>et
al</italic>. (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. This includes a
description of work on prediction of MCI to AD conversion. Taking advantage of the
richness of the ADNI data, prediction models have been developed based on a range of
various imaging, cerebrospinal fluid, and genetic biomarkers, as well as cognition.
Our prediction results appear to be comparable to non-cognitively oriented methods
that rely on baseline data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Advantages of a cognitive testing approach include
non-invasiveness and cost, especially if focused and efficient NP batteries can be
designed, and computer-based adaptive testing adopted in the future.</p><p>Other cognitive testing-based approaches to prediction include Tabert <italic>et al</italic>.
(2006) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>] and Fleisher <italic>et al</italic>.
(2007) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Their prediction models depend
directly on NP measurement scores, which in general may be difficult to interpret in
terms of identifying which cognitive functions may be the source of poor scores. We
believe that the results presented here add to these works, such as through a more
specific consideration of multidomain MCI. Poset-based methods also provided insight
into the course of cognitive change in MCI, by indicating how specific functions are
affected over time. The findings depicted in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> allow for
insight into the heterogeneity in cognitive progressions that arise among MCI, and
thus help in identifying profiles of high risk.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Our results suggest the utility of the poset-based approach in uncovering heterogeneity
in risk for conversion from MCI to AD by generating subgroups tied to specific cognitive
functions. Duration of 24 months from baseline measurement was considered. Among the
cognitive functions evaluated, episodic memory was mostly strongly linked to conversion
from MCI to AD. This confirms similar findings in Tierney <italic>et al</italic>. (2005)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>], Tabert <italic>et al</italic>. (2006)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>], Blacker <italic>et al</italic>. (2007)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>], and Landau <italic>et al</italic>. (2010)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. We did find that cognitive
flexibility and perceptual motor speed also is associated with conversion, as certain
subjects are apparently affected in these domains during the 24 months preceding
conversion. Conversely, MCI subjects with relatively less episodic memory impairment
were observed to convert at a much lower rate. The importance of the APOE e4 allele in
affecting risk for conversion is also clear [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>].</p><p>More precisely, it appears that in our model certain levels of episodic memory
functioning are more discriminatory than others in terms of identifying MCI subjects at
especially high risk for conversion. In particular, level-2 episodic memory functioning,
more so than level-3, appears to best identify risk for conversion. It appears that
delayed recall with distractors may be too difficult a task to discriminate risk very
well. On the other hand, for those that can perform well at level 3 relative to others
with MCI, risk of conversion is much lower, as illustrated in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>.</p><p>Poset modeling also appears to be helpful in further clarifying the notion of
multidomain MCI. Our analyses suggest that perceptual motor speed functioning may have a
stronger link to subsequent risk of AD progression than other cognitive functions when
considered in conjunction with relatively reduced function of level-2 episodic memory.
On the other hand, additional impairment with cognitive flexibility does not appear to
increase risk beyond that due to episodic memory impairment. These results suggest that
having relatively lower functioning across multiple functions can indeed increase risk
for AD, but, that it may matter which of the functions are impaired. Because
corresponding samples become smaller as specific combinations of deficits are analyzed,
however, these analyses must be viewed as preliminary.</p><p>A possible concern is that the ranges of performance levels for functions in the poset
model are limited, particularly when a functioning level is either high or low. However,
it should be kept in mind that there are also limited NP response data available, due to
the time-consuming and burdensome nature of NP measurement. Hence, there are statistical
limitations to the granularity of information on functioning that can be assessed
accurately. Our model was shown to be feasible, while still being able to provide
discriminating information relating to AD conversion. Another limitation is the scope of
inference that can be made from the ADNI sample, which was overwhelmingly Caucasian, and
imbalanced towards males. Certainly, these findings should be validated in other
datasets.</p><sec><title>Future directions</title><p>Since the poset model allows for precise and detailed cognitive profiles, this
approach can be used in conjunction with imaging and genetic studies. As an example,
a cluster analysis approach has recently been applied to characterize MCI subgroups
by cognitive characteristics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. While
white matter lesion burden was found to differ by these groupings, in general,
cognitive subtypes resulting from cluster analysis can at times be more difficult to
interpret than profiles generated with poset models. Also, note the persistent
heterogeneity of conversion outcomes among MCI subjects even within the cognitively
homogeneous subgroups generated here. These subgroups could be an interesting basis
for functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) studies of cognitive reserve, which
may improve understanding of how this heterogeneity arises [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Poset modeling may also be
useful in clinical trial design, as enriched sampling from subgroups of MCI subjects
that have high positive predictive value of conversion could reduce sample size
requirements.</p><p>Finally, poset models can serve as a basis for adaptive NP testing, with NP measures
being selected for administration dynamically, based on the responses that have
already been observed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. As demonstrated, an attractive feature of poset models is
that since they are comprised of discrete states, accurate statistical classification
can be conducted with relatively few measures. Adaptive tests can further reduce
subject burden and allow for more focused and efficient testing, which in turn would
enhance the appeal of cognitive testing for prediction.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>AD: Alzheimer's disease; ADAS-Cog: Alzheimer's disease assessment scale-cognitive; ADNI:
Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging Initiative; APOE: Apolipoprotein E; AUC: area under the
curve; AVLT: auditory verbal learning test; fMRI, functional magnetic resonance imaging;
MCI: mild cognitive impairment; MMSE: mini-mental status exam; NP: neuropsychological;
poset: partially ordered set; ROC; receiver operator characteristic; WAIS-R: Wechsler
adult intelligence scale-revised.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>Dr Tatsuoka was funded in part by AstraZeneca Pharmaceuticals to do this research, and
has written a related patent. Drs Tseng, Varadi, Smyth and Yamada have no conflicts of
interest to report. Dr Jaeger was Director, Global Medicines Development, Neuroscience,
AstraZeneca Pharmaceuticals during the funding of this research, and is now with
CogState, Inc. Dr Smith was a consultant for Anavex Life Sciences Corporation,
Medivation, Eisai, Glaxo Welcome Kline, and Neurotez; he owns stock options in Neurotez,
Aria, Panancea, and Curaxis Pharmaceuticals. Dr Lerner receives research support from
Forest Labs, Pfizer, Medivation, Baxter Labs, and Avid Pharmaceuticals.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>CT developed the statistical methods, conducted statistical analyses, and helped prepare
the manuscript; HYT conducted analyses; JJ helped frame and conduct the analyses; FV
programmed the software, helped in developing the statistical methods, and helped in the
analysis; MS helped in the analyses; TY conducted analyses; KS helped in the analyses
and prepared the manuscript; AL helped frame and conduct the analyses, and prepare the
manuscript. All authors have read and approved the manuscript for publication. Data used
in the preparation of this article were obtained from the ADNI database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. As such, the investigators within the ADNI
contributed to the design and implementation of ADNI and/or provided data but did not
participate in analysis or writing of this report. ADNI investigators include a complete
listing available at [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional file 1</title><p><bold>Appendix: Statistical framework for data analysis and model validation</bold>.
This file contains statistical details relating to the poset modeling,
including parameter estimates and classification summaries. It also describes
how model validation was conducted.</p></caption><media xlink:href="alzrt168-S1.PDF"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was funded in part by the grants from AstraZeneca Pharmaceuticals and The
G.R. Lincoln Family Foundation. Data collection and sharing for this project was
funded by the ADNI (National Institutes of Health Grant U01 AG024904). ADNI is funded
by the National Institute on Aging, the National Institute of Biomedical Imaging and
Bioengineering, and through generous contributions from the following: Abbott,
AstraZeneca AB, Bayer Schering Pharma AG, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Eisai Global Clinical
Development, Elan Corporation, Genentech, GE Healthcare, GlaxoSmithKline,
Innogenetics, Johnson and Johnson, Eli Lilly and Co., Medpace, Inc., Merck and Co.,
Inc., Novartis AG, Pfizer Inc, F. Hoffman-La Roche, Schering-Plough, Synarc, Inc., as
well as non-profit partners, the Alzheimer's Association and Alzheimer's Drug
Discovery Foundation, with participation from the US Food and Drug Administration.
Private sector contributions to ADNI are facilitated by the Foundation for the
National Institutes of Health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. The
grantee organization is the Northern California Institute for Research and Education,
and the study is coordinated by the Alzheimer's Disease Cooperative Study at the
University of California, San Diego. ADNI data are disseminated by the Laboratory for
Neuroimaging at the University of California, Los Angeles. This research was also
supported by NIH grants P30 AG010129, K01 AG030514, and the Dana Foundation.</p><p>Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging Initiative (ADNI): 'Data used in the preparation of
this article were obtained from the Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging Initiative
(ADNI) database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. The ADNI was launched
in 2003 by the National Institute on Aging (NIA), the National Institute of
Biomedical Imaging and Bioengineering (NIBIB), the Food and Drug Administration
(FDA), private pharmaceutical companies and non-profit organizations, as a $60
million, 5-year public private partnership. The primary goal of ADNI has been to test
whether serial magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), positron emission tomography (PET),
other biological markers, and the progression of mild cognitive impairment (MCI) and
early Alzheimer's disease (AD). Determination of sensitive and specific markers of
very early AD progression is intended to aid researchers and clinicians to develop
new treatments and monitor their effectiveness, as well as lessen the time and cost
of clinical trials. The Principal Investigator of this initiative is Michael W
Weiner, MD, VA Medical Center and University of California - San Francisco.</p><p>ADNI is the result of efforts of many co-investigators from a broad range of academic
institutions and private corporations, and subjects have been recruited from over 50
sites across the US and Canada. The initial goal of ADNI was to recruit 800 adults,
ages 55 to 90, to participate in the research - approximately 200 cognitively normal
older individuals to be followed for 3 years, 400 people with MCI to be followed for
3 years and 200 people with early AD to be followed for 2 years.' For up-to-date
information, see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>].</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Doody</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohs</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabins</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Winblad</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>Current concepts in mild cognitive impairment</article-title><source>Arch Neurol</source><year>2001</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1985</fpage><lpage>1992</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archneur.58.12.1985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11735772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Grundman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Doody</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Galasko</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Levey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeiffer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van Dyck</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Thal</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><collab>Alzheimer's Disease Cooperative Study Group</collab><article-title>Vitamin E and donepezil for the treatment of mild cognitive impairment</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>352</volume><fpage>2379</fpage><lpage>2388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa050151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15829527</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Andrieu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Coley</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Aisen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrillo</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>DeKosky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Durga</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fillit</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Frisoni</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Froelich</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x000f6;nsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Khachaturian</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Orgogozo</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ousset</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampaio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhey</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilcock</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Vellas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>Methodological issues in primary prevention trials for neurodegenerative
dementia</article-title><source>J Alzheimers Dis</source><year>2009</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19221415</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><article-title>Mild cognitive impairment as a diagnostic entity</article-title><source>J Intern Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>256</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2796.2004.01388.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15324362</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohs</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><article-title>A new rating scale for Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>Am J Psychiatry</source><year>1984</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>1356</fpage><lpage>1364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6496779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Folstein</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Folstein</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>McHugh</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><article-title>"Mini-mental state". A practical method for grading the cognitive state of
patients for the clinician</article-title><source>J Psychiatr Res</source><year>1975</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-3956(75)90026-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1202204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tatsuoka</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>Sequential classification on partially ordered sets</article-title><source>Journal of the Royal Statistical Society, Series B</source><year>2003</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1467-9868.00377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tatsuoka</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Data analytic methods for latent partially ordered classification models</article-title><source>Journal of the Royal Statistical Society, Series C (Applied Statistics)</source><year>2002</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>350</lpage><comment>See also Corrigendum 2005, 54:465-467</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1467-9876.00272</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aisen</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Donohue</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Raman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojanowski</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckett</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jack</surname><given-names>CR</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Jagust</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Toga</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Saykin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><collab>Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging Initiative</collab><article-title>Clinical core of the Alzheimer disease neuroimaging initiative: Progress and
plans</article-title><source>Alzheimers Dement</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jalz.2010.03.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20451872</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jaeger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatsuoka</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Berns</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Varadi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Czobor</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Uzelac</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Associating functional recovery with neurocognitive profiles identified using
partially ordered classification models</article-title><source>Schizophr Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.schres.2006.03.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16690254</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jaeger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatsuoka</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Berns</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Varadi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Distinguishing neurocognitive functions in schizophrenia using partially ordered
classification models</article-title><source>Schizophr Bull</source><year>2006</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>691</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16424379</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Landau</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Madison</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiman</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Aisen</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojanowski</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jack</surname><given-names>CR</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Jagust</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><collab>Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging Initiative</collab><article-title>Comparing predictors of conversion and decline in mild cognitive impairment</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>2010</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>230</fpage><lpage>238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0b013e3181e8e8b8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20592257</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bienias</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Berry-Kravis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><article-title>The apolipoprotein E epsilon4 allele and incident Alzheimer disease in persons
with mild cognitive impairment</article-title><source>Neurocase</source><year>2005</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13554790490903038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15804918</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Tatsuoka</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Sequential classification on partially ordered sets</article-title><source>PhD thesis</source><year>1996</year><publisher-name>Cornell University, Statistics Department</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ishwaran</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><article-title>Approximate Dirichlet process computing in finite normal mixtures: Smoothing and
prior information</article-title><source>J Comp Graph</source><year>2002</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>1154</fpage><lpage>1166</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Tatsuoka</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Varadi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaeger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Latent partially ordered classification models and normal mixtures</article-title><source>Journal of Educational and Behavioral Statistics</source><comment> in press </comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Geweke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Bernardo JM, Berger J, Dawid AP, Smith AFM</person-group><article-title>Evaluating the accuracy of sampling-based approaches to the calculation of
posterior moments</article-title><source>Bayesian Statistics 4</source><year>1992</year><publisher-name>Oxford, UK: Oxford University Press</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Veitch</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Aisen</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckett</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cairns</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jack</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jagust</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Saykin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Siuciak</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Toga</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojanowski</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><collab>Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging Initiative</collab><article-title>The Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging Initiative: A review of papers published
since its inception</article-title><source>Alzheimer's &#x00026; Dementia</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><issue>Suppl</issue><fpage>S1</fpage><lpage>S68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23495233</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Querbes</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Aubry</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pariente</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lotterie</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Demonet</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Duret</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Puel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Celsis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><collab>Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging Initiative</collab><article-title>Early diagnosis of Alzheimer's disease using cortical thickness: impact of
cognitive reserve</article-title><source>Brain</source><year>2009</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>2036</fpage><lpage>2047</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awp105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19439419</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ewers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojanowski</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jack</surname><given-names>CR</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bokde</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheltens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vellas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hampel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><collab>North American Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging Initiative (ADNI)</collab><article-title>Prediction of conversion from mild cognitive impairment to Alzheimer's disease
dementia based upon biomarkers and neuropsychological test performance</article-title><source>Neurobiol Aging</source><year>2012</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1203</fpage><lpage>1214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2010.10.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21159408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tabert</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Manly</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelton</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenblum</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamora</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodkind</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Devanand</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><article-title>Neuropsychological prediction of conversion to Alzheimer disease in patients with
mild cognitive impairment</article-title><source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source><year>2006</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>916</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archpsyc.63.8.916</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16894068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fleisher</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sowell</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamst</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Thal</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><article-title>Clinical predictors of progression to Alzheimer disease in amnestic mild cognitive
impairment</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>2007</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>1588</fpage><lpage>1595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/01.wnl.0000258542.58725.4c</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17287448</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tierney</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McDowell</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><article-title>Neuropsychological tests accurately predict incident Alzheimer disease after 5 and
10 years</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>2005</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>1853</fpage><lpage>1859</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/01.WNL.0000163773.21794.0B</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15955933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Blacker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Muzikansky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanzi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>McArdle</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Neuropsychological measures in normal individuals that predict subsequent
cognitive decline</article-title><source>Arch Neurol</source><year>2007</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>862</fpage><lpage>871</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archneur.64.6.862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17562935</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Delano-Wood</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bondi</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Abeles</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jak</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Libon</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bozoki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Heterogeneity in mild cognitive impairment: Differences in neuropsychological
profile and associated white matter lesion pathology</article-title><source>J Int Neuropsychol Soc</source><year>2009</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>906</fpage><lpage>914</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1355617709990257</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19891820</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><article-title>Cognitive reserve and Alzheimer disease</article-title><source>Alzheimer Dis Assoc Disord</source><year>2006</year><volume>20</volume><issue>Suppl 2</issue><fpage>S69</fpage><lpage>S74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16917199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><article-title>Cognitive reserve</article-title><source>Neuropsychologia</source><year>2009</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>2015</fpage><lpage>2028</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2009.03.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19467352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><article-title>Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging Initiative (ADNI) database</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.loni.ucla.edu/ADNI">http://www.loni.ucla.edu/ADNI</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><article-title>Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging Initiative (ADNI) investigators</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.loni.ucla.edu/ADNI/Collaboration/ADNI_Authorship_list.pdf">http://www.loni.ucla.edu/ADNI/Collaboration/ADNI_Authorship_list.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><article-title>Foundation for the National Institutes of Health</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fnih.org">http://www.fnih.org</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><article-title>Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging Initiative (ADNI)</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.adni-info.org">http://www.adni-info.org</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>