<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Alzheimers Res Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Alzheimers Res Ther</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Alzheimer's Research &#x00026; Therapy</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1758-9193</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24625058</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4055000</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">alzrt245</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/alzrt245</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Platelet-activating factor antagonists enhance intracellular degradation of amyloid-&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in neurons via regulation of cholesterol ester hydrolases</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1"><name><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>Charlotte</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>csimmons@rvc.ac.uk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Ingham</surname><given-names>Victoria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>v.e.ingham@sms.ed.ac.uk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Alun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>aw510@cam.ac.uk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A4"><name><surname>Bate</surname><given-names>Clive</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>cbate@rvc.ac.uk</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Pathology and Pathogen Biology, Royal Veterinary College, Hawkshead Lane, North Mymms, Herts AL9 7TA, UK</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Veterinary Medicine, University of Cambridge, Madingley Road, Cambridge CB3 OES, UK</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 Simmons et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Simmons et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://alzres.com/content/6/2/15"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>The progressive dementia that is characteristic of Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease is associated with the accumulation of amyloid-beta (A&#x003b2;) peptides in extracellular plaques and within neurons. A&#x003b2; peptides are targeted to cholesterol-rich membrane micro-domains called lipid rafts. Observations that many raft proteins undertake recycling pathways that avoid the lysosomes suggest that the accumulation of A&#x003b2; in neurons may be related to A&#x003b2; targeting lipid rafts. Here we tested the hypothesis that the degradation of A&#x003b2; by neurons could be increased by drugs affecting raft formation.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Primary neurons were incubated with soluble A&#x003b2; preparations. The amounts of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in neurons or specific cellular compartments were measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay. The effects of drugs on the degradation of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> were studied.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was targeted to detergent-resistant, low-density membranes (lipid rafts), trafficked via a pathway that avoided the lysosomes, and was slowly degraded by neurons (half-life was greater than 5&#x000a0;days). The metabolism of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was sensitive to pharmacological manipulation. In neurons treated with the cholesterol synthesis inhibitor squalestatin, less A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was found within rafts, greater amounts of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> were found in lysosomes, and the half-life of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was reduced to less than 24&#x000a0;hours. Treatment with phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> inhibitors or platelet-activating factor (PAF) antagonists had the same effects on A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> metabolism in neurons as squalestatin. PAF receptors were concentrated in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) along with enzymes that constitute the cholesterol ester cycle. The addition of PAF to ER membranes triggered activation of cholesterol ester hydrolases and the release of cholesterol from stores of cholesterol esters. An inhibitor of cholesterol ester hydrolases (diethylumbelliferyl phosphate) also increased the degradation of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in neurons.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>We conclude that the targeting of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> to rafts in normal cells is a factor that affects its degradation. Critically, pharmacological manipulation of neurons can significantly increase A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> degradation. These results are consistent with the hypothesis that the A&#x003b2;-induced production of PAF controls a cholesterol-sensitive pathway that affects the cellular localization and hence the fate of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in neurons.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The amyloid hypothesis of Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease (AD) pathogenesis maintains that the primary event is the production of specific C-terminal amyloid-beta (A&#x003b2;) peptides following the abnormal proteolytic cleavage of the amyloid precursor protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. A&#x003b2; oligomers demonstrate disease-specific accumulation in human brain and cerebrospinal fluid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. The accumulation of A&#x003b2; peptides leads to the subsequent disruption of neuronal processes, abnormal phosphorylation of tau [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>], and synapse degeneration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Currently, soluble A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> oligomers are regarded as potent neurotoxins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>].</p><p>Neurodegeneration is preceded by the intraneuronal accumulation of A&#x003b2; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. The chronic nature of AD suggests that it is a slow accumulation of A&#x003b2; that triggers neurodegeneration and hence the clinical symptoms. Whereas the factors that affect the production of the A&#x003b2; have been studied extensively, the capacity of neurons to degrade A&#x003b2; once it has been formed has received less attention. Thus, the accumulation of A&#x003b2; within neurons may result from a slow rate of degradation. A&#x003b2; peptides can be degraded by proteases, including neprilysin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>], insulysin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], cathepsin B [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>], and acyl peptide hydrolase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. The observation that A&#x003b2; was degraded more quickly in microglial cells than in neurons (unpublished data) raised the question of whether the rate of degradation of A&#x003b2; within neurons could be increased.</p><p>Studies that use synthetic A&#x003b2; preparations may be compromised by their propensity to self-aggregate into a wide variety of oligomer sizes and conformations. The polymorphic nature of A&#x003b2; aggregates suggests that there exist disease-relevant conformations of A&#x003b2; but that other conformations are less toxic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. It is difficult to control the size and conformation of synthetic A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> oligomers in aqueous medium and consequently it is not clear which of the A&#x003b2; conformations are responsible for specific biological properties. To overcome this problem, conditioned media from 7PA2 cells (7PA2-CM) which contain naturally secreted A&#x003b2; oligomers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] were used in this study. The A&#x003b2; oligomers secreted by these cells are sodium dodecyl sulphate (SDS)-stable, as are the A&#x003b2; oligomers found within the cerebrospinal fluid of patients with AD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Although 7PA2-CM includes other amyloid precursor protein (APP) metabolites, including A&#x003b2;<sub>40</sub> and p3, we decided to specifically measure A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> peptides because of the close association of this isoform with disease.</p><p>A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> peptides are found in detergent-resistant, cholesterol-dense membrane micro-domains which are commonly referred to as rafts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Since many raft-associated proteins traffic through cells via recycling pathways that avoid the lysosomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>], we hypothesized that the targeting of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> to rafts caused it to avoid the lysosomes and degradation. Thus, the targeting of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> to rafts may contribute to their gradual accumulation within neurons and subsequently their toxic effects. In this study, non-toxic concentrations of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> were taken up by cultured neurons and targeted to detergent-resistant membranes (DRMs) (lipid rafts). As a consequence, it was slowly degraded and had a half-life of greater than 5&#x000a0;days. As the formation and function of lipid rafts is dependent upon the amount of cholesterol within cell membranes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>], the effects of the cholesterol synthesis inhibitor squalestatin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] on the cellular targeting of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> were studied. Here, we show that, in neurons treated with squalestatin, significantly less A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was targeted to rafts and more was found within lysosomes. Consequently, in squalestatin-treated neurons, the half-life of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was reduced to less than 24&#x000a0;hours. Such results indicate that the pharmacological manipulation of neurons can alter the clearance of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Primary neuronal cultures</title><p>Cortical neurons were prepared from the brains of mouse embryos (day 15.5). Neurons were plated at 10<sup>6</sup> cells per well in six-well plates in Ham&#x02019;s F12 containing 5% fetal calf serum for 2&#x000a0;hours. Cultures were shaken (600&#x000a0;rpm for 5&#x000a0;minutes), and non-adherent cells were removed by two washes in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS). Neurons were subsequently grown in neurobasal medium containing B27 components supplemented with 5 nM brain-derived nerve growth factor for 10&#x000a0;days. Immunohistochemistry showed that the cells were greater than 95% neurofilament-positive. Less than 3% stained for glial fibrillary acidic protein (astrocytes) or for F4/80 (microglial cells). Neurons were pre-treated with test compounds for 3&#x000a0;hours before the addition of A&#x003b2; preparations, and the amount of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in treated neurons was measured at specific time points thereafter. All experiments were performed in accordance with European regulations (European community Council Directive, 1986, 56/609/EEC) and approved by the Royal Veterinary College ethics committee.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell extracts</title><p>Neurons were washed twice with PBS and homogenized in a buffer containing 10&#x000a0;mM Tris-HCl, pH&#x000a0;7.4, 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl, 10&#x000a0;mM EDTA, 0.5% Nonidet P-40, 0.5% sodium deoxycholate, 0.2% SDS, and mixed protease inhibitors (4-(2-Aminoethyl) benzenesulfonyl fluoride hydrochloride (AEBSF), Aprotinin, Leupeptin, Bestatin, Pepstatin A, and E-46) (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) at 10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL. Nuclei and large fragments were removed by centrifugation (300&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> for 5&#x000a0;minutes).</p></sec><sec><title>Isolation of detergent-resistant membranes</title><p>These membranes were isolated by their insolubility in non-ionic detergents as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Briefly, cells were homogenized in an ice-cold buffer containing 1% Triton X-100, 10&#x000a0;mM Tris-HCl, pH&#x000a0;7.2, 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl, 10&#x000a0;mM EDTA, and mixed protease inhibitors at 10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL, and nuclei and large fragments were removed by centrifugation (300&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> for 5&#x000a0;minutes at 4&#x000b0;C). The post-nuclear supernatant was incubated on ice (4&#x000b0;C) for 1&#x000a0;hour and centrifuged (16,000&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> for 30&#x000a0;minutes at 4&#x000b0;C). The supernatant was reserved as the detergent-soluble membrane; the insoluble pellet was homogenized in an extraction buffer containing 10&#x000a0;mM Tris-HCl, pH&#x000a0;7.4, 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl, 10&#x000a0;mM EDTA, 0.5% Nonidet P-40, 0.5% sodium deoxycholate, 0.2% SDS, and mixed protease inhibitors at 10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL and was centrifuged (10&#x000a0;minutes at 16,000&#x02009;<italic>g</italic>); and the soluble material was reserved as the DRM fraction.</p></sec><sec><title>Sucrose density isolation</title><p>Neurons were harvested with a Teflon scraper and collected at 800&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> for 5&#x000a0;minutes. Cell pellets were homogenized in a buffer containing 250&#x000a0;mM sucrose, 10&#x000a0;mM Tris-HCl (pH&#x000a0;7.4), 1&#x000a0;mM EGTA, mixed protease inhibitors, and 1&#x000a0;mM dithiothreitol at 10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL. Particulate membrane fragments and nuclei were removed by centrifugation (1,000&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> for 5&#x000a0;minutes). Membranes were washed by centrifugation at 16,000&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> for 10&#x000a0;minutes at 4&#x000b0;C and suspended in an ice-cold buffer containing 1% Triton X-100, 10&#x000a0;mM Tris-HCl pH&#x000a0;7.2, 150&#x000a0;mM NaCl, 10&#x000a0;mM EDTA. Sucrose solutions of 5%, 10%, 15%, 20%, 25%, 30%, and 40% were prepared and layered over each other. Solubilized membranes were added on top and centrifuged at 50,000&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> for 18&#x000a0;hours at 4&#x000b0;C. Serial 1-mL aliquots were collected from the bottom of gradients.</p></sec><sec><title>Isolation of lysosomes</title><p>Lysosomes were isolated by using a lysosome enrichment kit designed for cultured cells in accordance with the instructions of the manufacturer (Pierce, Rockford, IL, USA). Briefly, treated cells were collected and homogenized in ice-cold lysosome enrichment reagents containing protease inhibitors (as above). The cell extract was overlaid on a discontinuous density gradient prepared from OptiPrep&#x02122; media and centrifuged at 145,000&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> for 2&#x000a0;hours at 4&#x000b0;C. Serial 1-mL aliquots were collected from the bottom of gradients. The lysosome fraction was collected, washed three times in PBS (18,000&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> for 30&#x000a0;minutes at 4&#x000b0;C), and solubilized in an extraction buffer containing 10&#x000a0;mM Tris-HCl pH&#x000a0;7.4, 100&#x000a0;mM NaCl, 10&#x000a0;mM EDTA, 0.5% Nonidet P-40, 0.5% sodium deoxycholate, 0.2% SDS, and protease inhibitors (as above). Samples were mixed with an equal volume of Laemmli buffer, boiled, and subjected to electrophoresis on a 15% polyacrylamide gel. Proteins were transferred onto a Hybond-P polyvinylidiene fluoride (PVDF) membrane by semi-dry blotting. Membranes were blocked by using 10% milk powder in PBS containing 0.2% Tween 20. Blots were probed with anti-lysosome-associated membrane protein 1 (LAMP-1) (Pharmingen, San Diego, CA, USA) followed by peroxidase-labelled anti-rabbit antibodies and visualized by using enhanced chemiluminescence.</p></sec><sec><title>Isolation of endoplasmic reticulum</title><p>Endoplasmic reticulum (ER) fractions were isolated from treated cells by using an ER preparation kit (Sigma-Aldrich) in accordance with the instructions of the manufacturer. Homogenized cell extracts were separated on a discontinuous density gradient (OptiPrep&#x02122;). Serial 1-mL aliquots were collected from the bottom of gradients. Fractions were diluted 1:20 in carbonate buffer and distributed into Nunc Maxisorp immunoplates (Nunc, Roskilde, Denmark) overnight. Plates were blocked with 5% milk powder and probed with monoclonal antibody (mAb) reactive to the ER marker Grp 78 (Stressgen Biotechnology, Victoria, Canada), polyclonal anti-PAF receptor (Cayman Chemical Company, Ann Arbor, MI, USA), anti-cholesterol ester hydrolase (CEH) (LifeSpan BioSciences, Seattle, WA, USA), or anti-acyl-coenzyme A:cholesterol acyltransferase (ACAT) (Abcam, Cambridge, UK), followed by biotinylated anti-rabbit IgG (Sigma-Aldrich), extravidin-alkaline phosphatase (Sigma-Aldrich), and the addition of the substrate p-nitrophenyl phosphate (p-NPP), 1&#x000a0;ng/mL, diluted in diethanolamine buffer. Optical density was read in a spectrophotometer at 405&#x000a0;nm.</p></sec><sec><title>Cholesterol and protein content</title><p>Protein concentrations were measured by using a micro-BCA protein assay kit (Pierce). The amount of cholesterol was measured by using the Amplex Red cholesterol assay kit (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). Cholesterol was oxidized by cholesterol oxidase to yield hydrogen peroxide and ketones. The hydrogen peroxide reacts with 10-acetyl-3, 7-dihydroxyphenoxazine (Amplex Red) to produce highly fluorescent resorufin, which is measured by excitation at 550&#x000a0;nm and emission detection at 590&#x000a0;nm. Samples were incubated in the presence or absence of cholesterol esterase to determine the amounts of esterified cholesterol.</p></sec><sec><title>Drugs</title><p>Arachidonyl trifluoromethyl ketone (AACOCF<sub>3</sub>), acetyl salicylic acid, diethylumbelliferyl phosphate (DEUP), ginkgolide B, ibuprofen, platelet-activating factor (PAF), 1-O-Hexadecyl-2-acetyl-<italic>sn</italic>-glycerol-3-phospho-(N,N,N-trimethyl)-hexanolamine (Hexa-PAF), methyl arachidonyl fluorophosphonate (MAFP), acetyl salicylic acid, ibuprofen, simvastatin, and squalene were all obtained from Sigma-Aldrich. Squalestatin was a gift from GlaxoSmithKline (Uxbridge, Middlesex, UK). Stock solutions were dissolved in ethanol or di-methyl sulphoxide and diluted in medium to obtain final working concentrations. Vehicle controls consisted of equivalent dilutions of ethanol or di-methyl sulphoxide in culture medium.</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of A&#x003b2;-containing medium</title><p>Conditioned media (CM) from Chinese hamster ovary (CHO) cells stably transfected with a cDNA encoding APP<sub>751</sub> (referred to as 7PA2 cells) was cultured in Dulbecco&#x02019;s modified Eagle&#x02019;s medium with 10% fetal calf serum as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. CM from these cells contains stable A&#x003b2; (7PA2-CM). 7PA2-CM was centrifuged at 100,000&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> for 4&#x000a0;hours at 4&#x000b0;C to remove cell debris and then passed through a 50-kDa filter (Sartorius, Goettingen, Germany) before use. To demonstrate A&#x003b2; species, concentrated 7PA2-CM was mixed 1:1 with (0.5% NP-40, 5&#x000a0;mM CHAPS, 50&#x000a0;mM Tris-HCl, pH&#x000a0;7.4, and mixed protease inhibitors) and separated by polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE) under non-denaturing conditions. Proteins were transferred onto a Hybond-P PVDF membrane (Amersham Biotech, now part of GE Healthcare, Little Chalfont, Buckinghamshire, UK) by semi-dry blotting. Membranes were blocked by using 10% milk powder and incubated with mAb 6E10 reactive with amino acids 1 to 16 of human A&#x003b2; (Signet, part of Covance, Princeton, NJ, USA). Bound mAbs were detected with biotinylated anti-mouse IgG, extravidin-peroxidase, and enhanced chemiluminescence.</p></sec><sec><title>Size exclusion chromatography</title><p>7PA2-CM or brain extracts were concentrated by desalting columns (3-kDa filter; Sartorius) and injected into a Superdex 75 PC column (separates peptides ranging from 3 to 70&#x000a0;kDa) (GE Healthcare) and eluted at a rate of 0.2&#x000a0;mL/minute. Fractions were collected and tested by A&#x003b2; enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) (see below).</p></sec><sec><title>Sample preparation</title><p>To detach A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> from cellular binding proteins that could occlude specific epitopes, cell extracts (200&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L) were mixed with 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of 70% formic acid and sonicated. A 50-&#x003bc;L aliquot was added to 450&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of 1&#x000a0;M Tris-HCl with protease inhibitors (as above) and sonicated before addition to ELISA.</p></sec><sec><title>Synthetic A&#x003b2;</title><p>A peptide corresponding to amino acids 1 to 42 of A&#x003b2; (A&#x003b2;<sub>1-42</sub>) was obtained from Bachem (Bubendorf, Switzerland) and dissolved in hexafluoroisopropanol, lyophilized, and stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C. On the day of use, it was dissolved in dimethylsulphoxide at 1&#x000a0;mM, diluted in culture medium, and sonicated prior to addition to cells.</p></sec><sec><title>A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay</title><p>Nunc Maxisorp immunoplates were coated with mAb 4G8 (epitope 17-24) (Covance) in carbonate buffer overnight. Plates were blocked with 5% milk powder in PBS-tween, and samples were applied. The detection antibody was an A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> selective rabbit mAb BA3-9 (Covance) followed by biotinylated anti-rabbit IgG (Sigma-Aldrich). Total A&#x003b2; was visualized by addition of the substrate (pNPP) 1&#x000a0;ng/mL, diluted in diethanolamine buffer, and optical density was read in a spectrophotometer at 405&#x000a0;nm.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical methods</title><p>Differences between treatment groups were assessed by using Student <italic>t</italic> tests.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Squalestatin increased the degradation of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub></title><p>The amount and distribution of cholesterol are recognized as factors that affect the progression of AD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. As squalestatin reduced the cholesterol content of cultured neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>], the fate of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in squalestatin-treated neurons was examined. Treatment with 200 nM squalestatin for 24&#x000a0;hours reduced the cholesterol content of neurons from 519&#x000a0;ng cholesterol/10<sup>6</sup> cells&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;48 to 369&#x000a0;ng&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;66, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;6, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.05, without affecting neuronal viability as measured by thiazolyl blue tetrazolium (MTT). Both treated and untreated neurons were subsequently incubated with 7PA2-CM containing 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>, a mixture of monomers, dimers, trimers, and tetramers as shown in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>A. An analysis of concentrated 7PA2-CM by size exclusion chromatography also showed that it contained three main peaks corresponding to monomers, dimers, and trimers (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>B). The concentrations of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> used did not affect neuronal survival during the 5-day incubation period. In control neurons, A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> had a half-life of greater than 5&#x000a0;days, whereas in squalestatin-treated neurons, the half-life of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was reduced to less than 24&#x000a0;hours (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>C). A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was not detected in cell supernatants, suggesting that the A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> had been digested rather than secreted from neurons. Experiments performed using synthetic A&#x003b2;<sub>1-42</sub> showed that it behaved like the cell-derived A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>; it had a half-life of greater than 5&#x000a0;days in untreated neurons and a much shorter half-life in squalestatin-treated neurons (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>D).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Squalestatin increased the degradation of A&#x003b2;</bold><sub><bold>42</bold></sub><bold>. (A)</bold> Immunoblot showing amyloid-beta (A&#x003b2;) monomers (M), dimers (D), and trimers (T) in conditioned media from 7PA2 cells (7PA2-CM) (1) and in A&#x003b2;-depleted 7PA2-CM (2). <bold>(B)</bold> A&#x003b2; monomers, dimers, and trimers eluted from a Superdex 75 PC column (separates proteins ranging from 3 to 70&#x000a0;kDa) loaded with concentrated 7PA2-CM. Values are mean A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> of duplicates. <bold>(C)</bold> Neurons were pre-treated with control medium (&#x025cf;) or 200 nM squalestatin (&#x025cb;), pulsed with 7PA2-CM containing 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>, and incubated for 1 to 5&#x000a0;days as shown. Values are mean A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> remaining in neurons&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation (SD) from triplicate experiments performed four times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;12). <bold>(D)</bold> Neurons were pre-treated with control medium (&#x025cf;) or 200 nM squalestatin (&#x025cb;), pulsed with 100 nM synthetic A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>, and incubated for 1 to 5&#x000a0;days as shown. Values are mean A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in neurons&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD from triplicate experiments performed four times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;12). <bold>(E)</bold> Neurons were pre-treated with control medium (&#x025a0;) or 200 nM squalestatin (&#x025a1;) and pulsed with 7PA2-CM containing A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> as shown for 2&#x000a0;hours. Values are mean neuronal A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD from triplicate experiments performed three times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;9). <bold>(F)</bold> Neurons, incubated with 7PA2-CM containing 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> for 2&#x000a0;days, were treated with control medium (&#x025a0;) or 200 nM squalestatin (&#x025a1;) for 24&#x000a0;hours. Values are the mean A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> remaining in neurons&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD from triplicate experiments performed three times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;9). *Concentrations of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> significantly less (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.05) than controls.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt245-1"/></fig><p>Similar results were obtained in neurons that had been treated with 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M simvastatin, a clinically approved hydroxymethyl glutaryl coenzyme A reductase inhibitor that also reduced cellular cholesterol levels. As cholesterol depletion has been demonstrated to affect the expression of some receptors, including the cellular prion protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>] and acetylcholine receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>], the possibility that it reduced the binding of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> to neurons was explored. There were no significant differences in the amounts of cell-bound A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> between control and squalestatin-treated neurons, indicating that cholesterol depletion did not affect the binding of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> to neurons (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>E). In further studies, neurons were pulsed with 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>; after 2&#x000a0;days, 200 nM squalestatin was added, and cell extracts were collected 1&#x000a0;day later. The amount of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in squalestatin-treated neurons was significantly less than in mock-treated neurons (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>F).</p></sec><sec><title>Squalestatin altered the distribution of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in neurons</title><p>Next, we looked at the distribution of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> within neurons. In control neurons incubated with 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> for 2&#x000a0;hours, most A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was found within DRMs, observations that are consistent with reports that membrane-bound A&#x003b2; was recruited into lipid rafts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. In squalestatin-treated neurons, significantly less A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was found within DRMs (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>A). Since many of the proteins that are targeted to lipid rafts traffic via a recycling pathway that avoids the lysosomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>], an organelle fractionation technique was used to examine the targeting of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> to lysosomes. Organelles from neurons were separated on a density gradient, and lysosomes were identified by using immunoblots for lysosome-associated antigen 1 (LAMP-1), a marker of late endosomes/lysosomes. LAMP-1 was enriched within fractions 4 to 6, which were subsequently pooled to represent the lysosomes (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>B). Firstly, we showed that treatment with 200 nM squalestatin did not affect the amount of the LAMP-1 found in neurons (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>C). Next, treated neurons were incubated with 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> for 2&#x000a0;hours, and the amount of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in lysosomes was measured. The amounts of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in lysosomes from squalestatin-treated neurons were significantly higher than the amounts of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in lysosomes from control neurons (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>D).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Squalestatin alters the cellular distribution of A&#x003b2;</bold><sub><bold>42</bold></sub><bold>. (A)</bold> Concentrations of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in detergent-resistant membranes (DRMs) (rafts) or detergent-soluble membranes (DSMs) 2&#x000a0;hours after the addition of conditioned media from 7PA2 cells (7PA2-CM) containing 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> to neurons pre-treated with control medium (&#x025a0;) or 200 nM squalestatin (&#x025a1;). Values are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation (SD) from triplicate experiments performed three times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;9). <bold>(B)</bold> Cell extracts from neurons were separated on sucrose density gradients and analyzed by immunoblot for lysosome-associated membrane protein 1 (LAMP-1), a marker of lysosomes. <bold>(C)</bold> Immunoblot showing the amount of LAMP-1 in extracts from neurons treated with control medium or 200 nM squalestatin. <bold>(D)</bold> The amount of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in lysosomes derived from neurons treated with control medium (&#x025a1;) or 200 nM squalestatin (&#x025a1;) and incubated with 7PA2-CM containing 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> for 2&#x000a0;hours. Values are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD from triplicate experiments performed three times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;9). *Concentrations of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> significantly higher (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.05) than controls.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt245-2"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Squalene reversed the effect of squalestatin on the cellular distribution of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub></title><p>One explanation of these results is that the squalestatin-induced reduction in cholesterol disrupts the formation of lipid rafts that direct A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> into a pathway that avoids the lysosomes. This hypothesis was tested by incubating neurons with combinations of squalestatin and squalene. The addition of 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M squalene alone did not increase cholesterol concentrations above those of control cells (527&#x000a0;ng cholesterol/10<sup>6</sup> cells&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;28 to 519&#x000a0;ng&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;48, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;6, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.74), but the addition of 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M squalene reversed the effects of 200 nM squalestatin on cellular cholesterol concentrations (496&#x000a0;ng cholesterol/10<sup>6</sup> cells&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;45 to 369&#x000a0;ng&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;66, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;6, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.05). The addition of 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M squalene also reversed the effects of 200 nM squalestatin on the trafficking of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>; the amount of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in DRMs was significantly lower and the amount in lysosomes significantly higher in neurons treated with squalestatin when compared with neurons treated with a combination of squalestatin and squalene (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Furthermore, the effect of squalestatin on the degradation of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> by neurons was reversed by the addition of squalene. When neurons incubated with 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> for 2&#x000a0;days were subsequently treated with combinations of squalestatin and squalene for 24&#x000a0;hours, the amounts of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in neurons treated with 200 nM squalestatin and 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M squalene were significantly higher than in neurons treated with 200 nM squalestatin alone (8.9 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8 compared with 2.4 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;9, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.01).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><bold>Squalene reversed the effects of squalestatin upon A&#x003b2;</bold><sub>
<bold>42 </bold>
</sub><bold>trafficking</bold></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="center" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></th><th colspan="3" align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>Concentration of A&#x003b2;</bold><sub>
<bold>42</bold>
</sub><bold>, nM</bold><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th align="center"><bold>Cell extracts</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>DRMs</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Lysosomes</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>Control</bold><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">8.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">8.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>Squalestatin</bold><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">8.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6<sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5<sup>b</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>Squalene</bold><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">8.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.85<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>Squalestatin&#x02009;+&#x02009;squalene</bold></td><td align="center">8.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6</td><td align="center">7.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9</td><td align="center">0.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Neurons were pre-treated with 200 nM squalestatin, 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M squalene, or a mixture of squalestatin and squalene and then incubated with conditioned media from 7PA2 cells (7PA2-CM) containing 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> for 2&#x000a0;hours. The concentrations of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in whole cell extracts, detergent-resistant membranes (DRMs) (lipid rafts), and lysosomes were measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay. Values are the mean concentration of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation from triplicate experiments performed three times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;9). <sup>a</sup>Amounts of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> significantly lower than in control cells. <sup>b</sup>Amounts of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> significantly higher than in control cells.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> and platelet-activating factor affect the degradation of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub></title><p>As A&#x003b2; activates cytoplasmic phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> (cPLA<sub>2</sub>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>], an enzyme that is implicated in tubule formation and intracellular trafficking [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>], specifically within the trans-Golgi network [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>], the effects of cPLA<sub>2</sub> inhibitors on A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> distribution were studied. Neurons were pulsed with 7PA2-CM containing 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> for 2&#x000a0;hours and were washed, and cell extracts were collected at time points thereafter. Pre-treatment of neurons with cPLA<sub>2</sub> inhibitors (1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M AACOCF<sub>3</sub> or MAFP) significantly reduced the half-life of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in neurons (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>A). As the activation of cPLA<sub>2</sub> results in the production of prostaglandins and PAF, specific inhibitors/antagonists of these mediators were also tested. The half-life of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was reduced in neurons pre-treated with PAF receptor antagonists (1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M ginkgolide B or 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M Hexa-PAF) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>B) but not in neurons pre-treated with cyclo-oxygenase inhibitors (1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M aspirin or 2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M ibuprofen) that reduce the production of prostaglandins. In neurons pre-treated with ginkgolide B or Hexa-PAF, the half-life of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was reduced to less than 24&#x000a0;hours. The addition of 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M Hexa-PAF to neurons that had been incubated with 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> for 2&#x000a0;days resulted in the increased degradation of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>C). A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was not detected in the supernatants collected from either control or treated neurons, indicating that it was not secreted. Such results suggest that PAF, produced in response to A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>-induced activation of cPLA<sub>2</sub>, regulates the trafficking and hence the degradation of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in neurons. In support of this hypothesis, we found that the addition of 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M PAF reversed the effects of the cPLA<sub>2</sub> inhibitor (AACOCF<sub>3</sub>) upon the degradation of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in neurons (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>D). Experiments performed using synthetic A&#x003b2;<sub>1-42</sub> showed that it had a half-life of approximately 24&#x000a0;hours in neurons pre-treated with Hexa-PAF (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>E).</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Platelet-activating factor (PAF) receptor antagonists increased the degradation of A&#x003b2;</bold><sub><bold>42</bold></sub><bold>. (A)</bold> Amounts of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in neurons pre-treated with control medium (&#x025cf;), 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M AACOCF<sub>3</sub> (&#x025cb;), or 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M MAFP (&#x025a1;), pulsed with conditioned media from 7PA2 cells (7PA2-CM) containing 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>, and incubated for 1 to 5&#x000a0;days. Values are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation (SD) from triplicate experiments performed four times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;12). <bold>(B)</bold> Amounts of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in neurons pre-treated with control medium (&#x025cf;), 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M Hexa-PAF (&#x025cb;), or 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M ginkgolide B (&#x025a1;), pulsed with 7PA2-CM containing 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>, and incubated for 1 to 5&#x000a0;days. Values are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD from triplicate experiments performed four times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;12). <bold>(C)</bold> Neurons were incubated with 7PA2-CM containing 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>. After 2&#x000a0;days, 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M Hexa-PAF (&#x025cb;) or control medium (&#x025cf;) was added and the amounts of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> were measured thereafter. Values are mean A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD from triplicate experiments performed four times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;12). <bold>(D)</bold> Neurons were pre-treated with control medium (&#x025cf;), 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M PAF (&#x025a1;), 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M AACOCF<sub>3</sub> (&#x025cb;), or a combination of 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M AACOCF<sub>3</sub> and 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M PAF (&#x025a0;) and incubated with 7PA2-CM containing 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> for 1 to 5&#x000a0;days. Values are mean A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD from triplicate experiments performed three times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;9). <bold>(E)</bold> The amount of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in neurons pre-treated with control medium (&#x025cf;) or 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M Hexa-PAF (&#x025cb;), pulsed with 100 nM synthetic A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>, and incubated for 1 to 5&#x000a0;days. Values are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD, from triplicate experiments performed four times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;12). AACOCF<sub>3</sub>, arachidonyl trifluoromethyl ketone; Hexa-PAF, 1-O-hexadecyl-2-acetyl-<italic>sn</italic>-glycerol-3-phospho-(N,N,N-trimethyl)-hexanolamine; MAFP, methyl arachidonyl fluorophosphonate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt245-3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Hexa-PAF altered the distribution of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in neurons</title><p>As the effects of Hexa-PAF on the neuronal degradation of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> were similar to those of squalestatin, its effects upon cellular distribution of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> were studied. After the addition of 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> for 2&#x000a0;hours, we found no significant differences in the amounts of cell-associated A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> between control and Hexa-PAF-treated neurons (9.1 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 compared with 8.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;9, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.32). However, pre-treatment of neurons with 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M Hexa-PAF or 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M ginkgolide B significantly reduced the amount of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> found within DRMs (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>A). Since the detergent solubility assay is a crude test of membrane targeting, neurons were incubated for 2&#x000a0;hours with 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> and membranes were separated on sucrose density gradients. In control neurons, most of the A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was found in low-density membrane fractions. In neurons pre-treated with 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M Hexa-PAF, less of the A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was found within low-density fractions (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>B). Although treatment with 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M Hexa-PAF did not affect the amount of the LAMP-1 found in neurons (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>C), the amounts of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in lysosomes from neurons pre-treated with Hexa-PAF or ginkgolide B were significantly higher than the amounts of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in lysosomes from control neurons (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>D).</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Platelet-activating factor (PAF) receptor antagonists altered the distribution of A&#x003b2;</bold><sub><bold>42 </bold></sub><bold>in neurons. (A)</bold> The amount of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in detergent-soluble membrane (DSM) (&#x025a1;) or detergent-resistant membrane (DRM) (&#x025a0;) extracts from neurons pre-treated with control medium, 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M ginkgolide B, or 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M Hexa-PAF and pulsed with conditioned media from 7PA2 cells (7PA2-CM) containing 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> for 2&#x000a0;hours. Values are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation (SD) from triplicate experiments performed four times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;12). *Concentration of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> significantly higher (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.05) than in control neurons. <bold>(B)</bold> Neurons treated with control medium (&#x025cf;) or 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M Hexa-PAF (&#x025a1;) and pulsed with 7PA2-CM containing 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> for 2&#x000a0;hours. Cell extracts were separated on sucrose density gradients. Values are mean A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD from triplicate experiments (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). <bold>(C)</bold> Immunoblot showing the amounts of lysosome-associated membrane protein 1 (LAMP-1) in neurons treated with control medium or 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M Hexa-PAF. <bold>(D)</bold> Neurons were pre-treated with control medium (&#x025a1;), 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M Hexa-PAF, 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M ginkgolide B, or 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M PAF and pulsed with 7PA2-CM containing 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> for 2&#x000a0;hours when lysosomes were isolated. Values are mean A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD from triplicate experiments performed four times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;12). *Concentration of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> significantly higher (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.05) than in control neurons. Hexa-PAF, 1-O-hexadecyl-2-acetyl-<italic>sn</italic>-glycerol-3-phospho-(N,N,N-trimethyl)-hexanolamine.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt245-4"/></fig></sec><sec><title>The effects of Hexa-PAF are not reversed by squalene</title><p>The similar effects of squalestatin and Hexa-PAF upon A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> trafficking suggested that Hexa-PAF may affect cholesterol synthesis. However, treatment with either 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M PAF or 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M Hexa-PAF did not significantly affect the amounts of cholesterol in neurons and the addition of 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M squalene did not reverse the effects of Hexa-PAF upon the targeting of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> to DRMs or lysosomes (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>) nor alter the half-life of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in Hexa-PAF-treated neurons, indicating that Hexa-PAF did not affect cholesterol synthesis. Next, we explored the hypothesis that PAF increased cholesterol in specific cellular compartments. We sought to identify such compartments by separating organelles upon density gradients. PAF receptors were found in high concentrations in fractions 6 to 8 (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>A), fractions that also contained Grp78, a marker of the ER. These fractions were subsequently pooled and incubated with or without PAF. The addition of 2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M PAF caused a significant increase in cholesterol (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>B). The PAF-induced increase in cholesterol in these fractions was not blocked by the inclusion of 200 nM squalestatin, indicating that PAF was not stimulating cholesterol synthesis. Conversely, the addition of PAF significantly reduced the amounts of cholesterol esters in ER fractions (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>C).</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Platelet-activating factor (PAF) increased cholesterol in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) of neurons. (A)</bold> Neuronal extracts were separated by density gradient centrifugation and analyzed for PAF receptor (&#x025a1;) and the ER marker Grp 78 (&#x025a0;). <bold>(B)</bold> The amounts of cholesterol in ER fractions incubated with control medium (&#x025a1;), 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M squalestatin, or 2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M PAF or pre-treated with squalestatin and incubated with PAF (&#x025a0;) for 1&#x000a0;hour. Values are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation (SD) from triplicate experiments performed three times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;9). *Concentration of cholesterol significantly higher (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.05) than in controls. <bold>(C)</bold> The amounts of cholesterol esters in ER fractions incubated with control medium (&#x025a1;), 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M squalestatin, or 2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M PAF or pre-treated with squalestatin and incubated with PAF (&#x025a0;). Values are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD from triplicate experiments performed three times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;9). *Concentration of cholesterol esters significantly lower (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.05) than in controls.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt245-5"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><bold>Squalene does not reverse the effects of Hexa-PAF upon A&#x003b2;</bold><sub>
<bold>42 </bold>
</sub><bold>trafficking</bold></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="center" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></th><th colspan="3" align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>Concentration of A&#x003b2;</bold><sub>
<bold>42</bold>
</sub><bold>, nM</bold><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th align="center"><bold>Cell extracts</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>DRMs</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Lysosomes</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>Control</bold><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">8.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">8.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>Hexa-PAF</bold><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">8.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9<sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6<sup>b</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>Squalene</bold><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">8.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>Hexa-PAF&#x02009;+&#x02009;squalene</bold></td><td align="center">8.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6</td><td align="center">2.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center">3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4<sup>b</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Neurons were pre-treated with 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M Hexa-PAF, 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M squalene, or a mixture of Hexa-PAF and squalene and then incubated with conditioned media from 7PA2 cells (7PA2-CM) containing 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> for 2&#x000a0;hours. The amounts of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in whole cell extracts, detergent-resistant membranes (DRMs) (lipid rafts), and lysosomes were measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay. Values are the mean concentration of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation from triplicate experiments performed three times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;9). <sup>a</sup>Amounts of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> significantly lower than in control cells. <sup>b</sup>Amounts of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> significantly higher than in control cells. Hexa-PAF, 1-O-hexadecyl-2-acetyl-<italic>sn</italic>-glycerol-3-phospho-(N,N,N-trimethyl)-hexanolamine.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Platelet-activating factor stimulates the release of cholesterol from stores of cholesterol esters</title><p>To determine the source of the PAF-induced increase in cholesterol, other methods of cholesterol regulation were explored. The amounts of cholesterol within cells is tightly controlled via a mixture of synthesis, uptake, and efflux and by esterification of cholesterol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. The cholesterol ester cycle involves the esterification of cholesterol by ACAT and the storage of cholesterol esters as cytoplasmic droplets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]. Conversely, the hydrolysis of cholesterol esters results in the release of cholesterol from these stores. Thus, the cholesterol ester cycle helps maintain a constant level of cholesterol in cell membranes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. Our findings that that both ACAT and CEH were concentrated in the ER fractions along with PAF receptors (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>A) suggested that PAF-induced activation of CEH released cholesterol. To explore the role of CEH in the trafficking of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>, an inhibitor of CEH (DEUP) was used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]. Treatment with 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M DEUP did not significantly affect total neuronal cholesterol levels (552&#x000a0;ng cholesterol&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;34 compared with 519&#x000a0;ng&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;48, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;6, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.26). However, pre-treatment of ER fractions with 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M DEUP blocked the PAF-induced increase in cholesterol (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>B) and the PAF-induced reduction in cholesterol esters (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>C). Pre-treatment of neurons with 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M DEUP did not alter the amount of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> that bound to neurons, but reduced the amounts of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in DRMs and increased the amounts of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in lysosomes (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). As a consequence, the half-life of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in DEUP-treated cells was reduced to approximately 24&#x000a0;hours (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>D). Pre-treatment of neurons with 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M DEUP also reduced the half-life of synthetic A&#x003b2;<sub>1-42</sub> to approximately 24&#x000a0;hours (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>E). Notably, these effects of DEUP were not reversed by the inclusion of 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M squalene, indicating that they were not mediated by inhibition of cholesterol synthesis. Collectively these results suggest that CEH regulates the hydrolysis of cholesterol esters in the ER which is involved in the trafficking of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>.</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Platelet-activating factor (PAF) causes the release of cholesterol in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER). (A)</bold> Neuronal extracts were separated by density gradient centrifugation and analyzed for cholesterol ester hydrolase (CEH) (&#x025a1;) and anti-acyl-coenzyme A:cholesterol acyltransferase (ACAT) (&#x025a0;). <bold>(B)</bold> The amount of cholesterol in ER fractions pre-treated with control medium (&#x025a1;), 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M diethylumbelliferyl phosphate (DEUP), or 2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M PAF or pre-treated with DEUP and incubated with PAF (&#x025a0;). Values are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation (SD) from triplicate experiments performed three times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;9). *Significantly less (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.05) cholesterol than ER fractions incubated with PAF. <bold>(C)</bold> The amount of cholesterol esters in ER fractions incubated with control medium (&#x025a1;), 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M DEUP, or 2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M PAF or pre-treated with DEUP and incubated with PAF (&#x025a0;). Values are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD from triplicate experiments performed three times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;9). *Significantly more (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.05) cholesterol esters than ER fractions incubated with PAF. <bold>(D)</bold> Neurons treated with control medium (&#x025cf;) or 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M DEUP (&#x025cb;) were pulsed with conditioned media from 7PA2 cells (7PA2-CM) containing 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> and incubated for 1 to 5&#x000a0;days as shown. Values are mean A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD from triplicate experiments performed four times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;12). <bold>(E)</bold> The amount of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in neurons pre-treated with control medium (&#x025cf;) or 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M DEUP (&#x025cb;), pulsed with 100 nM synthetic A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>, and incubated for 1 to 5&#x000a0;days. Values are mean A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD from triplicate experiments performed four times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;12).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt245-6"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><bold>Squalene does not reverse the effects of DEUP upon A&#x003b2;</bold><sub>
<bold>42 </bold>
</sub><bold>trafficking</bold></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="center" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></th><th colspan="3" align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>Concentration of A&#x003b2;</bold><sub>
<bold>42</bold>
</sub><bold>, nM</bold><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th align="center"><bold>Cell extracts</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>DRMs</bold></th><th align="center"><bold>Lysosomes</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>Control</bold><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">8.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">8.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>DEUP</bold><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">8.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7<sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3<sup>b</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>Squalene</bold><hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">8.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">0.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>DEUP&#x02009;+&#x02009;squalene</bold></td><td align="center">8.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8</td><td align="center">2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center">2.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3<sup>b</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Neurons were pre-treated with 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M diethylumbelliferyl phosphate (DEUP), 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M squalene, or a mixture of DEUP and squalene and then incubated with conditioned media from 7PA2 cells (7PA2-CM) containing 10 nM A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> for 2&#x000a0;hours. The amounts of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in whole cell extracts, detergent-resistant membranes (DRMs) (lipid rafts), and lysosomes were measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay. Values are the mean concentration of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation from triplicate experiments performed three times (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;9). <sup>a</sup>Amounts of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> significantly less than in control cells. <sup>b</sup>Amounts of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> significantly higher than in control cells.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study showed that A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> taken up by cultured neurons was found predominantly within lipid rafts, traffics via a pathway that avoids the lysosomes and consequently was cleared slowly. We hypothesize that the slow clearance of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> from neurons is a significant factor in the accumulation of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> within the brain and leads to synapse damage and dementia in AD. Critically we show that these properties are dependent upon A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>-induced activation of PLA<sub>2</sub>, the production of PAF, and the activation of CEH, the blockade of which alters the distribution of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in neurons and greatly increased its degradation.</p><p>This study used nanomolar concentrations of A&#x003b2; which did not affect the viability of neurons and which were similar to those found in the cerebrospinal fluid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>] or in soluble brain extracts from patients with AD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]. In control neurons, most of the A&#x003b2; was found within rafts, an observation consistent with reports that A&#x003b2; in the brain is found within cholesterol-dense membrane rafts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Reports that A&#x003b2; affects cellular cholesterol homeostasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>] suggested that A&#x003b2; modifies the biochemistry of cell membranes and thus creates the rafts that are responsible for its trafficking. The targeting of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> to rafts may have important biological consequences as many of the proteins that are targeted to rafts avoid the classic endocytic trafficking pathway that ends in the lysosomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]. Our observations were compatible with A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> trafficking via a recycling pathway in neurons as little A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was found within lysosomes and consequently A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> had a long half-life (over 5&#x000a0;days) in these neuronal cultures.</p><p>Here, we show that the trafficking of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> within neurons could be affected by inhibiting cholesterol synthesis. Cholesterol has multiple effects upon cells, including altering membrane fluidity, protein trafficking, endocytosis, and exocytosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>]. More specifically, cholesterol is important for the formation and function of membrane rafts, and in cholesterol-depleted neurons, most of the A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was excluded from such rafts. Consequently, more A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was found within lysosomes and the half-life of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was reduced from over 5&#x000a0;days in untreated neurons to less than 24&#x000a0;hours in squalestatin-treated neurons. Squalestatin was used because it inhibits squalene synthetase and reduces cholesterol production without affecting the production of the isoprenoids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. However, because squalestatin does not cross the blood-brain barrier, it does not have clinical application. Similar results were obtained in neurons treated with simvastatin, a cholesterol synthesis inhibitor that crosses the blood-brain barrier (data not shown). Simvastatin is widely used clinically and has been reported to reduce cholesterol levels within the brain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>].</p><p>Since cholesterol synthesis inhibitors affect many cholesterol-sensitive processes, we sought to find a compound with a more selective effect on rafts containing A&#x003b2;. Here, we showed that inhibitors of cPLA<sub>2</sub>, an enzyme that is implicated in tubule formation and intracellular trafficking [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>], also affected A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> distribution. The activation of cPLA<sub>2</sub> is the first step in the production of PAF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>]. PAF is produced in neurons incubated with A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>, and the amounts of PAF were elevated in both the temporal cortex of patients with AD and in murine AD models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>]. Our study suggested that the effects of cPLA<sub>2</sub> inhibitors on A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> distribution were mediated by a reduction in PAF production; not only did PAF antagonists have similar effects as cPLA<sub>2</sub> inhibitors, but PAF also reversed the effects of cPLA<sub>2</sub> inhibitors on A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> distribution and degradation.</p><p>Treating neurons with PLA<sub>2</sub> inhibitors, PAF antagonists, or PAF did not affect total cellular cholesterol concentrations, suggesting that these drugs did not affect cholesterol synthesis. PAF receptors were concentrated in the ER, and PAF increased cholesterol concentrations within ER fractions. Our studies are consistent with the hypothesis that local cholesterol concentrations within the ER affect the formation and functional rafts involved in the trafficking of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>. Consequently, PAF antagonists had similar effects to squalestatin on the trafficking of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in that they reduced the amount of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> within rafts. PAF is involved in endocytosis and endosome formation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>], and the blockade of PAF receptors may block the formation of endocytic structures involved in the trafficking or A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>. In neurons pre-treated with PAF receptor antagonists, more A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was detected within lysosomes, sites of protein degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>], and the half-life of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was reduced to less than 24&#x000a0;hours.</p><p>Notably, the PAF-induced increase in cholesterol was accompanied by reduced cholesterol esters, suggesting that cholesterol was being released from stores of cholesterol esters. The enzymes involved in the cholesterol ester cycle, ACAT and CEH, were also concentrated in the ER [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">67</xref>], and the PAF-induced increase in cholesterol was blocked by inhibition of CEH. The role of CEH in A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> metabolism was demonstrated by using an inhibitor of CEH [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>], which greatly increased the degradation of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in a similar manner as PAF antagonists or squalestatin. Collectively these results indicate that PAF regulates the deacylation of cholesterol esters in the ER, freeing cholesterol that affects the formation and function of rafts which are involved in the trafficking of A&#x003b2;<sub>42.</sub></p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In summary, these results support the hypothesis that A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub>-induced activation of PLA<sub>2</sub> leads to the production of PAF which releases cholesterol from cholesterol esters. The cholesterol helps stabilize A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in rafts which traffic via a recycling pathway that avoids the lysosomes. Thus, PAF receptor antagonists that reduce the release of cholesterol affect the rafts that direct A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> into the recycling pathway as summarized in Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>. Consequently, in these neurons, the half-life of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was greatly reduced. In neurons treated with cholesterol synthesis inhibitors, PAF antagonists, or CEH inhibitors, the trafficking of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> is altered so that A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> was found outside rafts, was targeted to lysosomes, and rapidly degraded. The novel observation that the activation of specific signaling pathways controls the trafficking and degradation of A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> may aid the development of drugs to delay the progression of AD.</p><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>Platelet-activating factor (PAF)-mediated hydrolysis of cholesterol esters stabilizes amyloid-beta (A&#x003b2;)-containing lipid rafts.</bold> Schematic demonstrating the putative mechanism regulating the formation of A&#x003b2;-containing rafts. In this theory, A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> activates cPLA<sub>2</sub>, resulting in the production of PAF. PAF activates cholesterol ester hydrolase (CEH) and the release of cholesterol from stores of cholesterol esters, which stabilizes A&#x003b2;<sub>42</sub> in rafts. Inhibition of cPLA<sub>2</sub> (arachidonyl trifluoromethyl ketone, or AACOCF<sub>3</sub>), antagonism of the PAF receptors (Hexa-PAF), or inhibition of CEH (diethylumbelliferyl phosphate, is DEUP) reduces the cholesterol concentrations in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER). cPLA<sub>2</sub>, cPLA2 is cytoplasmic phospholipase A<sub>2</sub>; Hexa-PAF, 1-O-hexadecyl-2-acetyl-<italic>sn</italic>-glycerol-3-phospho-(N,N,N-trimethyl)-hexanolamine.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alzrt245-7"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>7PA2-CM: conditioned media from 7PA2 cells; AACOCF3: arachidonyl trifluoromethyl ketone; ACAT: acyl-coenzyme A:cholesterol acyltransferase; AD: Alzheimer&#x02019;s diesease; A&#x003b2;: amyloid-beta; CEH: cholesterol ester hydrolase; CM: conditioned media; cPLA2: cytoplasmic phospholipase A<sub>2</sub>; DEUP: diethylumbelliferyl phosphate; DRM: detergent-resistant membrane; ELISA: enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay; ER: endoplasmic reticulum; Hexa-PAF: 1-O-hexadecyl-2-acetyl-<italic>sn</italic>-glycerol-3-phospho-(N,N,N-trimethyl)-hexanolamine; LAMP-1: lysosome-associated membrane protein 1; mAb: monoclonal antibody; MAFP: methyl arachidonyl fluorophosphonate; PAF: platelet-activating factor; PBS: phosphate-buffered saline; PLA2: phospholipase A<sub>2</sub>; PVDF: polyvinylidiene fluoride; SDS: sodium dodecyl sulphate.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>VI and CS contributed to data collection and analysis and to drafting and critical revision of manuscript. CB contributed to conception and design, data collection and analysis, and manuscript writing and revision. AW contributed to conception and design and to manuscript writing. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This work was supported by the Royal Veterinary College BioVeterinary Science research project funds. We thank Professor Edward Koo for supplying 7PA2 cells.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vassar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Citron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Ab-generating enzymes: recent advances in b and g-secretase research</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-6273(00)00051-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11055423</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Georganopoulou</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Thaxton</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mufson</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirkin</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><article-title>Nanoparticle-based detection in cerebral spinal fluid of a soluble pathogenic biomarker for Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>2273</fpage><lpage>2276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0409336102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15695586</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>De Felice</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Velasco</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacor</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bigio</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jerecic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Acton</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shughrue</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen-Dodson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinney</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><article-title>Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease-type neuronal tau hyperphosphorylation induced by A&#x003b2; oligomers</article-title><source>Neurobiol Aging</source><year>2008</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1334</fpage><lpage>1347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2007.02.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17403556</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Selkoe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><article-title>Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease: a central role for amyloid</article-title><source>J Neuropath Exp Neurol</source><year>1994</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>438</fpage><lpage>447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005072-199409000-00003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8083687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chromy</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Freed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Liosatos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozovsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Trommer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Viola</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wals</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Finch</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Krafft</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><article-title>Diffusible, nonfibrillar ligands derived from A&#x003b2;<sub>1-42</sub> are potent central nervous system neurotoxins</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1998</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>6448</fpage><lpage>6453</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.95.11.6448</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9600986</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Krafft</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Finch</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><article-title>Targeting small Ab oligomers: the solution to an Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease conundrum?</article-title><source>Trends Neurosci</source><year>2001</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0166-2236(00)01749-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11250006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gouras</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tampellini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Capetillo-Zarate</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Intraneuronal beta-amyloid accumulation and synapse pathology in Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>Acta Neuropathol</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>523</fpage><lpage>541</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00401-010-0679-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20354705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Milner</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Beal</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Greengard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouras</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><article-title>Intraneuronal Alzheimer Ab<sub>42</sub> accumulates in multivesicular bodies and is associated with synaptic pathology</article-title><source>Am J Path</source><year>2002</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1869</fpage><lpage>1879</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0002-9440(10)64463-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12414533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsubuki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirotani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerard</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hama</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Saido</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><article-title>Metabolic regulation of brain abeta by neprilysin</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2001</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1550</fpage><lpage>1552</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1059946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11375493</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckman</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sambamurti</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobbs</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckman</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hersh</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><article-title>Amyloid-b peptide levels in brain are inversely correlated with insulysin activity levels in vivo</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2003</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>6221</fpage><lpage>6226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1031520100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12732730</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Halabisky</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller-Steiner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Devidze</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Grubb</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Cystatin C-cathepsin B axis regulates amyloid beta levels and associated neuronal deficits in an animal model of Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2008</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2008.10.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18957217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yamin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Connor</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McKee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Acyl peptide hydrolase degrades monomeric and oligomeric amyloid-beta peptide</article-title><source>Mol Neurodegener</source><year>2009</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>33</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1750-1326-4-33</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19627603</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease: synaptic dysfunction and A beta</article-title><source>Mol Neurodegener</source><year>2009</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>48</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1750-1326-4-48</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19930651</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Manzoni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Messa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cagnotto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cant&#x000fa;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Favero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmona</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Overcoming synthetic A beta peptide aging: a new approach to an age-old problem</article-title><source>Amyloid</source><year>2009</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13506120902879848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20536398</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Podlisny</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ostaszewski</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Squazzo</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rydell</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Teplow</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Selkoe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><article-title>Aggregation of secreted amyloid b-protein into sodium dodecyl sulfate-stable oligomers in cell culture</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1995</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>9564</fpage><lpage>9570</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.270.16.9564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7721886</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloodgood</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Selkoe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabatini</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><article-title>Natural Oligomers of the alzheimer amyloid-b protein induce reversible synapse loss by modulating an NMDA-type glutamate receptor-dependent signaling pathway</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>2866</fpage><lpage>2875</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4970-06.2007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17360908</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Munoz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepardson</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemere</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Regan</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabatini</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Selkoe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><article-title>Amyloid-&#x003b2; protein dimers isolated directly from Alzheimer&#x02019;s brains impair synaptic plasticity and memory</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>837</fpage><lpage>842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm1782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18568035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Selkoe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><article-title>Ab oligomers - a decade of discovery</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1172</fpage><lpage>1184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-4159.2006.04426.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17286590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oshima</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Morishima-Kawashima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugihara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Games</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><article-title>Accumulation of amyloid b-protein in the low-density membrane domain accurately reflects the extent of {beta}-amyloid deposition in the brain</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>2001</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>2209</fpage><lpage>2218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0002-9440(10)64693-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11395399</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kawarabayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Younkin</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen-Lang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsubara</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashe</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Younkin</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><article-title>Dimeric amyloid &#x003b2; protein rapidly accumulates in lipid rafts followed by apolipoprotein E and phosphorylated tau accumulation in the Tg2576 mouse model of Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>3801</fpage><lpage>3809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5543-03.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15084661</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liyanage</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Bickel</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lansbury</surname><given-names>PT</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Kosik</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><article-title>A detergent-insoluble membrane compartment contains A beta in vivo</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>1998</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>730</fpage><lpage>734</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm0698-730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9623986</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nabi</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>PU</given-names></name><article-title>Caveolae/raft-dependent endocytosis</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>673</fpage><lpage>677</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200302028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12771123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>Caveosomes and endocytosis of lipid rafts</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>4707</fpage><lpage>4714</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.00840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14600257</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><article-title>Lipid rafts: contentious only from simplistic standpoints</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>456</fpage><lpage>462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm1925</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16625153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pike</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><article-title>Lipid rafts: heterogeneity on the high seas</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BJ20031672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14662007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rajendran</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Lipid rafts and membrane dynamics</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1099</fpage><lpage>1102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.01681</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15764592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Motteram</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sapra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Snowden</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><article-title>Squalestatin 1, a potent inhibitor of squalene synthase, which lowers serum cholesterol in vivo</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1992</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>11705</fpage><lpage>11708</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1601846</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>London</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><article-title>Insolubility of lipids in Triton X-100: physical origin and relationship to sphingolipid/cholesterol membrane domains (rafts)</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-4157(00)00007-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11090825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maxfield</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><article-title>Role of cholesterol and lipid organization in disease</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>612</fpage><lpage>621</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature04399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16319881</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shobab</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsiung</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><article-title>Cholesterol in Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>Lancet Neurol</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>841</fpage><lpage>852</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(05)70248-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16297842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bate</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Squalestatin protects neurons and reduces the activation of cytoplasmic phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> by A&#x003b2;<sub>1-42</sub></article-title><source>Neuropharmacology</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>222</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropharm.2007.05.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17583757</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bate</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmona</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Diomede</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Squalestatin cures prion-infected neurons and protects against prion neurotoxicity</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>14983</fpage><lpage>14990</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M313061200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14754889</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Barrantes</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><article-title>Cholesterol effects on nicotinic acetylcholine receptor</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-4159.2007.04719.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17986142</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Usardi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanger</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderton</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><article-title>Membrane-bound &#x003b2;-amyloid oligomers are recruited into lipid rafts by a fyn-dependent mechanism</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>2008</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1552</fpage><lpage>1559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18096814</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Michikawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Haass</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanagisawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Amyloid precursor protein in unique cholesterol-rich microdomains different from caveolae-like domains</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1388-1981(99)00174-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10601697</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>PU</given-names></name><name><surname>Nabi</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><article-title>Distinct caveolae-mediated endocytic pathways target the Golgi apparatus and the endoplasmic reticulum</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1059</fpage><lpage>1071</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.00327</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12584249</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anfuso</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Assero</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lupo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicotra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cannavo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Strosznajder</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapisarda</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pluta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Alberghina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Amyloid b(1-42) and its b(25-35) fragment induce activation and membrane translocation of cytosolic phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> in bovine retina capillary pericytes</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbalip.2004.09.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15522829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><article-title>Amyloid-b peptide induces temporal membrane biphasic changes in astrocytes through cytosolic phospholipase A<sub>2</sub></article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2008</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>2512</fpage><lpage>2519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamem.2008.07.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18725190</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shelat</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Chalimoniuk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Strosznajder</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Simonyi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><article-title>Amyloid beta peptide and NMDA induce ROS from NADPH oxidase and AA release from cytosolic phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> in cortical neurons</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2008</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-4159.2008.05347.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18346200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lehtonen</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Holopainen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinnunen</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><article-title>Activation of phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> by amyloid b-peptides in vitro</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1996</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>9407</fpage><lpage>9414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi960148o</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8755719</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Doody</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> (PLA<sub>2</sub>) enzymes in membrane trafficking: mediators of membrane shape and function</article-title><source>Traffic</source><year>2003</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>214</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-0854.2003.00078.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12694560</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>de Figueiredo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Doody</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Polizotto</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Drecktrah</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Banta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Strang</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><article-title>Inhibition of transferrin recycling and endosome tubulation by phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> antagonists</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>47361</fpage><lpage>47370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M108508200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11585839</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grimmer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Walchli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>van Deurs</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandvig</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Golgi vesiculation induced by cholesterol occurs by a dynamin- and cPLA2-dependent mechanism</article-title><source>Traffic</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0854.2005.00258.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15634214</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>de Figueiredo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Drecktrah</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Katzenellenbogen</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Strang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><article-title>Evidence that phospholipase A2 activity is required for Golgi complex and trans Golgi network membrane tubulation</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1998</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>8642</fpage><lpage>8647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.95.15.8642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9671731</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikonen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>How cells handle cholesterol</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1721</fpage><lpage>1726</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11099405</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>CCY</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Acyl-coenzyme A:cholesterol acyltransferase</article-title><source>Annu Rev Plant Physiol Plant Mol Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>638</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ikonen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Cellular cholesterol trafficking and compartmentalization</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm2336</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18216769</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gocze</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>A cholesteryl ester hydrolase inhibitor blocks cholesterol translocation into the mitochondria of MA-10 Leydig tumor cells</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><year>1992</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>2972</fpage><lpage>2978</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1332853</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bibl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mollenhauer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Esselmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewczuk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Klafki</surname><given-names>H-W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sparbier</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Smirnov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cepek</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Trenkwalder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruther</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kornhber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiltfang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>CSF amyloid-&#x003b2;-peptides in Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease, dementia with Lewy bodies and Parkinson&#x02019;s disease dementia</article-title><source>Brain</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1177</fpage><lpage>1187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awl063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16600985</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirttila</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sersen</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Aisen</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wisniewski</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><article-title>Plasma and cerebrospinal fluid levels of amyloid beta proteins 1-40 and 1-42 in Alzheimer disease</article-title><source>Arch Neurol</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archneur.57.1.100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10634455</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Savva</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brayne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Welzel</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Shankar</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Selkoe</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ince</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><article-title>The presence of sodium dodecyl sulphate-stable A&#x003b2; dimers is strongly associated with Alzheimer-type dementia</article-title><source>Brain</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1328</fpage><lpage>1341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awq065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20403962</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherny</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Beyreuther</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Masters</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><article-title>Soluble pool of A beta amyloid as a determinant of severity of neurodegeneration in Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>Ann Neurol</source><year>1999</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>860</fpage><lpage>866</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1531-8249(199912)46:6&#x0003c;860::AID-ANA8&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-M</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10589538</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lue</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Roher</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Brachova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sue</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Beach</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurth</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rydel</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Soluble amyloid beta peptide concentration as a predictor of synaptic change in Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>1999</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>853</fpage><lpage>862</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0002-9440(10)65184-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10487842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Amyloid beta peptide alters intracellular vesicle trafficking and cholesterol homeostasis</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1998</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>13266</fpage><lpage>13271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.95.22.13266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9789077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grimm</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimm</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>Amyloid beta as a regulator of lipid homeostasis</article-title><source>Trends Mol Med</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molmed.2007.06.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17644432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>ZX</given-names></name><name><surname>Papadopoulos</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><article-title>Function of beta-amyloid in cholesterol transport: a lead to neurotoxicity</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>2002</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1677</fpage><lpage>1679</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12206998</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thomsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Roepstorff</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stahlhut</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van Deurs</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>Caveolae are highly immobile plasma membrane microdomains, which are not involved in constitutive endocytic trafficking</article-title><source>Mol Biol Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>238</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.01-06-0317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11809836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenworthy</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Polishchuk</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lodge</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirschberg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Phair</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lippincott-Schwartz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Rapid cycling of lipid raft markers between the cell surface and Golgi complex</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>541</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.153.3.529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11331304</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thelen</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rentsch</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutteck</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Heverin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Olin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>von Eckardstein</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjorkhem</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lutjohann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Brain cholesterol synthesis in mice is affected by high dose of simvastatin but not of pravastatin</article-title><source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1146</fpage><lpage>1152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/jpet.105.094136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16282522</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kirsch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckert</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><article-title>Statin effects on cholesterol micro-domains in brain plasma membranes</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><year>2003</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>843</fpage><lpage>856</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-2952(02)01654-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12628479</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Francescangeli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dreyfus</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Boila</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Freysz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Goracci</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Activities of enzymes involved in the metabolism of platelet-activating factor in neural cell cultures during proliferation and differentiation</article-title><source>Neurochem Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1299</fpage><lpage>1307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1021997300288</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9342735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Simonyi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> in the central nervous system: implications for neurodegenerative diseases</article-title><source>J Lipid Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14657205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Swayne</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Moffat</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ethier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourgeois</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rashidian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Figeys</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><article-title>Amyloid-{beta}42 signals tau hyperphosphorylation and compromises neuronal viability by disrupting alkylacylglycerophosphocholine metabolism</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2009</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>20936</fpage><lpage>20941</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0905654106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19926863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelher</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamboni-Robertson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamiel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheppard</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Silliman</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><article-title>Platelet-activating factor-induced clathrin-mediated endocytosis requires beta-arrestin-1 recruitment and activation of the p38 MAPK signalosome at the plasma membrane for actin bundle formation</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>7039</fpage><lpage>7050</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16709866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lieber</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelher</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamboni-Robertson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheppard</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mierau</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Elzi</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Silliman</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><article-title>Platelet-activating factor-mediated endosome formation causes membrane translocation of p67phox and p40phox that requires recruitment and activation of p38 MAPK, Rab5a, and phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase in human neutrophils</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2008</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>8192</fpage><lpage>8203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18523285</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolter</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandhoff</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Principles of lysosomal membrane degradation: cellular topology and biochemistry of lysosomal lipid degradation</article-title><source>Biochim Biophy Acta</source><year>2009</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>674</fpage><lpage>683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamcr.2008.09.020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohgami</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamauchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><article-title>Cholesterol sensing, trafficking, and esterification</article-title><source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.cellbio.22.010305.104656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16753029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>